<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Review of Mr. M.H.'s new notion of schism, and the vindication of it</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12986612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12986612</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 393:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Review of Mr. M.H.'s new notion of schism, and the vindication of it</title>
                  <author>Murrey, Robert, fl. 1692-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Mory ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Manuscript attribution to 'Mr. Murrey'. Wing attributes to Murray.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry, Matthew, 1662-1714. --  Schism.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVIEW OF Mr. <hi>M.H</hi>'s NEW NOTION OF SCHISM, AND THE Vindication OF IT.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>March 10. 1691/2.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Guil. Lancaſter R. P. D. Henrico Ep<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Londin. à Sacris Domeſt.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Mory</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church yard.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96210:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96210:2"/>
            <head>A Review of Mr. <hi>M. H</hi>'s New Notion of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and the Vindication of it.</head>
            <p>THE Vindicator begins with a Complaint <hi>of the unhappy Flames which have been kindled amongſt us about matters of Church Government, and Worſhip.</hi> And tells us further,<note place="margin">Vindic. p. <hi>1:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That he muſt be as great an Enemy, that would not contribute his utmoſt to the extinguiſhing of them.</hi> And ſo far I confeſs we agree with him; but whether Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his Vindicator be the ſole Extinguiſher, is a Queſtion that may deſerve ſome further debate. More has been ſaid to the former already, than he is at leiſure to anſwer; and therefore I ſhall only add one thing at preſent, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe who have learnt out the firſt occaſion of Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Book, tell me, That it was to ſatisfy the Scruples of ſome particular perſons, whom his Followers would have allured and drawn into his Conventicle. It was not to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the differences amongſt ſo many learned Men as are engaged in this Controverſie. Neither was it to inform the world concerning that mighty ſecret, <hi>the true cauſe of our Animoſities,</hi> viz. <hi>That all other wars and fightings proceed from our luſts, that war in our minds.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>James</hi> was aware of that, long before Mr. <hi>H.</hi> And as for his <hi>New Notion of Schiſm,</hi> [the breach of Love] it was calculated for the Ladies, and the great deſign of his Book was to make two Female Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes. Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Attempt was indeed <hi>modeſt,</hi> becauſe this was all he aimed at, but this <hi>Vindicator</hi> abuſes him, by aſcribing too much to him. To place him in the Chair of Controverſy, and make him the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining Oracle over thoſe two learned Partles, the <hi>Churchmen</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is enough to make any Man's head giddy, if he be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely confident; and is ſo plain an Abuſe upon Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> as muſt needs put him (if he be not very ſtupid) quite out of countenance. Eſpecially if he does but remember what little ſucceſs his Book had with thoſe for whoſe ſake it was written. For if it were not able to unſettle the minds of one or two of the weaker Sex, ſurely he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect it to controul the ſentiments of wiſe and learned Men. And therefore it was an Abuſe upon Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and an high piece of Arrogance in the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> to make ſo many his <hi>Pupils:</hi> as if all the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> underſtood nothing at all either of the <hi>Duty of Charity,</hi> or the <hi>Cauſe of Animoſities,</hi> or the <hi>Nature of Schiſm,</hi> till Mr. <hi>H.</hi> firſt informed them, and ſhewed 'em their miſtake.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Churchmen</hi> are abſolutely condemned (if this <hi>Gentleman</hi> be Judge) for <hi>impoſing unneceſſary ſuſpected terms of Communion meer Trifles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vindic. p. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>under fevere Penalties; Fines, Impriſonments, Exile,</hi> &amp;c. And certainly they were extremely to blame, if all this were done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and no body reclaimed; as it ſeems his <hi>experience has ſufficiently convinced him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 2.</note> But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96210:3"/>
other Mens experience makes 'em of a contrary Opinion, who, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the conſtancy which this Man boaſts of, found the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> generally ſo good natur'd and flexible, that during the little time the Laws were executed, a dangerous Faction was broken, and more done towards <hi>bringing Engliſh Proteſtants to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> than ten thouſand ſuch little blue Books as theſe of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Vindicator</hi> will be able to effect. The good <hi>Engliſh Proteſtents,</hi> tho' a little fond of <hi>Novelty;</hi> yet when once the <hi>Teachers</hi> were ſuppreſt, whoſe intereſt it was to <hi>bellow</hi> againſt all Eſtabliſhmets, ſoon came into the Church: and without any fear of thoſe <hi>Mormos</hi> wherewith they had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly terrified, did readily and chearfully join with us in full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. And perhaps the <hi>Teachers</hi> themſelves might have learnt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> by this time, through the execution of thoſe penal Acts, as well as their Predeceſſors and Brethren did before 'em. For the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> are not ſuch abſolute deſpiſers of the things of this world, as never to look about 'em for ſecular advantage, tho' not ſo much I hope as to debauch their Conſciences, yet enough to open their Eyes. And therefore when they ſaw themſelves deprived of thoſe goodly <hi>Tythe-Barns</hi> which had ſo plentifully fed them; and that the <hi>Government</hi> was firmly ſetled which turned them out; and withal knew they ſhould have ſpoiled one another, if they had all <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticled:</hi> they thought it high time to make further Inquiry into the terms of our Communion; and finding them at laſt to be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they imagined, many of the ableſt and beſt thought fit to comply.<note place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> More I am ſure they were than either <hi>five or ſix;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he needs not upbraid us with that number being departed from us: it being no wonder if five or ſix <hi>Clergymen</hi> in all <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſo ill preferred, and ſo little deſerving; as to find it their intereſt to go over to the <hi>Conventicles,</hi> upon the opening of a <hi>Toleration,</hi> where leſs Learning will ſerve; and they will be much better paid, and thought of, than we could find them worthy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ib.</note>Nor are the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> any more <hi>the Support of our Trifles,</hi> than the <hi>Penal Ordinances</hi> formerly were of theirs, (I mean, the <hi>Directory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>) witneſs that 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1645. <hi>That if any Perſon or Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhall at any time, or times hereafter, uſe, or cauſe the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Book of Common-Prayer to be uſed in any Church, or Chappel, or publick Place of Worſhip; or in any private Place, or Family, within the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>or Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>or Port and Town of</hi> Berwick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>every ſuch Perſon ſo offending therein, ſhall for the firſt Offence, pay the Sum of Five Pounds lawfull Engliſh Money; for the ſecond Offence, Ten Pounds; and for the third, ſhall ſuffer One whole Years Impriſonment, without Bail or Mainpriſe.</hi> More of this kind may be ſeen in that <hi>Ordinance,</hi> but from this it is evident, 1. That our <hi>Ceremoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> did not fall <hi>into ſuch Contempt,</hi> as the <hi>Vindicator</hi> ſuppoſes, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>when the Enforcements were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away,</hi> that being done by a former <hi>Ordinance, Jan.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1644. for if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96210:3"/>
they had, there had been no occaſion for theſe ſevere <hi>Penalties.</hi> 2. That <hi>Enforcements</hi> were neceſſary to ſupport the <hi>Directory.</hi> And laſtly, That they were neceſſary to preſerve it from Contempt, for thus it was ordained, <hi>Aug.</hi> 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1645. <hi>That what Perſon ſoever ſhall with intent to bring the ſaid Directory into contempt or neglect, or to raiſe oppoſition againſt it, preach, write, print, or cauſe to be written, or printed, any thing in the deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or depraving of the ſaid Book, or any thing therein contained, or any part thereof, ſhall loſe and forfeit for every ſuch Offence, ſuch a Sum of Money, as ſhall at the time of his Conviction be thought fit to be impoſed upon him, by thoſe before whom he ſhall have his Tryal: provided it be not leſs than Five Pounds, nor exceeding the Sum of Fifty Pounds.</hi> In this Act they have an Eye to thoſe that might preach it into Contempt. So that it was not of ſuch value in the Eyes of their own Miniſters, but ſeveral of thoſe who were at that time in poſſeſſion of the Pulpits might poſſibly fall away, and preach againſt it. And as for the Service of the Church, Men were ſo far from totally neglecting it, that after Ten Years ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> they found it neceſſary to diſcourage it. <hi>He that uſed the Book of Common-Prayer was to be adjudged ſcandalous, ejected out of his Living, and expelled the whole Pariſh, for fear leſt he ſhould make an Intereſt againſt the new Modes.</hi> So that here it ſeems <hi>Fines, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments,</hi> and <hi>Exile,</hi> were found as neceſſary to ſupport the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> and <hi>Independant Worſhip,</hi> as the <hi>Church-Liturgy;</hi> and <hi>People</hi> were then as true to the latter, as either Mr. <hi>H.</hi> or his <hi>Vindicator</hi> can be to the former.</p>
            <p>But why are Penal Laws only <hi>the Props of controverted Ceremonies?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vind. p. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The Papiſts, as well as other Diſſenters, were obnoxious to the ſame Laws, as this Gentleman may well remember, ſince they joined their Intereſt and Malice to have them repeal'd; and yet, I hope, he will not ſay that the Papiſts were ever puniſh'd for not complying with Ceremonies: nor can it be reaſonably affirm'd concerning their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Sufferers, unleſs frequenting the Church, and receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, diſturbing Miniſters, and holding Conventicles, Things which the Penal Laws do principally regard, are no more but Ceremonies: <hi>i. e.</hi> in the language of this modeſt Gentleman, <hi>all Trifles,</hi> pag. 2. and <hi>Religious Impertinencies,</hi> pag. 13.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble my ſelf with giving further Reaſons for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thoſe Laws, nor to ſhew him that Religion has been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by ſuch under moſt Chriſtian Emperors; for having ſhewn it to be the practice of their own R. Parliament, and <hi>Oliver,</hi> I ſuppoſe it is <hi>inſtar omnium;</hi> and will go farther with this Vindicator to make it authentick, than all the examples from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to our own Age.</p>
            <p>It will be more proper for us to enquire into Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s peaceable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and how he has managed <hi>the Weapon (viz.</hi> the Notion of Schiſm) <hi>which he lately wreſted out of the Gladiator's hand,</hi> Vind. p. 4. it being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a matter of no ſmall importance; for if his account be ſo clear as this Gent. makes it, all Church Diſcipline is out of doors; their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96210:4"/>
own as well as ours: and a Man may appeal from the Stool of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to the Quakers Meeting-houſe, without any guilt, if breach of Communion be no Schiſm, as theſe Gent. alledge: But if his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count be not clear, or his Notion defective, or a falſe ſignification impoſed upon the word Schiſm, then he has <hi>acquitted no body:</hi> the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, moderate,</hi> and <hi>peaceable,</hi> muſt come to Church ſtill; and only the worſt ſort of <hi>Bigotts</hi> remain in the Conventicle. The management of this buſineſs being therefore of ſuch grand importance, upon both accounts, let us ſee how the little Champion has weilded his weapon.</p>
            <p>We have ſome reaſon in the firſt place to queſtion the peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his deſign: for the Notion it ſelf being contrived to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and juſtifie Separation; I am afraid the laſt reſult, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it, will not be Peace. Suppoſe a Man ſhould introduce the ſame Doctrine into the State, and tell People that it is lawful to act in ſeparate Bodies; That they need not own the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor ſubmit to King <hi>William</hi>'s Laws; they may govern themſelves by a diſtinct Politie of their own; they may be for King <hi>James,</hi> or a Commonwealth, according to their ſeveral apprehenſions: The Nature and Rights of Government are things <hi>dark,</hi> and <hi>obſcure;</hi> and withal ſo <hi>trivial,</hi> and <hi>light,</hi> that it is not material what Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or Perſon prevails: ſo that <hi>diverſity of Opinion, Judgment, or Apprehenſion, cannot be call'd, or lookt upon, in it ſelf, a thing criminal,</hi> Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Enqu. p.</hi> 7. provided they ſtill preſerve Charity. King <hi>William</hi> will never be ſo cruel as <hi>to hang 'em, only becauſe their heads are not exactly of his ſize,</hi> ib. p. 19. I fancy thoſe who are at the helm would ſcarce be perſuaded that his deſigns were peaceable, tho' he ſhould ſecond this Diſcourſe with the moſt earneſt perſuaſions to Charity. And if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> or any body elſe, ſhould attempt to debauch 'em with ſuch anarchical Principles, he would be reckoned a mover of Sedition, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a healer of Breaches; and perhaps meet with ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, as the beſt Vindicator he has would not know what to ſay to. And his attempt is not much better with relation to the Church; it being not eaſy to conceive, how he that ſets People at liberty to divide and break into Parties, (as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> does,) can be a promoter of Peace: for if it be lawful for People to ſeparate, and break into Parties, there will be no longer any Union, than while their Intereſts, and perhaps their Humors, as well as their Principles, oblige them to it. When the ſeveral Religious Intereſts once come to interfere, the Parties themſelves will fall out; and while they are ſtriving for the maſtery, not only ruin the Eccleſiaſtical, but likewiſe endanger the Civil Peace.</p>
            <p>Of this we had ſufficient experience in the former Confuſions, when the moderate, as well as the fierce, were engaged in the Cauſe, and every Man lent a Coal to enflame the Controverſy. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and peaceable Presbyterian, one that had obtained that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96210:4"/>
among all that knew him, could nevertheleſs tell the world in his Epiſtle, <hi>That Churches were not to be own'd, after the independent m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>de: for it would lay the foundation of ſtrife and diviſion in the Kingdom, to have two ways of Church-Government, which may agree with ſome Machiavilian, but no Chriſtian Policy,</hi> &amp;c. And the Parliament was applauded by another moderate Gent. <hi>Becauſe they endeavoured to fence the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard with a ſetled Militia, and then to gather out the Malignants as Stones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cotton</hi> upon the firſt of the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and to make a Winepreſs therein for the ſqueezing of Delinquents.</hi> And the mild Independent is the very ſame, when he comes to be upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. <hi>Good Kings ought to put upon their People Laws, and ſtrait binding to the Purity of Religion, and the Worſhip of God. It is not an Impeachment to their Chriſtian Liberty, (as the Anabaptiſts do vainly talk) but an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to their Beauty, making their Necks comely, as with a Chain of Gold. They were not only to chide the Money-changers, but to whip them away, and overthrow the very Tables, leſt they ſhould recover their Trade again.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon <hi>is begun to fall before the Ark, his Head is off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bridge.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but let not ſo much as the ſtump remain.</hi> And if the like diſorders ſhould happen again, I am very much afraid leſt theſe two charitable Gentlemen, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his Vindicator, would become as great Incendiaries, as any of the former. (Mr. <hi>H.</hi> already is not without grains of malice, too often ſprinkled among his Charity:) And as for the Vindicator he is all o're ſpite, and from the beginning of his Book throughout, by his falſe and malicious Suggeſtions, he breaks the Laws of Charity, and ſhews himſelf a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> according to his <hi>own Notion.</hi> Nay, at laſt, when he draws towards a Concluſion, leſt his Readers ſhould not have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his many <hi>ſpiteful Reflections,</hi> he takes care to put them in mind, with a great deal of boaſting Inſolence, <hi>how roughly,</hi> i. e. <hi>how maliciouſly</hi> he has treated <hi>T. W.</hi> p. 90. From ſuch Men who are ſo uncharitable, even while they pretend the contrary, and ſuch <hi>Notions</hi> which intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Anarchy, Confuſion,</hi> and <hi>Licentiouſneſs,</hi> little Peace is to be expected, whatever is deſign'd. We know it is too much the cuſtom of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians, to cry <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> even when they mean nothing leſs: and every Man that has but the ſenſe of the <hi>Kid</hi> in the <hi>Fable,</hi> will eaſily perceive in the preſent Caſe, that altho' it may be the voice of the <hi>Goat</hi> which we hear, yet it is really the <hi>Wolf</hi> that ſtands at the door.</p>
            <p>Nor is Mr. <hi>H.</hi> more unfortunate in his Methods of peace, than he is in the deſcription of Schiſm. It is certainly the lateſt that has been coined, and perhaps the wildeſt that ever any man father'd upon the Scriptures, or offer'd to ſet up in contradiction to the received opinion of Sixteen hundred years.</p>
            <p>He tells us p. 15. <hi>that Schiſm is an uncharitable diſtance, diviſion, or alienation of affections, among thoſe who are called Chriſtians; and agree in the fundamentals of Religion, occaſioned by their different apprehenſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout little things.</hi> From which deſcription of Schiſm (if I underſtand it right) theſe following particulars may be regularly drawn. Firſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96210:5"/>
of all, That he that was never truly admitted into the Chriſtian Church, may be guilty of Schiſm if he be called a Chriſtian. For Mr. <hi>H.</hi> tells us that Schiſm is among thoſe who are called Chriſtians. Secondly, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Hereticks in fundamentals are no Schiſmaticks, for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſuppoſes that where there is a Schiſm both parties muſt agree in the fundamentals of Religion. So that the groſſeſt Hereticks are excus'd from Schiſm, which falls heavieſt upon thoſe who differ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſmalleſt things, which is all one as if he ſhould have ſaid, the leſs the fault, is the greater the crime. For inſtance, If people divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e from the Church becauſe they will not own the divinity of our Saviour, or the doctrine of the Trinity; theſe people are no Schiſmaticks, becauſe they differ in fundamentals<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen of his own Congregation ſhould happen to fall out, and carry at a diſtance becauſe they could not agree about the upper end of a Seat in Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Meeting-houſe, this would be the horrid crime of Schiſm, the <hi>Arch rebel againſt God,</hi> according to every branch of the aforeſaid deſcription. Thirdly, Another inference to be made from it is, that alienation of affections is Schiſm, but a diviſion, and alienation of Communion, is not. And conſequently no one can charge another with Schiſm, except he be able to look into his heart; It being impoſſible to know according to this deſcription, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are really Schiſmaticks, if they profeſs themſelves to be in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, except we could make enquiry into the ſecrets of their hearts, and diſcover every thing tranſacted there. And on the contrary, people may be the greateſt Schiſmaticks under the outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Charity, and yet no body can accuſe them with that fault. If theſe propoſitions be duly inferr'd from Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s deſcription, I believe he will not find many that will join with the Vindicator in his commendation of it.</p>
            <p>And as for the clearneſs he talks of, there are ſo many ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities ſtill remaining, as perhaps may trouble another inquirer to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to us. As 1ſt, Whether the uncharitable diſtance muſt really be among thoſe who are Chriſtians, or them that are none? for people many times call things by wrong names. Secondly, What he means by fundamentals of Religion? Whether, <hi>ſalutis,</hi> or <hi>theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicae veritatis?</hi> Whether thoſe that are ſo to every man in his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate capacity? Or thoſe which are the fundamentals of Church Communion? Thirdly, What he means by little things? Whether diviſion of affection about all manner of little things be Schiſm? Or only about Eccleſiaſtical little things, the <hi>trifles and Religious imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies</hi> which the Vindicator ſo frequently deſpiſes? The clearing of theſe particulars had been of no ſmall importance in this controverſy, and therefore if the deſcriber had been pleaſed to have explained them to us, his notion might have been abundantly clearer than it is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96210:6"/>But perhaps the Vindicator does not take this deſcription for the clear account; and that may be the reaſon why he minces and alters it himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 80. Whether for the better or the worſe I ſhall not ſay. Perhaps the ſignification of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> does the buſineſs; and <hi>the import of thoſe words</hi> is the only thing of which <hi>he has given us a clear account.</hi> Vind. p. 4. Let us therefore take a review of that enquiry; and ſee whether there be any juſt occaſion for ſuch mighty boaſting.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>that there is but one Scripture in the old Teſtament, relating to this affair, viz. Numb.</hi> 11.26. When I obſerve that if this Text be nothing to the purpoſe, then there is none, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently either the Jewiſh Church was in no danger of Schiſm, at leaſt wiſe not infeſted with it: Or elſe the inſpired writings are ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly defective; that have not one word relating to it. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore it is to be noted that in this text there is no mention of any <hi>diviſion or alienation of affections;</hi> and therefore unleſs it is to be found in ſome other place, (which, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> denies) there is not one old Teſtament Schiſmatick in the whole Bible. Or laſtly, if there were any ſuch guilt among them, it could not be of the ſame nature with that which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> determines to be the only Schiſm among Chriſtians. But if all or moſt of theſe conſequences be falſe, or abſurd; they will give us ſome occaſion to ſuſpect the ingenuity, and truth of his firſt account.</p>
            <p>As to the inſtance he gives us about <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> propheſying in the Camp; it is methinks extreamly forreign to this controverſy. They were to bear the weight of government with <hi>Moſes</hi> under God, and to aſſure both <hi>Moſes</hi> and the people of their Commiſſion from Heaven, had the miraculous impulſe of propheſie before the Congregation, as a full and certain evidence of their newly received authority. This prophecying was intended for a ſign, as appears <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24. and therefore how either the Enquirer or Vindicator can make it <hi>a repraeſentutive of their preachings,</hi> I cannot imagine. Theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Theodoretus ad quaeſtionem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denam evenirit Septuaginta ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui ut praefecti ſunt prophetaſſe poſtea vero mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime (juxta Graecam ſcilicet verſionem) reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondet <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> — hoc autem <hi>ſeu Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernationis judican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> munere inquit Theod.</hi> ornati ſunt Septuag. illi &amp; ut conſtaret populo divinum munus illos &amp; conſecutos quaedam statim praedix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>runt. Quod quidem receptior. Magiſtrorum ſenſui per quam conſonum. <hi>Selden. de Synod. l. 2. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> Prophets were inſpired to be the Rulers of the Nation, which I hope theſe Gentlemen will not as yet pretend to. They were all acted by a conſtraining impulſe which ſurely is not the caſe of our Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts. If the Spirit ſhould ſo reſt upon them, that they could not forbear preaching; he were abundantly worſe <hi>than</hi> Joſhua <hi>that ſhould complain to my Lord</hi> Moſes, tho it were in the Camp, or the ſtable. <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> were two of the Seventy deſigned for govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (I wiſh theſe Gentlemen could afford as good a proof of their Authority to preach.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96210:7"/>
            <p>They were left behind in the<note n="†" place="margin">Duo remanent Eld. &amp; Medad non imperii neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentes ſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militate ſubmiſſi dum ſe honore arbitrantur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignos Hieron. Ep. ad Fabiol.</note> Camp, and there the Spirit reſted upon them; which was a ſufficient proof to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that God had admitted them to the government, altho abſent from the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: Eſpecially conſidering that they were of them that were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſo that he might not exclude them. And therefore Mr. <hi>H.</hi> does impertinently alledge in this caſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32. <hi>That the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Theod. quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Eldad.</hi> &amp; <hi>Medad.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; ipſeque reſpondet eos fuiſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets.</hi> Neither can he find that any of them ſcrupled, or refuſed, that <hi>Religious impertinence</hi> of coming to the Tabernacle; or to join with the reſt in full communion, which had been the moſt eminent circumſtance in the whole affair to his purpoſe. Nay laſtly, the buſineſs was chiefly ſecular, and diſtinct from that which did more peculiarly belong to the Eccleſiaſtical body: and therefore there could be nothing in this caſe to illuſtrate the buſineſs of Schiſm.</p>
            <p>But why is this the only Text that occurs in the old Teſtament? Perſons of far greater learning, and authority in the Church, have made uſe of ſeveral others; I hope you will ſay not impertinently when I give you their names. That of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> has been thought by ſome not wholly unfit to illuſtrate the nature of Schiſm: they taking occaſion from the infirmity of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to leſſen his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,<note place="margin">Ainſ. in loc.</note> and to raiſe their own; (as Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi>) intending no doubt to draw the people from him. And therefore their ſin is called Aemulation by <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> and by him applyed to the latter Schiſm of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as Schiſm is uſually the child and companion of Aemulation, which made the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Schiſmaticks, and their Leaders to break communion with, and to rebel againſt their lawful Presbyters, as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> did againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> themſelves are taught ſubjection to the Prieſts, and Levites; leſt God ſhould do to them as he did to <hi>Miriam, Deut.</hi> 24.8, 9. inflict the ſame puniſhment for the like fault. From which reaſoning in St. <hi>Clemens,</hi> it is plain he reckoned Schiſm in the Church, to be like Sedition in the State, ſomething more than barely a breach of Charity.<note place="margin">Vid. opt. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> That of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> was urged by the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts your Predeceſſors againſt the Catholicks, who did not diſown the way of arguing, but only ſet the inſtances right by comparing <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> with the <hi>Donatiſs,</hi> and the Church with <hi>Moſes</hi> whom they withſtood. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not think ſo ſlightly of this inſtance, when he alledged it in his 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> againſt the Gnoſtic Schiſmaticks; who led captive ſilly women laden with ſins,<note place="margin">Vid. Hammon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in loc. Clem. Rom. p. <hi>120.</hi> Optat. cont. Parm. l. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>167.</hi>
               </note> who did not only break charity, but reſiſted the truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. That of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> is thought fit to be uſed by St. <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 11. concerning the Gnoſtic Separatiſts, <hi>v.</hi> 9. By St. <hi>Clemens</hi> againſt the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> By <hi>Optatus</hi> againſt the Donatiſts, calling 'em their wretched Maſters, the dividers of the people, the Maſters of the firſt Schiſm, the Schiſmatics, <hi>viz.</hi> your Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96210:8"/>
And yet to Mr. <hi>M. H. it does not occur.</hi> Theſe inſtances and many more of the like ſort produced by St. <hi>Clemens,</hi> and others, as that of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau, Joſeph</hi> and his Brethren, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the quarrelling <hi>Hebrew,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>tho not all of them deſigned to run upon all four,</hi> as the Vindicator ſpeaks <hi>p.</hi> 40. Yet being alledged againſt Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics, are intended ſome to ſhew the miſchiefs of Aemulation and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which are always the ingredients of Schiſm; Others more nearly to ſignify the pernicious nature and heinous guilt, of making parties, in oppoſition to lawful authority; or to contend with them that are truly our Superiors in the Church, and by this way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we may learn, that according to the ſentiments of thoſe primitive worthies, Schiſmatics are guilty of Aemulation, which muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be betwixt divided parties, and Intereſts, and conſequently where there is Schiſm there is likewiſe a breach of Communion. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that it is in oppoſition to our Eccleſiaſtical Governors. This muſt neceſſarily be the Senſe of thoſe who uſe this way of reaſoning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but neither of theſe things could be imputed to <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad;</hi> and therefore their notion of Schiſm could not be the ſame with Mr. <hi>M. H</hi>'s. and that is (I ſuppoſe) the reaſon why he neither makes uſe of their Inſtances, nor they of his.</p>
            <p>By his exception againſt thoſe Texts, which <hi>obliged the Jews to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>only in one place,</hi> viz. <hi>at</hi> Jeruſalem.<note place="margin">Mod. Enq. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And to offer only upon that Altar; a man will be apt to conclude him extreamly ignorant in the Religion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the myſtical reaſonings upon which it was built. To ſay nothing as yet of our own, how far it has any relation to it. He ſuppoſes firſt of all, that the <hi>Jews were bound to worſhip at one place, viz</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſecondly, that <hi>this obligation is vacated by that Goſpel rule which wills us to pray every where,</hi> Enq. p. 3. Which two things if they be true (as he ſuppoſes) then the Male <hi>Jews</hi> never prayed at all, but when they came to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> 3 times a Year, at the Feaſt of Unleavened bread, the Feaſt of Weeks, and the Feaſt of Tabernacles; which methinks is a very ſcandalous account of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> devotion, but the whole aſſertion is falſe. The <hi>Jews</hi> had their Proſeuchae every where without the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their Synagogues within, the Tabernacle was at <hi>Shiloh,</hi> there was an Altar at Mount <hi>Ebal; Samuel</hi> ſacrificed at <hi>Miſpeh,</hi> and in <hi>Zuph,</hi> in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and in <hi>Bethlehem; Elijah</hi> at Mount <hi>Carmel.</hi> They had their daily Sacrifices of the Sabbaths, and of the new Moons. Nor is it eaſy to imagine that they ſhould all go once a week from the moſt diſtant places to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> unleſs they had very little buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at home, or were extraordinary Travellers. They had their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuchae and Synagogues for publick worſhip, and their private devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which might be ſaid any where. All inferior Altars and places of worſhip were in communion with the ſupream one; and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who did legally and regularly communicate at them, were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96210:9"/>
underſtood to partake thereby of that one Altar, and therefore if <hi>the Synagogues be certainly the patterns of our Chriſtian Aſſemblies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> pray Sir aſſign us an Altar with which we muſt hold communion, which will ſurely be that of the Biſhop according to the ſentiments of the primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Nor was the precept of offering only upon one Altar ſo purely ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial, but that it was founded upon very rational, tho myſtical principles; according to tne ſenſe and interpretation of the Helleniſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Jews,</hi> the end of it was to diſtinguiſh the <hi>Segullah,</hi> or peculiar people; thoſe that were in ſpecial Union, and Covenant with the Deity, from thoſe that were not or had broken off from it.</p>
            <p>The principle and archetypal head of that Union was God himſelf, to whom none but the <hi>Segullah</hi> were united. The <hi>Segullah</hi> were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Sacraments, which were the legal Symbols and Ratifications of that Union<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the High Prieſt was the repreſentative of the Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typal head, ſo that none could be in Union with God, unleſs united to the High Prieſt: None united to the High Prieſt unleſs they did partake of that Altar where he offered, and thoſe which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant upon it. And therefore the Sacraments belonging to Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Altars, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Samaria</hi> and its dependents, erected in oppoſition to that of the true High Prieſt, did not unite them to God, neither conſequently were the Worſhippers at that Altar to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned of the <hi>Segullah,</hi> or peculiar people; but rather as the Altar of <hi>Samariah</hi> was againſt the Altar of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo were the <hi>Samaritan</hi> worſhippers againſt the true <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Chriſtians I hope are as well united to the Father and the Son as ever the <hi>Jews</hi> were. They are as truly the <hi>Segullah,</hi> or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people, and the ways of tranſacting that Union by the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Sacraments and Prieſthood as certain. And therefore have been maintained by the Primitive Fathers and Mr. <hi>Dodwell,</hi> upon the ſame manner of reaſonings which the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed.<note place="margin">See his one Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if this way of reaſoning be good, there are two other Texts in the old Teſtament, which will help to diſcover the notion of Schiſm; one relating to that Altar of the Tribes beyond <hi>Jordan, Joſhuah</hi> 22. the other to thoſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Nor is any thing in this fooliſh paragraph concluſive againſt theſe reaſonings, which it was either deſigned to Anſwer, or elſe it is very impertinent. No man ever denied that Chriſtians might pray every where, in any Kingdom, City, or place whereſoever they come, only we deſire it may be remembred that the Jews had the ſame liberty. And if private Chriſtians may pay their devotion to Almighty God any where, in the Church, in their Families, in their Cloſets, in the Fields, and any other place; they certainly have the liberty <hi>to pray every where:</hi> and yet this cannot <hi>vacate the obligation of holding communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with one Altar,</hi> for the Jews themſelves had the very ſame liberty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96210:10"/>
while they were under that obligation. If Chriſtians have a liberty to build their Oratories, and Churches for the public ſervice of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, whereſoever they pleaſe, without being excluded, or confined to any place; they may certainly fulfil <hi>the Goſpel rule of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every where,</hi> and yet this will be no prejudice to their holding Communion with the Biſhop of the Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>For if Uniting our Selves to a Congregation in communion with the Biſhop, be any violation of that <hi>Goſpel rule;</hi> becauſe they meet in a particular Church and the Biſhop lives in a particular City; I cannot ſee how Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his Vindicator, will acquit themſelves from the ſame guilt, whoſe Congregations are confined to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar houſe, or a particular ſtable. Their people muſt be with their Teacher where ever he aſſembles, ours with their Prieſt at the place of publick worſhip: And if we are to be condemned for breaking this Goſpel rule, I can ſee no reaſon why Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his followers ſhould plead not guilty.</p>
            <p>'Tis true we are not confined to that one Altar at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the obligation was taken away by the authority of our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.21. in his anſwer to the woman of <hi>Samaria. The hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father:</hi> Not that it was forbidden to worſhip at either of thoſe places, in the times of the Goſpel; but the true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Evangelical worſhip ſhould not be confin'd to either, the Jewiſh diſpenſation was to be laid aſide, and a more ſpiritual one introduc'd; the literal to be exchanged for the myſtical <hi>Iſrael. The hour cometh and now is when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father, in ſpirit and in truth, for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him. God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit, and in truth.</hi> v. 23, 24. That which under the Goſpel was to anſwer the High Prieſthood, ſhould not be confined to one City, or one Mountain, and that which correſponded to the worſhip ſhe then diſcourſed of, namely the ſharing in the ſame Sacrifices, ſhould be henceforth ſo ſpiritual, and free, that all people might partake and communicate in it, however diſtant their reſidences were, which they could not do before. This, as it is the genuine ſenſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours diſcourſe, ſo methinks theſe following obſervations may be drawn from it. 1ſt, That there is ſomething under the Goſpel, which does really correſpond to that ſolemn worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for it being that only which the woman diſcourſed of to our Saviour; his anſwer muſt neceſſarily bear a relation to it. And therefore the worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſpiritual worſhip, were a type, and antitype one of another. So that as all the Jews did communicate at one Altar, in the like manner Chriſtians muſt partake in the ſame ſpiritual Sacrifices. 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, That as the deſign of thoſe anniverſaries was to keep 'em in the ſame Communion; ſo that ſpiritual worſhip here ſpoken of is for the very ſame end. 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, That as the Prieſthood and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96210:11"/>
Altar were the principles of unity amongſt them, ſo there is a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Prieſthood and Altar, which do the ſame thing among us. 4<hi rend="sup">thly</hi>, That as he who broke the communion with that Altar, was off from the Church of the Jews; So he who ſeparates from ours is divided from the body of Chriſtians. And 5<hi rend="sup">thly</hi>, That as in one caſe they forfeited the Jewiſh priviledges, ſo they do likewiſe the Chriſtian in another. Theſe two laſt obſervations were included in the diſcourſe, as is plain from our Saviours confining Salvation to the Jews: For the concluſion bearing a relation to all the premiſes, the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers under the Goſpel, are parallel with thoſe under the Law. And therefore as Salvation was of the Jews, and belonged only to thoſe who did worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> ſo likewiſe Salvation under the Goſpel, muſt for the ſame reaſon, be confined to the ſpiritual Worſhippers; that is to thoſe who are united to the one Chriſtian Altar, as the Jews were to that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and by the ſame parity of reaſon all others excluded. So that I can ſee no cauſe why Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhould conclude, that <hi>the binding of the Jews to communicate at one Altar, is nothing to us.</hi> For if we are under a parallel obligation to do the ſame thing, to preſerve that unity in the ſpirit, which they did in the letter. If the Jewiſh Church was a repreſentation of the Chriſtian, and their Altar, and Prieſthood a type of ours: Surely ſomething is to be learned by us from what they did. Unity and Communion is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a Ceremony, and Schiſm which is the breach of it, is I ſuppoſe the ſame thing in the Chriſtian, that it was under the Jewiſh OEconomy. St. <hi>Paul</hi> is pleaſed to argue from the Jewiſh precedents, for the right of maintenance; that they <hi>who miniſter about holy things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ive of the things of the Temple, they which wait at the Altar ſhould be partakers with the Altar,</hi> and that <hi>even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dodw.</hi> one Altar.</note> Plainly ſuppoſing that our Clergy anſwers the Levitical Prieſthood, our Churches their Temple, our Communion Table their Altar, and that what was thought equal in their caſe in the proviſions of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is for that very reaſon to be taken for ordained in the caſe of the Goſpel Miniſtry;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dod.</hi> one Alt. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> there being no other Evangelical ordinance. And why we may not argue from Jewiſh precedents in the caſe of Schiſm, having the Apoſtles example for it in caſe the of maintenance, I cannot underſtand. St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues from the Aaronical, to the Melchizedechian Prieſthood; from the Prieſthood of mortal men, to the immortal Prieſthood of the Son of God; from the rights of the literal, to thoſe of the myſtical Altar; and tells us that the Law was a Schoolmaſter to bring us to Chriſt; and yet Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> is ſo apt a Scholar, that in one of the moſt eminent and principal inſtances, he can find nothing to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sigon: de Rep. Heb.</hi> l. 2. c. 8.</note>
               <hi>The Synagogues</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> allows <hi>were the patterns of Chriſtian Aſſemblies, but not the Temple,</hi> p. 3. I ſhould rather have thought the Synagogues,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96210:12"/>
and Temple too; eſpecially if we believe the account which <hi>Sigonius</hi> gives; in which he is follow'd by other learned men; <hi>viz.</hi> That Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues were firſt erected in the time of the Captivity, that they who wanted the Temple to pray and teach in might have ſome place like the Temple, in which they might aſſemble to perform that ſort of duty. Now Mr. <hi>H.</hi> tells us that Synagogues were the patterns of Chriſtian Aſſemblies: <hi>Sigonius</hi> that they were like and inſtead of the Temple, and therefore any man would believe that the Chriſtian Aſſemblies and the Temple being both like the Synagogue, were alſo like one another: and conſequently the Temple as well as the Synagogue the pattern of Chriſtian Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>But I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es not allow the Temple to be a pattern for fear of the Altar, and the <hi>Vindicator</hi> we find is for <hi>Prophets, rather than Prieſts,</hi> p. 41. <hi>The Prieſts</hi> (he tells us) <hi>were engag'd principally in the Ceremonial, but the Prophets in the Moral part of Worſhip; which was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the Mind of God to the People, and preſſing them to Obedience: and it is to this rather, than the Prieſtly Office, that a Goſpel Miniſter ſucceeds, ib.</hi> So that according to this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> Preaching is the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of a Chriſtian Miniſter, and Prayers and Sacraments, which are the work of a Prieſt, are to paſs for <hi>Cyphers,</hi> and <hi>Religious Impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> Our <hi>Author</hi> might have conſidered, that the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> ſo long as it laſted, did accompany the Prieſthood; and when at laſt the Scribes ſucceeded in the place of the Prophets, <hi>Ezra</hi> himſelf was both Prieſt and Scribe, and accordingly prepared his heart to teach Gods Precepts and Judgments in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ezr. 7.10. and <hi>(the Prophecy that ſometimes accompanied the High Prieſthood)</hi> ſeems to outlive all the reſt, as appears from the inſtance of <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> who foretold the death of our Saviour; <hi>And,</hi> as the Apoſtle declares, <hi>this ſpake he not of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but being High Prieſt that ſame year, he propheſied,</hi> John 11.51. So that Prophecy and Prieſthood being united in the ſame perſon, if the Goſpel Miniſter ſucceeds to the one, why not to the other? or if he ſucceeds to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prophets, why not to ſuch as were Prieſts, as well as Laymen? or if only to the Laymen, pray who were the perſons after Prophecy ceaſed among them, to whom the Goſpel Miniſter ſucceeded? or had he no Repreſentative at all? perhaps you will ſay it was the Scribe, who being Interpreter of the Law was for that reaſon a Type of the Goſpel Miniſter, like as the Synagogue where he taught was of Chriſtian Aſſemblies. And thence we may infer, That the <hi>Scribe</hi> and the <hi>Synagogue</hi> are as like Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> as two Beans; and yet I am afraid the Synagogue will not ſuit his purpoſe, any more than the Temple; the <hi>Archiſynagogus</hi> will ſpoil his Pattern, as well as the High-Prieſt: For as there is no ſuch an Officer in the independent way, ſo both the Ordination and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the inferior Scribes belonging to him, he ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles one of our Biſhops, that I fancy Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Vindicator</hi> will neither of them like him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96210:13"/>The Inſtance of <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> and Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Opinion of the Old Teſtament being thus far conſidered; let us now attend him into the new, for there he tells us <hi>the ſpecial Enquiry lies,</hi> p. 6. And the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry he there makes, is after <hi>the ſignification of the word Schiſm;</hi> and the Reaſon he gives for ſo doing, is becauſe <hi>words,</hi> as he tells us, <hi>are the ſignifications of things.</hi> Whether there be not a little Nonſenſe in this weighty Reaſon, (which he lays as the foundation of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Enquiry) I refer to the captions, being willing rather to excuſe it in a Man of his parts.</p>
            <p>But he muſt pardon me, if I make bold to ſearch more ſtrictly into his <hi>ground work;</hi> 'tis in kindneſs to the Superſtructure, which will not abide a Storm, if the Foundation be ſandy. That Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s is ſo, will appear, if we conſider, that altho' words do ſignify things, yet one word does not always ſignify only one thing, neither is the ſame thing always ſignified by the ſame word. And therefore as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
may have ſeveral meanings; ſo other words in the new Teſtament, may expreſs the nature of Schiſm, as well as that, or at leaſt help us to underſtand, the true meaning of it. Thus Mr. <hi>H.</hi> himſelf interprets <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 11. St. <hi>Paul</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls the Schiſmatics <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 19. St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. And there are ſeveral other terms and paſſages in the new Teſtament relating to Schiſm, which methinks ought not to have been omitted, by one that pretends to give us <hi>a clear</hi> and <hi>a full account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is defective in his inquiry, by reaſon of his ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all thoſe paſſages, ſo neither is he exact in his interpretation of the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you have the various meanings of 'em in a literal ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> taken for <hi>a rent,</hi> and <hi>rending,</hi> and <hi>cleaving,</hi> and <hi>breaking,</hi> but <hi>little to the purpoſe,</hi> as he tells you, p. 6, 7. If it makes but little yet that little is ſomething, which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ought not to have paſſed over in ſilence, and another man will ſuppoſe that it makes a great deal; for as in the literal ſenſe, it imports a ſeparation of parts, the rending, or breaking, or cleaving of one body into two; So likewiſe in the Eccleſiaſtical there is ſomething aequivalent meant by it; <hi>viz.</hi> the dividing of Chriſts body, the Church, and making two of that Society, which ought to be united in one: which is moſt viſibly done by ſeparation and breach of Communion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He ſays it is uſed <hi>figuratively for a diviſion,</hi> and that two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi> 1ſt, <hi>A diviſion in apprehenſion,</hi> and 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, <hi>A diviſion in affection.</hi> Theſe two parts of it being the neceſſary ingredients of his deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but if there ſhould be no real ground for this figurative diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the places he has quoted for the difference in apprehenſion, may as well be underſtood concerning difference in affection, and ſo on the contrary, or if ſomething more is to be found in 'em relating to this affair, than what Mr. <hi>H.</hi> has noted; then I ſuppoſe we may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96210:14"/>
reaſonably demure to his clear and full account. The Texts he cites for <hi>a diviſion in apprehenſion</hi> are, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.43. <hi>c.</hi> 9.16. <hi>c.</hi> 10.19. and <hi>Acts</hi> 23.19. Now let any man look into his Bible, and examine theſe paſſages, and I believe the meaneſt capacity will eaſily diſcover a great deal more than barely <hi>a diviſion in apprehenſion.</hi> See <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. and there you will find the Sanhedrim, and their Officers, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple divided about our Saviour. Among the people, ſome cry him up, as <hi>that Prophet,</hi> and <hi>the Chriſt;</hi> others object againſt it, <hi>but ſhall Chriſt come out of Galilee,</hi> &amp;c? Among the Officers ſome were for taking him, others againſt it. In the Sanhedrim one party chid the Officers for not bringing him, <hi>v.</hi> 45. reckoning them <hi>ſeduced by him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</note> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 47. and the people <hi>curſed, v.</hi> 49. <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to be of <hi>Galilee</hi> (which was then a term of reproach) becauſe tho one of the Sanhedrim, yet he was ſecretly his diſciple, and ſtood up for him againſt them all, <hi>v.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. Now here was not only a diverſity of opinion, but a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into parties; a ſtrugling of Intereſts; a baffling of authority; a cenſuring and reviling of thoſe that were for our Saviour, as <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> and <hi>accurſed,</hi> and <hi>Galilaeans.</hi> Whether here was not a diviſion in affection, and what is more, a diviſion and breaking into parties, as well as a diviſion in apprehenſion; let Mr. <hi>H.</hi> himſelf judge, or the Vindicator for him, in caſe he is not able.</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner he deals with <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. Where we read of a diſſention among the multitude, concerning our Saviour, occaſioned by his curing the blind man. Some contending that he <hi>was not of God,</hi> becauſe he <hi>broke the Sabbath;</hi> others, that he was <hi>not a ſinner,</hi> becauſe he <hi>did ſuch Miracles.</hi> The Man and his Parents were both of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's party, but the Parents durſt not expreſly own him to be the Meſſias, <hi>for fear of the Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Pray, Sir, what where they afraid of? Was it leſt they ſhould differ <hi>in apprehenſion?</hi> the Text tells us other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. It was becauſe the Jews had ordained, That <hi>if any man did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he was the Chriſt, he ſhould be</hi> excommunicated <hi>out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue,</hi> was to be turned both out of ſacred and civil communion, and accordingly the Son himſelf was ſo uſed as we find (<hi>v.</hi> 33, 34.) for daring and perſiſting in that acknowledgment. Now where the one party were ſo incenſed againſt them that owned our Saviour, and the other ſo zealous in their belief; as to argue for him notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>odium</hi> and trouble which thereby they might incur, to call a diſſention betwixt theſe parties, only a difference in apprehenſion, has ſomething in it peculiar to Mr. <hi>H.</hi> The diſſentions betwixt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men may perhaps paſs under that cold title, but the diſſentions of parties and multitudes, (eſpecially where people diſpute warmly againſt the ſenſe and intereſt of a Government, as thoſe who took part with our Saviour, in the Jews opinion, did) for the moſt part ſignifies a great deal more. And ſhould there have been ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention in behalf of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, or the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96210:15"/>
when the Independents were uppermoſt, the poor Malignants would have felt more than barely a difference of apprehenſion: And their Taskmaſters would ſoon have interpreted it to be the making of parties; how far the caſes are parallel, let the Reader conſider.</p>
            <p>The next place he alledges for <hi>diviſion in apprehenſion,</hi> is <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.19. and altho ſome went ſo far as to cry out againſt our Saviour, that he is mad, and hath a Devil, which expreſſions could hardly be uſed without ſome warmth and reſentment, as well as reproach and bitterneſs againſt thoſe who owned him to be the Chriſt: Yet Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is ſo very <hi>ingenious,</hi> as to apply it only to <hi>diviſion in apprehenſion,</hi> and ſo exceeding <hi>modeſt</hi> as to impoſe his miſtaken ſenſe (without ſo much as offering at any proof) upon the reſt of mankind,</p>
            <p>Having done with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he falls next upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which he ſays <hi>is uſed in the ſame ſenſe, Acts</hi> 23.7. Here the Phariſees and Sadduces were divided about St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there aroſe a diſſention or an uproar, (for ſo the word may ſignify), <hi>and the multitude was divided,</hi> and altho' the diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was carried on with the crys of the people, and the ſtrivings of the Phariſees, with ſo much noiſe and tumult, that the chief Captain was at laſt afraid, <hi>laſt Paul ſhould have been pull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d in pieces of 'em:</hi> yet this dividing of the multitude according to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s. clear account, did ſignify no more, but only <hi>diviſion in apprehenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a man ſhould have ſaid the ſame thing concerning the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention</hi> at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> about K. <hi>William</hi> and K. <hi>J.</hi> wherein the multitude was likewiſe divided; whether it would have been ingenious, or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, let Mr. Vindicator judge. 'Tis true, the Sadduces had had great Guns, nor did the Phariſees run away, neither do we read of any mighty General that loſt his life, yet there was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
in both caſes, and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s life was in very great danger as well as King <hi>William</hi>'s; it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 7. and but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Now I ſuppoſe any one might conclude from all the aforeſaid Texts, that the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do import a diviſion <hi>in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> as well as <hi>in apprehenſion,</hi> or ſomething more than either, or both of 'em together; namely, the dividing of the people <hi>into contrary par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> and therefore Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is neither <hi>ingenuous,</hi> nor fair, in reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words only to one ſenſe, which are ſo capable of ſeveral, even in thoſe very paſſages which he himſelf cites. If other people would have been as haſty and as fanciful as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to infer a notion of Schiſm from the Engliſh of a word, and that again underſtood and expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as themſelves pleaſe, without taking in the ſenſe of the context to which it relates, they might have made ſhort work on't, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his Vindicator both Schiſmatics: for if <hi>Schiſma</hi> be <hi>diſſention,</hi> as it is rendered in theſe texts, <hi>Schiſmatici</hi> are <hi>diſſenters,</hi> as theſe Gentlemen call themſelves; and ſo the buſineſs is done.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96210:15"/>According to his ingenuity in expounding theſe Texts, he draws his inference from them; <hi>viz. That this diverſity of opinion, judgment, or apprehenſion, cannot be call d or lookt upon in it ſelf a thing criminal; inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as there are many things which (either becauſe they are dark and obſcure and ſo not capable of demonſtration, or becauſe they are trivial and of light mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo not worth a demonſtration) it is no matter what opinion men are of concerning them,</hi> p. 7, 8. Now I would ask Mr. <hi>H.</hi> whether this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph relates to the aforementioned Texts or not? If not, then he might as well have told us his own opinion, with out quoting them it receiving no authority or confirmation from them: and therefore ſhould not have been obtructed upon the World, under the pretext and umbrage of Scripture, but I ſuppoſe he intended it as a poſition, grounded upon the aforeſaid Texts, as appears from his calling it <hi>this diverſity;</hi> which pronoun relative <hi>This,</hi> muſt refer to the Antecedent Texts, and his own paraphraſe, and expoſition of them; and if ſo, it is one of the flieſt Libels upon our Saviour, and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and their believing Friends, and one of the beſt apologies for the Jews and Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces their Enemies, that I have lately met with. For if it were a thing <hi>ſo dark and obſcure, or ſo trivial and light, that the difference was no way criminal, either on one ſide or other, if it were no matter what opinion me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had of our Saviour and St. <hi>Paul, no matter</hi> whether they believ'd the reſurrection, or denied it; <hi>no matter</hi> whether people took our Saviour for the Meſſias, or a mad man; <hi>no matter</hi> what became of Chriſt and his great Apoſtles; or if theſe things were ſo obſcure and dark, and their ignorance about them ſo very invincible, the Jews ſurely were not much to be blam'd for any thing they did; nor the believers much to be commended for making ſuch a pother about things of ſuch <hi>ſmall concernment,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>ſo dark and obſcure, that they could no way demonſtrate whether they did right or not.</hi> This muſt needs be the conſequence of this paragraph, if it relates to the former; and yet I am willing to excuſe Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> from it, having the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rather to believe that he knew not what he ſaid.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble my ſelf much about his pretty ſayings, <hi>p.</hi> 8. tho' perhaps it might juſtly be enquired,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 39. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Whether Hereſy does not always include Schiſm?</hi> Whether Evil does not ſometimes happen from the diverſity, as well as the erroneouſneſs of Opinions? Whom he means by <hi>the Worſhipers of the Diana of their own Opinions, and the Sottiſh;</hi> Whom <hi>by the Saints;</hi> and whether Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is not a <hi>Schiſmatic,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>own Notion,</hi> by the uncharitable and partial Inſinuations of his 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Paragraphs, in the laſt of which ſure he means ſome body, when he talks of <hi>a great ſtrangeneſs to the Spirit of the Goſpel. The Diſciples of St. John Baptiſt</hi> (he tells you) <hi>were hugely diſpleaſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt's Diſciples did not faſt ſo often as they did, and quarrelled with Chriſt himſelf about it,</hi> Mat. 9.14. Now all that thoſe Diſciples did, was to ask our Saviour a queſtion in calm and proper terms, without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96210:16"/>
any token of the leaſt diſpleaſure that I can find, <hi>viz. Why do we, and the Phariſees faſt oft, but thy Diſciples faſt not?</hi> ib. And there was ſo much reaſon for that Enquiry, (conſidering how much Religion they pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Faſting, and what a good opinion they had of our Saviour, and how hard it was for them to reconcile the practice of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, with the Character which their Maſter had given of him) that a Man would wonder how it came to enter into Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s head, that <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciples were angry. Surely Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> is of a very tender conſtitution, if he thinks that he who asks him a queſtion, muſt neceſſarily be diſpleaſed, and quarrel with him. But if <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciples were ſo hugely diſpleaſed, and did really quarrel with our Saviour, when they ask'd him that queſtion, ſurely there was <hi>a diviſion in Affection,</hi> as well as <hi>in Apprehenſion:</hi> and therefore this Text, as well as the reſt, might have been urged under that Head.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Caſe at all ſo applicable to the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and us, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would make it: The Faſting and Abſtinence of <hi>John</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and the Phariſees, was arbitrary, and peculiar to their Sects, not enjoined by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; And, on the other hand, our Saviour had all Authority, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, (as he was both King and Prieſt) united in his Perſon. Now if in either of theſe Points, the Caſe of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> be parallel: If Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can ſhew that our Holy-days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are only the private Inſtitutions of a particular Sect, without the Authority and Sanction either of Church or State; or if he can make it appear that he is equal to our Saviour, that he is a Prieſt, and a King, or a God among his People, let him change the Cuſtoms among them as ſoon as he pleaſes; let 'em faſt all <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and carouze all <hi>Lent</hi> and go contrary in every thing to the <hi>Rubrick</hi> and <hi>Canon,</hi> provided <hi>[they have as much reaſon for their thoughts and practices, as we have for ours,]</hi> which (with ſubmiſſion to Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) we could never yet ſee.</p>
            <p>Thus much I ſhall freely grant him, that in caſe there ariſes a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt private perſons, ſuch as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and I, about matters of Religion, (I ſhould be but a <hi>ſaucy Procruſtes,</hi> if I ſhould go about to appoint the length of him;) but if Authority thinks fit to call him to the Standard, he is undoubtedly a Subject, and I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he ſhould not go as well as I. Some People have not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, ſince they of his Party did uſurp <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair: how zealous they were for drawing up every body to their own pitch; not only thoſe that were in Covenant, but thoſe that were out: inſomuch that if your ſize were too ſmall, and you could not ſtretch, it would be next door to hanging before they had done with you. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſmoothneſs and love which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> perſonates in this Book, yet there is ſtill ſo much roughneſs and ſpite, (which he could not hide, and which the <hi>Vindicator</hi> openly boaſts of) in his rude uſage of <hi>F.W.</hi> as makes me often pray, that I may never ſtand in need of either of theſe Mens Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96210:16"/>We come now to conſider the ſecond ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and a Man would have thought by this time it had been half con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued, but you muſt examin three places in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> and thence you may be <hi>furniſhed with a true Notion of Schiſm,</hi> p. 9. Now if I had been as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> I would have ſcratcht out all the former Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; for if here be the true Notion, what's all this ſtuff for before? But then the little Book had been a great deal leſs than it is.</p>
            <p>Juſt now you muſt look into three places for the true Notion of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> but <hi>(Hocus-Pocus)</hi> turn over the Leaf, and you have it in one of them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren — that there be no diviſions, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) no Schiſms among you.</hi> And for the underſtanding of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you muſt obſerve this method, <hi>i.e.</hi> Firſt of all, <hi>You muſt enquire into the exegetical Exhortations that accompany it.</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>Into the</hi> Corinthians <hi>miſcarriage, which occaſioned this Caution,</hi> p. — The exege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Exhortations are, Firſt, <hi>That ye all ſpeak the ſame thing,</hi> viz <hi>in the fundamental Doctrines of Chriſtianity,</hi> as he underſtands St. <hi>Paul;</hi> but then he tells us from himſelf,<note place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Ov.</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Convoc. Book, <hi>p.</hi> 226.</note> and <hi>Eſtius</hi> (one of thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> with their <hi>Popiſh Annotations) That in little things it can never be made a Duty to be of the ſame Opinion, ſince it is morally impoſſible.</hi> Now, for my part, I can ſee no more impoſſibility for Men to be of the ſame Opinion in little things, than in great. There is but one truth (and one beſt) in both. Their nature is as plain, and it is as eaſy to me to find out my Duty with relation to <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> as it is rightly to apprehend the great Myſteries of the <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Trinity,</hi> and therefore I know no reaſon why I may not agree with other People in little things, as well as in great. A Table-geſture is a little thing, and yet I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> believes, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf made it a Duty to uſe it at the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> It would be pretty to ſee him demonſtrate, according to his own Rule, that it is <hi>morally impoſſible</hi> that we who now think otherwiſe, <hi>ſhould ever be of the ſame Opinion:</hi> and conſequently, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> could never make it our Duty. If the <hi>Gentleman</hi> were better acquainted with <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> he would find that whole Churches and Nations had their peculiar Cuſtoms and Ceremonies, and yet their Members agreed well enough in their Opinions about the things he calls <hi>little,</hi> while they had no ſuch People as he to diſturb their Peace.</p>
            <p>He bids us obſerve, <hi>That St.</hi> Paul <hi>does not oblige us to think the ſame thing, but (tho' your thoughts be divers) yet ſpeak the ſame thing,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>in your Preaching and Converſe, ſpeak of thoſe things only wherein you are agreed.</hi> I obſerved before from Mr. <hi>H.</hi> that they were to <hi>ſpeak the ſame things only in the fundamental Doctrines of Chriſtianity;</hi> and if he will allow me to lay theſe two <hi>Obſervations</hi> together, the Senſe will be thus, <hi>viz.</hi> you are not obliged to think the ſame thing, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to be of the ſame opinion in the <hi>fundamental Doctrines of Chriſtianity,</hi> and in your <hi>Preaching and Converſe,</hi> take care to ſpeak of thoſe things only
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96210:17"/>
wherein you are agreed; and as for the reſt of the <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> you may let them alone, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> according to Mr. <hi>M. H. do not fall out, and fight about them.</hi> As if there were no difference betwixt <hi>meer ſilence,</hi> and <hi>falling out,</hi> and <hi>fighting:</hi> But tho' Mr. <hi>H.</hi> may preach <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals</hi> according to this <hi>Gnoſtic Rule,</hi> I am ſure that St. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf followed a contrary practice, or elſe he might have ſaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble of many ſharp perſecutions, as well as a great deal of pains in this <hi>Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That ye be perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment; which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>muſt be underſtood of a ſerious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor after it, for otherwiſe a perfect conjunction muſt be reſerved for a world of everlaſting perfection.</hi> If Mr. <hi>H.</hi> had but lookt into his <hi>Greek Teſtament,</hi> and duly conſidered the <hi>Original,</hi> perhaps he would have found no great reaſon for this <hi>Interpretation.</hi> The words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Be ye compacted,</hi> or <hi>knit together in the ſame mind and opinion.</hi> For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is in the <hi>literal</hi> Notion, to <hi>compact,</hi> or <hi>knit together,</hi> either the <hi>members</hi> of a <hi>body,</hi> or the <hi>parts</hi> of a <hi>building,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> obſerves, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed for the <hi>breaking of a Net,</hi> John 21.11. So <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is, in <hi>Engliſh, mending their Nets,</hi> Mat. 4.21. And as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are oppoſed in the <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe, ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
are by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor were the <hi>Corinthians all agreed in the great Goſpel Truths,</hi> as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ignorantly ſuppoſes, <hi>p.</hi> 11. The <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is ſurely to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the great <hi>Goſpel-Truths,</hi> and yet many of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> denied it, which gave occaſion to St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo ſtrenuouſly to aſſert it in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Chapter</hi> of this firſt <hi>Epiſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clem. Rom. p. 60. &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Vid.</hi> Chryſoſt. <hi>&amp;</hi> Theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum <hi>in locum. Vid.</hi> Hammond. <hi>in cap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> and St. <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> in his. That <hi>Marriage</hi> is <hi>lawful,</hi> and <hi>Fornication</hi> otherwiſe, are (I ſuppoſe) conſiderable <hi>Goſpel-Truths:</hi> And yet the <hi>Corinthian Schiſmatic</hi> allowed and practiſed <hi>Fornication,</hi> even ſuch as was condemned by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and no where ſcarce in uſe, (except among the brutiſh <hi>Arabs</hi>) viz. <hi>That a Man ſhould have his Fathers wife,</hi> cap. 5.1. And yet this done by a <hi>Doctor</hi> of ſome <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Achaia,</hi> within the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Precinct, according to St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Not only admitted to be a partaker of the <hi>Divine Myſteries,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he had obtained the <hi>dignity</hi> of a <hi>Doctor.</hi> And altho' ſome of thoſe <hi>ancient Heretics</hi> could diſpenſe with <hi>Fornication,</hi> yet they diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded People from <hi>Marriage,</hi> teaching them, <hi>that it was of the Devil.</hi> That we ought to own our <hi>Saviour</hi> in times of the <hi>greateſt perſecution,</hi> is a <hi>great Goſpel-Truth,</hi> Luke 12.9. and yet the <hi>Corinthian Schiſmatics</hi> taught and practis'd otherwiſe, (which <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> is likewiſe thought to oppoſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 11, &amp;c.) and went ſo far as to partake of the <hi>Idol Sacrifices</hi> according to their <hi>worldly wiſdom,</hi> that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96210:17"/>
they might eſcape <hi>perſecution,</hi> which made the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> argue that point, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. and to determin ſo peremptorily and ſeverely, <hi>cap.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Ye cannot drink the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devils; Ye cannot be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Lord's Table, and the Table of Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might give you ſeveral other inſtances of the Gnoſtick hereſy, (too rife at that time in the Corinthian Church) but theſe ſurely are ſufficient to prove againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> that they were not <hi>all agreed in the great Goſpel-Truths.</hi> Now Hereſy includes Schiſm as it breaks the unity of the Faith, one of the indiſpenſible requiſites to the unity of the Church. And therefore the Corinthian Hereticks being Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matics likewiſe <hi>(i.e.)</hi> disjointed, and looſe from the body of the Church, the Apoſtle bids 'em be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, well-jointed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted in the Church. Again, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment <hi>(i. e:)</hi> by uniting themſelves to it both in affection and principles, a work ſurely to be done while men are in this world; and if it be not, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will find it too late when he enters into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>I have only two things further to note under this particular. Firſt, That the Apoſtle charging the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to be perfectly join'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment, or opinion (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>); it is ſtrange how Mr. <hi>H.</hi> could obſerve <hi>that they were not obliged to think the ſame thing,</hi> And ſecondly, That this Text relating ſo plainly to <hi>difference in apprehenſion,</hi> even according to his own expoſition, it is no leſs unaccountable to me, why it might not as well have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced under that head, as any one of thoſe which he alledged to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>We muſt enquire into the</hi> Corinthians <hi>miſcarriage which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned this caution, which,</hi> he tells us, <hi>we have,</hi> v. 11, 12. <hi>There were contentions among them,</hi> v. 11. <hi>Now the contention was about their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> aſſures us, <hi>p.</hi> 11. But I would ask him, firſt of all, was there no miſcarriage antecedent to that contnetion? Yes ſurely, their heretical and wicked opinions, which occaſioned the antecedent caution, <hi>viz.</hi> That ye all ſpeak the ſame things. In theſe the Schiſm was founded, and they were probably the occaſion of their aſcribing themſelves to <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and Chriſt. For where difference in opinion occaſions debates among people, not only the merits of the cauſe, but likewiſe the original of each party, and the means of knowing what they pretend to teach others are very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently enquired into. Thus it was in our Saviour's caſe, when he taught ſomething new and extraordinary, beyond the common rate of their ordinary Scribes; <hi>Whence hath this man this wiſdom and theſe mighty works? Is not this the Carpenters ſon? Is not his Mother called Mary, &amp;c? And are not his Siſters all with us? Whence then hath this man all theſe things?</hi> Mat. 13.54, 55, 56.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96210:18"/>And there ſeems to be abundantly more occaſion, for the like enquiry in the caſe of the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> as will appear, if we conſider the circumſtances of thoſe early times, when this Epiſtle was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, eſpecially what means of knowledge the <hi>Corinthians</hi> then had; and what proofs they might make uſe of to evince the truth or falſhood of any Doctrine in debate.</p>
            <p>They could not have the writings of the New Teſtament, (this Epiſtle being one of the firſt. And it may reaſonably be conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (perhaps proved) that of that little which was then written, they had ſeen nothing. For neither in their Epiſtle to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo far as St. <hi>Paul</hi> alludes to it, neither in his to them, is there the leaſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of any ſuch thing. And yet in the Epiſtles to the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> (which were of a prior date) had they been in their hands, they might have found the reſolution of ſome of thoſe caſes which they put to the Apoſtle, and therefore ſaved themſelves the labour of that part of their appeal.</p>
            <p>And as for the writings of the Old Teſtament, there were two ſorts of errors, (not to mention any more) which were not eaſily confuted by their authority. One was touching the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, which (altho it might be proved from the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet the Gnoſtics who denyed it, may reaſonably be ſuppoſed to have learnt from the Sadduces, ſome of their firſt Maſters, how to evade thoſe proofs; and as for the other Judaizing Doctrines, the Old Teſtament did ſo far ſeem to countenance them, that it was not likely that every <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be able to prove it otherwiſe. And therefore it might become the skill and authority of the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle himſelf to ſhew the contrary.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had not the aſſiſtance of the written rule, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for information, or proof, in theſe caſes, ſo both muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from their Teachers; either in word or writing. For inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (beſides what they had learned from our Saviour and his Apoſtles) they had their Prophets and Evangeliſts continually among them who being endued with the Spirit, were thereby qualified to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and educate the younger converts in the Doctrines of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and from theſe the <hi>Corinthians</hi> received their common Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>But as the Orthodox Prophets had their true inſpirations, ſo the Heretical Teachers pretended to the ſame; and as the former had their true miracles for the confirmation of their Doctrines, ſo the latter had their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their lying wonders for the confirmation of theirs, to deceive, if it were poſſible, the very elect. And that which made it ſtill more difficult for the ordinary <hi>Corinthians</hi> to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, was, becauſe both parties continued in the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: the Heretics not daring to go out <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to ſeparate from the Church, till a conſiderable time after this, when many of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were dead.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96210:18"/>Now where both ſides were equal in order, pretended to the ſame inſpirations, the ſame miracles, and lived in the ſame communion: the proof of each Doctrine muſt depend upon the credit and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe perſons from whom it was derived. If from Chriſt, it was the greateſt; if from the Apoſtles, it was next; if from one of the firſt Converts (well learned in the Chriſtian doctrines) high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approved and dignified by the Apoſtles, (as <hi>Apollos</hi> was) it was of the laſt great authority. Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> recommends the authority of the houſhold of <hi>Stephanas,</hi> as being the moſt early Converts in that Region, the firſt-fruits of <hi>Achaia;</hi> who having <hi>addicted themſelves unto the Miniſtry of the Saints, I beſeech you brethren</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that you ſubmit your ſelves unto ſuch,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.15, 16. <hi>Therefore acknowledge ye them that are ſuch,</hi> v. 18. Hereby plainly directing them which ſide to chooſe, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe that were of <hi>Stephanas, Fortunatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Acha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>'s party, who took part with the Apoſtles, and conſequently were Orthodox. So likewiſe he magnifies his own authority, as prior and greater than that of the firſt-fruits; telling them that <hi>he planted,</hi> Cap. 3.6. <hi>as the wiſe Maſter-builder, he had laid the foundation,</hi> v. 10. That <hi>although they had ten thouſand Inſtructors in Chriſt, yet not many Fathers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in Chriſt Jeſus he had begotten them through the Goſpel,</hi> c. 4.15. So that having received their Chriſtianity originally from him, they ought not to gainſay his doctrines, they might not oppoſe their firſt-fruits to his authority. The Colledge of their Prophets could not judge him. And as for thoſe who were the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and therefore ſaid, they were of Chriſt <hi>(i. e.)</hi> had heard our Saviour themſelves, and therefore pretended to have received their Doctrine from him, and were conſequently of greater authority than the firſt-fruits, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived theirs only from the Apoſtles, yet theſe were not to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited in oppoſition to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who being choſen into the number of the ſelect witneſſes, no other witneſs that was not one of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber could be equal to him. Or if any man ſhould oppoſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of an Apoſtle, St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or any of the reſt, againſt St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, yet the Anſwer is eaſy, <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> Can he make two men the Apoſtles of contrary doctrines? The Apoſtles and all other Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Teachers muſt neceſſarily ſpeak the ſame thing. They <hi>being la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers together with God,</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.9. Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>Stewards of the myſteries,</hi> c. 4.1. but <hi>can lay no other foundation than that is laid in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> c. 3.11.</p>
            <p>So that if men pretend the authority of St. <hi>Peter</hi> againſt thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines that are really St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, their pretences by this very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are proved fictitious, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> could never be the Author of any ſuch thing. Or if the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who ſay they are of Chriſt, ſhould pretend his authority againſt that which is tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ly St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, yet the anſwer is the ſame: <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> He choſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Paul,</hi> and gave him his Spirit to preach theſe doctrines, and therefore thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96210:19"/>
muſt neceſſarily belye our Saviour, who cannot be ſuppoſed to make the Apoſtles Preachers of one Doctrine, and himſelf preach the contrary. And yet if any man ſhould ſet up <hi>Paul</hi> againſt the true Doctrine of Chriſt, ſo as to make him the patron of their new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, becauſe he had the authority of an Apoſtle, yet the anſwer is eaſy, <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> He cannot have the authority of Chriſt to preach two contrary Doctrines, neither ought he to ſet up any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of his own againſt the Doctrine and Authority of Chriſt, which is the ground of that farther reaſoning, Was <hi>Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized in the name of Paul? I thank God that I baptized none of you but Criſpus and Gaius — and the houſhold of Stephanas, leſt any ſhould ſay that I had baptized in mine own name,</hi> c. 1. v. 13, 14, 15. Tho we are Stewards of the myſteries, have the authority of Apoſtles, and <hi>are accountable to no man ſave only to the Lord,</hi> c. 4.4. yet this authority does not impower us to be the patrons of contrary doctrines, that we ſhould preach to you one doctrine formerly, and now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary be obtruded upon ye under our names. <hi>It is required of Stewards that a man be found faithful,</hi> c. 4.2. and therefore we who are ſuch ought to be true to our Maſter, and conſiſtent to our ſelves. <hi>So that if we or an Angel from Heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8. And that they might take the greater notice, he ingeminates the ſentence, <hi>as we ſaid before, ſo ſay I now again — If any man preach any other Goſpel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you than that ye have received, let him be accurſed,</hi> Ibid. v. 9.</p>
            <p>Now for the Orthodox to ſay they were of <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> that they received their doctrines from them, was the ſame thing then as to quote Scripture now, <hi>i. e.</hi> it was the utmoſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they could alledge. But when the Hereticks pretended to the ſame authority, the Orthodox had no way left but to appeal to the Apoſtle himſelf, that it might appear under his own hand, what his doctrine really was, and which party was in the right, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly they diſpatched their Letters to him, by <hi>Stephanas, &amp;c.</hi> by whom likewiſe they received his anſwer in this Epiſtle concerning the things in debate.</p>
            <p>So that it was the Heretical Gnoſtics only (not the Orthodox par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) who are reprehended by the Apoſtle for ſaying, I am of <hi>Paul, &amp;c.</hi> 'Twas neceſſary for them to alledge theſe great authorities, that they might counterpoize the Orthodox, who juſtly pretended to the ſame, this being one of the beſt ways of proof in an age of inſpirations, while there was little or nothing written.</p>
            <p>And accordingly we find it made uſe of by the ſucceeding Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics, till ſuch times as the Canon of Scripture was collected, and made up, (which was the beſt part of a Century, at leaſt, after the writing of this Epiſtle.) And when that was done, they could not eaſily forget the ſame artifice, but ſtill vented their doctrines under
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96210:19"/>
the patronage of great names, ſo the <hi>Ebionites</hi> pretended to be the followers of St. <hi>James;</hi> the <hi>Baſilidans</hi> of St. <hi>Matthias; Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lides</hi> himſelf of <hi>Glaucias,</hi> (the hearer of St. <hi>Peter) Valentinus</hi> of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dades</hi> (who was converſant with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c.) Sometimes they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the truth by pretended and falſe traditions, otherwhiles by ſpurious and ſuppoſititious writings, and at laſt by corrupting the very Text it ſelf by their baſe interpolations.</p>
            <p>Nor is it to be ſuppoſed that this was the practice only of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Heretics, you may trace it in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> written ſeveral years before this 1ſt. to the <hi>Corinthians— That ye be not ſoon ſhaken in mind, or be troubled neither by Spirit, nor by word, nor by letter, as from us, as that the day of Chriſt is at hand. Let no man deceive you by any means, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.2, 3. Herein alluding to the pretended revelations, the falſe and ſpurious traditions of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Teachers, and either ſome counterfeit Epiſtle urged under the Apoſtles name, or at leaſt their corrupt gloſſes and interpretations of thoſe words in the 1ſt. Epiſtle, <hi>c.</hi> 5.2. and perhaps it may not be unreaſonably conjectured, that it was a counterfeit Epiſtle, or at leaſt that ſuch practices were then in uſe, becauſe the Apoſtle is ſo careful to give 'em a certain token in the cloſe of this Epiſtle, whereby they might diſtinguiſh betwixt thoſe that were genuine, and thoſe that were otherwiſe: <hi>The ſalutation of me Paul with mine own hand, which is the token in every Epiſtle,</hi> c. 3.17.</p>
            <p>And if this was the practice of the primitive Heretics, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after the writing of this Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> we may reaſonably ſuppoſe, that they did not wholly omit it at this time. And therefore I ſee no reaſon (but rather a great deal to the contrary) why any body ſhould be blamed, for ſaying, <hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſave only thoſe <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not to be ſuppoſed that the <hi>Orthodox</hi> complained of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for if they knew themſelves herein faulty, they might eaſily have reformed, without ever acquainting the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> with it. And it is ſomething remarkable, how <hi>Clemens</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem.</hi> Ep. ad Corinth. pag. <hi>110.</hi> Edit. Lond. <hi>1687.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Romanus</hi> aggravates the <hi>latter Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by extenuating this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that ſiding was leſs criminal, for then <hi>ye took part with the Apoſtles, who had born their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and a man highly approved by them, but now what kind of men are they that have turned you aſide,</hi> &amp;c. From which words it is plain, That as the <hi>latter Schiſmatics</hi> were all of a Party, ſo were the <hi>former:</hi> And therefore the being of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> &amp;c. is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by St. <hi>Clemens</hi> under one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>So that according to the circumſtances of thoſe times, the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and the account of <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> they were all of one Party, whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> reprehends, for ſaying, <hi>I am of Paul, &amp;c.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> among them (thoſe who had ſeen and heard
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96210:20"/>
our <hi>Saviour</hi>) pretended to be of Chriſt, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to have received theirs from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter;</hi> the elder <hi>Converts,</hi> among the reſt, who had been baptized by <hi>Apollos,</hi> to derive theirs from him. So that the <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> lay, in oppoſing the <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Doctors,</hi> maintaining their wild <hi>Hereſies,</hi> under the pretence and umbrage of theſe great names; and all other <hi>Heretics,</hi> who altho' they forſook not the Communion of the <hi>Church,</hi> yet making a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration within it, and forming a Party againſt the truth, and oppoſing their <hi>Orthodox Governors,</hi> have been reputed <hi>Schiſmatics</hi> upon the very ſame account in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Having thus far given an account of the <hi>Corinthian Schiſm,</hi> which will do but little ſervice to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Notion,</hi> let us now take a further view of his <hi>Enquiry,</hi> and conſider how ingeniouſly he manages the matter. He tells you, <hi>That Schiſms and Contentions are one and the ſame thing;</hi> as if <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Contention</hi> had been convertible terms, and every one that contends, tho' for the greateſt <hi>Truths</hi> againſt the moſt pernicious <hi>Hereſies,</hi> were for that reaſon a <hi>Schiſmatic.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> might as well, and as truly have ſaid, <hi>That Schiſms and Factions are the ſame thing,</hi> becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them likewiſe by that name: But, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to lay the greater <hi>Emphaſis</hi> upon the word <hi>Contentions,</hi> he adds, <hi>'tis worth noting that</hi> Clemens Romanus <hi>in that famous Epiſtle of his to the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>ſtill calls Schiſms <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Contentions,</hi> En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. 11. Now from this Note of Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s, I hope he will give me leave to make another; which is, that Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> never read that famous Epiſtle: For tho' <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſometimes uſed in that famous Writer, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſeveral other words, by which St. <hi>Clemens</hi> means <hi>Schiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, p. 110, 116. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, p. 33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, p. 108. Edit. Lond. 1687.</note> are brought in more frequently, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the plural ſcarcely once in that whole Epiſtle: But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> being a <hi>modeſt,</hi> as well as an <hi>ingenious</hi> perſon, was, it ſeems, contented to <hi>ſteal</hi> a Note out of Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis,</hi> rather than undergo the <hi>drudgery</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> of that famous Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange how Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in the next Paragraph ſhould ſay, <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was about their Miniſters.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> was aſcended up into Heaven long before this, and it would have been a ſtrange wild fancy in any <hi>Corinthian,</hi> not to be contented with any other Miniſter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only him. If Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Congregation</hi> at the next Election of a Miniſter, ſhould be divided into four Parties, and one of them be for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and no one elſe, I fancy the reſt would conclude, that either they were not right in their wits, or elſe that it is purely a trick to have none at all.</p>
            <p>And beſides, it would be hard for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to aſſign any reaſon why any body ſhould prefer <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> before <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I always thought our <hi>Saviour</hi> might have had the preference. And among all the wild Opinions of that Age, I believe neither Mr. <hi>H.</hi> nor his <hi>Vindicator</hi> can name one <hi>Heretic,</hi> who ever profeſſed himſelf to be for <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c. rather than for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96210:20"/>He tells you, <hi>That he that was of</hi> Apollos, <hi>was as much a Schiſmatic as he that was of</hi> Paul; which is very true, (tho' not for the reaſon which he gives.) They were all of one ſide, againſt the <hi>Orthodox.</hi> There being not four Parties among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> fancies, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf makes but two, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>Heretics,</hi> as is plain from that part of his ſalutation, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>To all that in every place call upon the Name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>That if one went to hear</hi> Paul, <hi>and another went to near</hi> Apollos, <hi>that did not make a</hi> Schiſm: <hi>no, nor if one communicated with</hi> Paul, <hi>and another with</hi> Apollos; which is certainly true: for it would have been no more <hi>Schiſm</hi> to hear and communicate, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, than it would be among us to communicate with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi> But I would fain know of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> how they muſt at that time hear and communicate with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was then in <hi>Aſia?</hi> how with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was then in <hi>Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was no occaſion for <hi>ſilencing either</hi> Apollos <hi>or</hi> Cephas, for they were of the ſame mind with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the other <hi>orthodox Doctors.</hi> And yet there might be occaſion enough to ſilence ſome of the <hi>ſchiſmatical Teachers,</hi> who made uſe of their Names, to give a reputation to their own <hi>Hereſies;</hi> and accordingly you find the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> threatning them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Now I write to them which heretofore have ſinned, and to all other, that if I come again I will not ſpare.</hi> And in the 10th <hi>Verſe, Therefore I write theſe things being abſent, leſt being preſent I ſhould uſe ſharpneſs, according to the power which the Lord hath given me,</hi> &amp;c. which power was not only to <hi>ſilence,</hi> but to <hi>excommunicate thoſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and inflict that further puniſhment which then attended thoſe <hi>Cenſures,</hi> and accordingly the <hi>inceſtuous Doctor</hi> was to be ſo dealt with by the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> authority and order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5. <hi>to be delivered unto Satan,</hi> by being <hi>excommunicated</hi> out of the Church, <hi>for the deſtruction of the fleſh,</hi> that Satan having him in his power, might torment his body with diſeaſes and pains.</p>
            <p>For ſuch a power as this the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had, whereby they were more eſpecially enabled to convict <hi>Heretics</hi> of <hi>Impoſture,</hi> who pretending to <hi>Miracles</hi> as well as the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> it was not eaſy for the common People to ſee which were in the right, unleſs ſomething extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary appeared on the one ſide more than the other. And in this caſe nothing could be ſo proper, as that power of inflicting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the very perſons of the Wonder-workers. They might equal the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves in their pretences to <hi>Inſpirations,</hi> to <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> and <hi>Knowledge.</hi> Their <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Conjurations</hi> might perhaps ſeem as ſtrange to the common People, as any <hi>true Miracles:</hi> But when the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> inflicted <hi>miraculous puniſhments,</hi> and yet they could neither <hi>ſave</hi> nor <hi>avenge</hi> themſelves by all their power, it would be plain enough to every one, who it was that acted by the <hi>power of God,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96210:21"/>
conſequently which ſide were in the <hi>right,</hi> and which <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> threatens the <hi>elated Gnoſtics,</hi> to <hi>know their power,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.19. <hi>For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power,</hi> i. e. it will not be ſo eaſy for you to judge by <hi>diſputations,</hi> &amp;c. who are the <hi>orthodox members</hi> of <hi>God's Church,</hi> as by theſe more evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of <hi>power,</hi> which make the caſe plain to every man.</p>
            <p>And yet the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was always tender how he uſed thoſe rigorous methods, this power being <hi>given for edification,</hi> and <hi>not for deſtruction,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.10. it was only to be exerted upon the moſt <hi>notorious</hi> and <hi>incorrigible Offenders.</hi> And this is the reaſon why we meet with ſo few inſtances of it, and why the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> leaves it to their choice, how he ſhould deal with them. <hi>What will ye, ſhall I come unto you with a rod, or in love, and in the ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.21. And this <hi>power</hi> ſeems to be appropriate to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of that early Age: For why elſe does the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the caſe of the <hi>inceſtuous Corinthian,</hi> affirm himſelf to be <hi>preſent in ſpirit</hi> at the meeting of the <hi>inferior Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> [<hi>When ye are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5.</note>] What matter whether the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> were preſent any way or not, if his preſence were no way neceſſary? why <hi>ſhould his ſpirit with the power of Chriſt,</hi> be ſo emphatically mentioned, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. if the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had that power of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo as to do it without him; perhaps one reaſon might be, becauſe the <hi>Corinthian</hi> was a Doctor.</p>
            <p>And we find the ſame authority over perſons of that degree, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the ſucceeding <hi>Biſhops.</hi> So <hi>Timothy</hi> might beſtow the <hi>marks of Honour,</hi> and likewiſe receive <hi>Accuſations againſt an Elder,</hi> and <hi>rebuke them that ſinned before all,</hi> ſo as to <hi>terrify others,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17, 19, 20. <hi>Titus</hi> was to <hi>rebuke ſharply the Gnoſtic Prophets,</hi> thoſe who bore the like character in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> to that of <hi>Epimenides</hi> among the <hi>Heathen,</hi> (i. e.) were <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Diviners,</hi> to <hi>ſtop their mouths,</hi> which was ſurely to <hi>ſilence</hi> them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13. So that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> who ſucceeded them in Authority, <hi>had power to ſilence the ſchiſmatical Teachers,</hi> which is all we contend for: But neither they nor we are for <hi>ſilencing thoſe Miniſters</hi> that being <hi>duly ordain'd,</hi> are <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>orthodox,</hi> according to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Suppoſition;</hi> and whether he and his <hi>Vindicator</hi> belong to the <hi>former,</hi> or the <hi>latter ſort,</hi> we are willing at any time to ſtand a fair Tryal.</p>
            <p>As for his inſtance of <hi>Apollos,</hi> it will do him but little ſervice, if <hi>Antiquity</hi> is to be credited, which makes this very <hi>Apollos</hi> the firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and it is to be noted, that there were <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> before, and therefore if <hi>Apollos</hi> was the firſt <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he was of another Order. And their boaſted Father St. <hi>Jerome</hi> expreſly tells us, that upon this very <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ron.</hi> in Comment. ad <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>um.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>In toto orbe decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, ut unus de Presbyteris electus ſuperponeretur caeteris, ad quem omnis eccleſiae cura pertineret, &amp; Schiſmatum ſemina tollerentur.</hi> Not that there was no Epiſcopal Authority before this time, it was lodged in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96210:21"/>
the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> till now, and this was the firſt time they communicated it to any other perſon.</p>
            <p>With the like ingenuity Mr. <hi>H.</hi> expounds the ſecond place in this Epiſtle, where he finds the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, telling us, Firſt, <hi>That it could not be meant of breach of Communion, becauſe they all came together into one place,</hi> v. 20. Secondly, That the Schiſms were <hi>Quarrels and Contentions about ſome little things relating to the circumſtances of public wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> Thirdly, That the quarrel <hi>ſeems to be obout the time of beginning their worſhip,</hi> in every of which conjectures Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is groſly miſtaken, and ſeems not to have underſtood St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s meaning, as will appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That altho it is true, as I noted before, that Schiſmatics did not as yet hold any ſeparate Conventicles, yet there was a moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious breach of communion, even at the Communion-Table; and their miſcarriages were ſo great, and of ſuch a kind, as were ſcarcely reconcileable with the nature of a Sacramental Feaſt. Inſomuch that the Apoſtle tells 'em, v. 20. <hi>When ye come together into one place, This is not to eat the Lord's Supper,</hi> and the reaſon was becauſe they did not communicate one with another. <hi>For in eating every one taketh before other his own Supper, and one is hungry and another is drunken (i. e.)</hi> The rich who contributed more plentifully to the common feaſt, did not ſuffer the poor to be ſharers with them, but ſnatcht up their own ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and eat and drank it themſelves. So that thoſe who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their poverty, brought little or nothing, <hi>went away hungry and aſhamed,</hi> v. 21, 22. Now this was ſo much a breach of communion, that according to this practice there was really no communion at all. The rich lookt upon what they brought as their own Supper, to which no man elſe had any right, and for this reaſon were ſo haſty to eat it up themſelves, that the poor had nothing. So that while one party had nothing to eat, and the reſt ate every man his own without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating one with another, there was ſo great a violation of the deſigned communion, that really they made it no communion at all.</p>
            <p>And yet I can find no quarrels, or contentions among them. The rich who fed ſo plentifully had no reaſon to quarrel, for they had their full ſhare even to exceſs. And altho the poor had really a juſt cauſe of complaint, yet perhaps becauſe they brought nothing they thought it not ſeemly to mutiny. All the Apoſtle mentions concerning their behaviour is that they were <hi>hungry,</hi> v. 21. and, as may be collected from the next verſe, out of countenance and <hi>aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis pretty to ſee Mr. <hi>H.</hi> bringing in his <hi>little things</hi> here again, as tho Hereſies, <hi>v.</hi> 10. to violate the pious deſign of a feaſt of Charity, <hi>v.</hi> 20. to be drunken themſelves and ſtarve the Poor. <hi>v.</hi> 21. to expoſe their poverty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and put them out of countenance; and all this in the Church, at their <hi>Agapae,</hi> or feaſts of charity, were to paſs under the title of <hi>little things.</hi> If there had been any quarrels among 'em, theſe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96210:22"/>
according to the Apoſtle, muſt have been the occaſions; which ſurely cannot be little things in the opinion of any man, who has not himſelf a very large Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> bids them <hi>tarry one for another,</hi> ver. 33. was, that they might have communion by eating together, and not, according to their rude and irregular practice, take every one before other his own Supper. But it is unreaſonable to conclude, <hi>That they quarrelled about the time of their meeting:</hi> For altho' the time were fully agreed on by every mans conſent, yet unleſs all Clocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> went alike in thoſe days, and all mens ſpeed were equal, ſome would come ſooner, and others later, as well as they do now; and the firſt might devour what they themſelves brought, before ſuch times as the reſt could be there to partake with them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall obſerve only two things more, before I paſs to the next Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in his account of this, very ingeniouſly paſſes over the next and immediate <hi>Context,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>For there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are approved, may be made manifeſt among you.</hi> Now ſuppoſe that any man ſhould infer hence, that the <hi>Schiſm</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. was occaſioned by their <hi>Hereſies;</hi> that their <hi>Diviſions</hi> were only into <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties,</hi> ſome being <hi>orthodox,</hi> and ſome <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi> as it is among us, and that hence proceeded the other <hi>irregular practices;</hi> I would fain know what he has to ſay to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>And 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, It may perhaps try the <hi>wit</hi> of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Brethren,</hi> to give a clear account how St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s reaſonings, <hi>ver.</hi> 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, and 32, can any way <hi>quadrate,</hi> or be <hi>reconciled</hi> to his <hi>Notion.</hi> And yet they muſt be all brought in, or elſe the 33<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>verſe</hi> quoted and urg'd by him, will bear no manner of relation to the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, which he deſigns it to interpret.</p>
            <p>The laſt place Mr. <hi>H.</hi> mentions, is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.25. <hi>That there be no Schiſm in the body.</hi> I ſhall paſs over his Remarks, <hi>p.</hi> 14. it being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us, that he is pleaſed to acknowledge, <hi>pag.</hi> 15. that to be <hi>Schiſm, which breaks or ſtockens the bond by which the members are knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;</hi> which thing is ſo notoriouſly done by <hi>ſeparation,</hi> and <hi>breach of communion,</hi> that whoever is guilty of that, may, according to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> juſtly be charged with <hi>Schiſm. That Bond,</hi> he tells us, <hi>is not an Act of Uniformity;</hi> neither, ſay I, is the <hi>obligation</hi> of that <hi>Bond</hi> taken away by an <hi>Act of Indulgence.</hi> And therefore, notwithſtanding the late <hi>Act,</hi> nay, tho' we ſhould have no <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> yet all this would not excuſe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Vindicator</hi> from being <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics,</hi> according to his own Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True Love and Charity in point of Affection,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> aſſures us) <hi>is the only Bond by which Chriſtians are knit together — And</hi> Schiſm <hi>is that which breaks that Bond.</hi> That <hi>Schiſm</hi> does uſually break <hi>Charity,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:96210:22"/>
no man will deny, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his Party are ſufficient inſtances of this truth, as thoſe perſons who have the zeal and courage to oppoſe their <hi>Faction,</hi> do always find when ever they fall into their hands.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> is likewiſe a means to prevent <hi>Schiſms,</hi> as it always pays a juſt deference to all <hi>ſpiritual Governors,</hi> cools and abates the violence of <hi>Faction,</hi> makes People <hi>humble, obedient,</hi> and <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible,</hi> and cauſes all to endeavor after <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> we do readily acknowledge; and for this reaſon both the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and others have all along in their diſcourſes about <hi>Schiſm,</hi> preſſed men to <hi>Charity,</hi> as a neceſſary means to bring them over to <hi>conformity</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> with a <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>orthodox Church.</hi> But to infer hence, <hi>That Charity in point of Affection, is the only Bond by which Chriſtians are knit together, and that Schiſm conſequently is nothing elſe but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs</hi> are Poſitions only fit for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to aſſert, and the <hi>Vindicator</hi> to juſtify.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not ſay, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> falſly quotes him, <hi>That it is the unity of the Spirit that is the bond of peace,</hi> Eph. 4.3. but exhorts the <hi>Epheſians to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> ſo that <hi>the bond of peace</hi> muſt needs be ſomething more than barely the <hi>unity of the Spirit.</hi> And by <hi>the unity of the Spirit,</hi> more is certainly to be underſtood than only <hi>Charity,</hi> as appears by the References made to it in the Context, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.7. &amp; 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which thorowly conſidered, makes this Text little or nothing to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And withal it is to be remembred, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> inſiſts upon ſeveral other tyes and obligations whereby Chriſtians are knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, beſides <hi>Charity, viz.</hi> they are incorporated into <hi>one ſociety, one body,</hi> as well as animated by <hi>one ſpirit,</hi> ver. 4. united in <hi>one hope</hi> of their bleſſed calling, <hi>ibid.</hi> united as Subjects to the ſame Lord, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of one and the ſame Faith; initiated into the ſame Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and Partners in the ſame Covenant, by one and the ſame Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; and united by our union and communion with the orthodox Governors and Paſtors of the Church, which, St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>were given us for the perfecting of the Saints;</hi> or, according to the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>the compacting or knitting together of the Saints,</hi> ver. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>the edifying</hi> or building up <hi>of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the unity of the faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>unto a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that we henceforth be no more Children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine by the ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive,</hi> ver. 13, 14. From all which it appears, that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is for one Doctrine, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> for another; and therefore having laid both opinions before the Reader, I freely leave it to his own choice whether of the two he will follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charity</hi> is certainly <hi>the bond of perfectneſs;</hi> but what is meant by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> has not informed us: which ſurely he ought to have done, before he had made any infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from theſe words, whether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>mercifulneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hammond</hi> in loc.</note> as it does, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.36. or <hi>perfectneſs,</hi> in all the duties of Chriſtianity. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:96210:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may either way be the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or bond of it; for <hi>Charity</hi> is a very large and comprehenſive virtue: The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>it is the fulfilling of the Law.</hi> So that every duty you can name is included in it, and every ſin a violation of it: The <hi>Thief</hi> breaks <hi>Charity,</hi> when he picks his Neighbour's <hi>Pocket:</hi> The <hi>Murderer,</hi> when he cuts his <hi>Throat:</hi> The <hi>Traytor,</hi> when he conſpires againſt his <hi>Prince:</hi> And the <hi>Schiſmatic,</hi> who makes <hi>Broils</hi> and <hi>Factions</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi> But ſtill, if any one ſhould ask you—<hi>Pray, Sir,</hi> What is Treaſon? and you ſhould anſwer, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs?</hi> What is Murder? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs.</hi> What is Theft? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs.</hi> What is Schiſm? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs.</hi> I believe no man would take you for a Conjurer in <hi>Logic,</hi> any more than in <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this is all that Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> has done towards furniſhing the world with a <hi>New Notion</hi> of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and to acquire to himſelf the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles of <hi>Modeſt</hi> and <hi>Ingenious,</hi> which the <hi>Vindicator</hi> ſo liberally beſtows upon him, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. which how well he deſerves, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge, and upon theſe doughty premiſſes he founds his Deſcription of <hi>Schiſm;</hi> which ought, I ſuppoſe, to have been a definition, that being much more proper for a Man of Art, and much more ſuitable to his deſign, of giving you the true nature, or <hi>formalis ratio:</hi> which are things a little too nice to be regularly inferred from every bungling Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. And having thus far enquired into Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Account, let us now return to the <hi>Vindicator:</hi> I fancy they are both of a Family, and therefore let us ſee whether he may not put in a better claim to the aforeſaid Titles.</p>
            <p>He acquits Mr. <hi>H. pag.</hi> 4. from being <hi>Author of the Reply,</hi> fearing leſt he ſhould have a ſhare in the credit of it, of which there was no great danger; for every body at firſt ſight was willing to diſcharge Mr. <hi>H.</hi> it being not eaſy to imagine, that he that could be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſuch a Book as that of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> ſhould ever be able to make any tolerable Vindication.</p>
            <p>In the next <hi>page</hi> he condemns <hi>T. W.</hi> for preferring <hi>Churchmen</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Diſſenters, (i.e.)</hi> his <hi>Friends</hi> before his <hi>Enemies.</hi> To this I ſhall only anſwer, That it is natural to all Mankind, and his own uſual practice, and therefore I may as well blame the <hi>Vindicator</hi> upon the ſame ſcore, eſpecially for ſo partially preferring Mr. <hi>H.</hi> before Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> p. 49.</p>
            <p>He boaſts, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. how <hi>early he and his Party were aware of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Popiſh deſigns.</hi> I would fain know where their Eyes were during the whole Reign of King <hi>James</hi> II. and the Toleration of King <hi>Charles,</hi> when, according to the ſenſe of all wiſe Men, the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Agents</hi> were moſt induſtrious.</p>
            <p>In all the glare of Goſpel-light theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> could ſee no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but rather did all they could to ſhelter and hide the deſign from other obſerving Proteſtants. Dr. <hi>W.</hi>—<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vox Cler.</hi> p. 10.</note>had 100 <hi>l.</hi> for writing a Book to that purpoſe. <hi>Lobb</hi> and <hi>Owen</hi> were in Fee with King <hi>James.</hi> Several of the <hi>principal Nonconformiſts</hi> aſſiſted in the management of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96210:23"/>
the <hi>Jeſuitical Intrigue.</hi> Many of their <hi>preſent Patrons</hi> were the Men pitcht upon at <hi>Court,</hi> to compleat our Ruine, by <hi>repealing the Penal Laws and Teſts,</hi> and thereby letting <hi>Papiſts</hi> into the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their <hi>Prieſts</hi> into our <hi>Churches.</hi> No Man among them <hi>opened his mouth</hi> againſt the <hi>common Foe,</hi> or endeavoured to <hi>fortify his Conventicle</hi> againſt <hi>Popiſh deluſions.</hi> And in the whole <hi>Catalogue</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of all the Diſcourſes publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Popery,</hi> during the Reign of K. <hi>James</hi> II. p. 33. printed at <hi>Lond.</hi> A. D. 1689.</note> 
               <hi>of Authors</hi> that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared during that Reign, in the <hi>defence</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> there were but <hi>Two Nonconformiſts</hi> in all <hi>England,</hi> who had the <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> to ſet Pen to Paper in thoſe Controverſies.</p>
            <p>So that altho' theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> can be aware of <hi>Popery</hi> as ſoon as any People living, (perhaps, when the greateſt danger is what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves invent) yet, as the wiſe man obſerves, <hi>A Gift blindeth the Eyes:</hi> Sprinkle a little <hi>Money</hi> among their <hi>Leaders,</hi> and give a <hi>Toleration</hi> to the reſt, that the Subjects may be paying in the <hi>Countrey,</hi> while the King pays them at <hi>London,</hi> they are all eaſy, and well ſatisfied, while they are all getting money; ſo that do what you will, they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend no danger. I appeal to the <hi>Memory</hi> of all <hi>England,</hi> whether this be not the Caſe: I appeal to your own <hi>Conſceences,</hi> wiſhing that you may repent, and beg pardon.</p>
            <p>For I muſt tell you further, (and perhaps it will be a kindneſs to let you know it) that however ſucceſsful you may ſeem to your ſelves, in preſerving your <hi>Reputatton</hi> among the <hi>leſs diſcerning Mob;</hi> yet the more <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>thinking People</hi> are very much ſcandaliz'd at theſe Practices, and ſometimes do not ſtick to ſay, <hi>That your zeal againſt</hi> Popery <hi>is all counterfeit; your deſign only to get uppermoſt; and that you can either rail againſt the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>or join with them, whether way ſoever does beſt fit your purpoſe of ruining the Church.</hi> Nay, ſome uncharitable People go further, and ſay, <hi>That ſince you join'd with</hi> Popery <hi>againſt the Church, more than ever you did with the Church againſt</hi> Popery, <hi>they are afraid leſt if that</hi> Religion <hi>ſhould prevail,</hi> (which God forbid) <hi>you would be a great deal better</hi> Conformiſts <hi>than you are now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is again angry with <hi>T.W.</hi> for mentioning thoſe great Men who have written in defence of the Church, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. and endeavours to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him with another Catalogue of baffled Names, <hi>Reynolds, Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, Blondel, Amies, Daille,</hi> &amp;c. People that have been ſo fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd and confuted by Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Pearſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dodwell,</hi> and others, that if the power of <hi>Reaſon</hi> could ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Prejudice,</hi> a Man would think there needed no further Arguings with theſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> whether this be ſo or not, we are willing to refer with him <hi>to the judgment of all diſintereſted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> if the <hi>Vindicator</hi> will but tell us where we may have a Councel of thoſe who are truly ſuch: For to me, the whole Chriſtian world ſeems to be concerned in theſe Controverſies. Thoſe who have a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as well as we; and thoſe that would have all theſe, if their circumſtances were ſo happy, are certainly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96210:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for us. And as for that ſmaller Party who are for none of theſe, and are moſt of them confined within our King's Dominions, they are all biaſſed and intereſſed againſt us; ſo that in rejecting <hi>the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of every intereſſed Party,</hi> methinks the <hi>Gentleman</hi> learnedly appeals to no body at all.</p>
            <p>Only perhaps the <hi>Turks, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> in his Opinion, may be proper Judges, who, I confeſs, are not much intereſs'd in the quarrels among <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And yet taking in all Mankind, (which muſt ſurely comprehend thoſe that lived in former Ages, as well as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and I am ſure they do not appear to be the Patrons or Friends of his <hi>Schiſm</hi>) the <hi>Jews</hi> muſt condemn him upon the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as they did the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> laid too much ſtreſs upon the buſineſs of Succeſſion; and the moſt rever'd Laws of the nobleſt body of <hi>Heathens</hi> that ever liv'd in the world, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt him:<note place="margin">Leg. <hi>12.</hi> Tab.</note> 
               <hi>Separatim nemo habeſſit Deos, neve novos neve advenas niſi publice adſcitos privatim colunto, conſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cta à Patribus delubra habento, Ritus Familiae Patriaeque ſervanto.</hi> So that I know no <hi>Patron,</hi> either <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Heathen,</hi> the <hi>Gentleman</hi> has to appeal to, unleſs it be his own ſcattered Party, or ſome of his Friends, the <hi>New Whigg Atheiſts.</hi> And as for their Judgment and Approbation, much good may it do him, I know no Man of ours that envies his happineſs.</p>
            <p>There is a wonderful vein of <hi>Argument</hi> (not to ſay <hi>Diſcretion</hi>) in his management of <hi>T. W.</hi>'s <hi>Honours,</hi> pag. 7. If he ſuppoſes any weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in himſelf, he does not pretend to be infallible. Suppoſe he makes but a ſlip in ſtyle, (which he hopes a Friend will pardon) the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance muſt neceſſarily be <hi>all vicious.</hi> But, on the contrary, if he allows a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> the leaſt grain of <hi>Chriſtian temper, humility,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> ſo as not to be totally diveſted of all three, it is enough to <hi>ſaint</hi> him, he needs trouble himſelf no further, for <hi>his condition is very hopeful,</hi> and <hi>cannot be deſperate,</hi> pag. 8.</p>
            <p>But, above all, the <hi>Addreſs</hi> to the <hi>Sceptic</hi> does moſt afflict him, eſpecially that <hi>T. W.</hi> ſhould ſuppoſe <hi>any Sceptic to be obſtinate,</hi> pag. 9. Now, for my part, I cannot perceive that ever he ſuppoſed any ſuch thing, his words are theſe: <hi>If thou be Sceptical, a ſlighter of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, obſtinate and perverſe, a deſpiſer and reviler of the Clergy.</hi> By which it is plain, <hi>T. W.</hi> intended four ſeveral Characters of thoſe who are Enemies to the Church, now there is no neceſſity that they ſhould all be united in the ſame perſon; but if they are all found among the members of the ſame Faction, (as certainly they are) it is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſufficient to acquit the <hi>Alderman.</hi> However, the witty <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> by changing <hi>Sceptical</hi> into <hi>Sceptic,</hi> and putting <hi>obſtinate</hi> to it, takes care to make <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> where otherwiſe it is not to be found. This being a part of the Ingenuity of theſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> to make <hi>Faults</hi> where they cannot find them; and to raiſe <hi>Blunders</hi> out of their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and then confute them; which ſurely is the worſt, tho' one of the eaſieſt ways of arguing that a man can chuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96210:24"/>He is mightily offended with the <hi>Alderman,</hi> for making <hi>the Ninth Article of the Apoſtles Creed the Standard whereby to diſcover Schiſm,</hi> as if it were a moſt heinous Crime, no leſs than declining the Authority of Scripture, to make uſe of it. The profeſſion of that <hi>Creed</hi> has been the badge and ſymbol of all orthodox Chriſtians, for many paſt Centuries: which certainly it would not have been, if they had not all believed it to be agreeable to the Scriprure. And unleſs theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> have a mind to extinguiſh all the former ſentiments of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> that they may the better impoſe upon the World what ever <hi>Notions</hi> they pleaſe, I know no reaſon why it ſhould now be laid aſide. 'Tis plain <hi>T. W.</hi> never intended to rival the Scripture with this Article; for he goes on immediately to explain it by the ſacred Text, tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in this Caſe he cannot be ſo happy as to pleaſe our peeviſh Author.</p>
            <p>He quarrels with him likewiſe about <hi>the Origination of the Catholic Church,</hi> and is angry that he does not date it <hi>from the Creation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> or <hi>from the Beginning of the Jewiſh Church:</hi> As if the <hi>Gentleman</hi> had never heard of the <hi>diſtinctions</hi> betwixt the <hi>Church Viſible,</hi> and <hi>Myſtical; Jewiſh,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> or ſome body or other had put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his head, that the <hi>Angels</hi> are <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> it being the <hi>Catholic Church</hi> under that denomination only that <hi>T. W.</hi> ſpoke of.</p>
            <p>When our <hi>Saviour</hi> uttered thoſe words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church;</hi> I deſire to know of the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> whether he did not ſpeak of the Church <hi>de futuro,</hi> and as yet unbuilt? And when St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſays, <hi>And the Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved;</hi> whether he did not ſpeak of it as already begun? ſo that the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> muſt have its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betwixt the time of that firſt ſaying to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and that other in St. <hi>Luke.</hi> If the <hi>Gentleman</hi> will try his <hi>Chronology,</hi> and aſſign us the year and day, we ſhall gladly hear him; but if he will ſtill derive its <hi>Epocha</hi> from the <hi>Creation of Angels,</hi> we are ready to aſſert the contrary. In the mean time he ought to be a little ſparing in his <hi>Reflections</hi> upon <hi>T. W.</hi> for if he were a Dunce, and a Blockhead, or a ridiculous Trifler for this account of the <hi>Origination</hi> of the <hi>Catholic Chriſtian Church,</hi> both<note n="*" place="margin">Probantibus actis Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum deſcenſum Spiritus Sancti quam Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram qui non recipiunt nec Spiritus Sancti eſſe poſſunt. Qui necdum Spiritum poſſint agnoſcere diſcentibus miſſum, ſed nec eccleſiam defendere qui quando &amp; quibus incunabulis institutum eſt Hoc corpus probare non habent. <hi>Tertull. de Prae. cap. 22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Acta Apoſtolorum nudam quidem ſonare videntur Hiſtoriam &amp; naſcentis Eccleſiae infantiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>xere. <hi>Hieron. Ep. 103.</hi>
               </note>, (not to ſay our <hi>Saviour</hi>) and St. <hi>Luke,</hi> muſt equally be comprehended in the ſame charge. Nay, the <hi>Vindicator</hi> himſelf grants in the next Paragraph, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> were the <hi>Church,</hi> without either <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Angels:</hi> And therefore if <hi>T. W.</hi> were a Fool for paſſing them by, I hope the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> will not diſdain to bear him company.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96210:25"/>He is mightily troubled, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. about the admiſſion of <hi>Church-Members,</hi> that it cannot be done barely <hi>upon their profeſſion of Faith, without complying with ſome ſignificant Rites that are alien to Scripture-Rules.</hi> If he had but told us plainly what he had meant, I could have given a more direct Anſwer, in the mean time let him know that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Charge.</p>
            <p>The Diſciples and Believers ſubmitted to the authority of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, in things indifferent. And if our Engliſh Diſſenters would be as juſt to their Succeſſors, according to the rules and examples re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture, no body would require more from 'em. As for the <hi>ſaying of the Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter, (which I ſuppoſe he durſt not quote, becauſe he was conſcious to himſelf that it was nothing to his purpoſe) it concerns the Papiſts only, and for what belongs to us, I refer him to many other excellent ſayings of the aforeſaid Biſhop, in his <hi>Unreaſonableneſs of Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next paragraph he complains <hi>that Chriſtianity does not make a greater progreſs in the world,</hi> and immediately charges the failure upon <hi>needleſs ceremonies, and want of worth in the managers.</hi> Now whether this be ſo or not he may eaſily try, if he will either ſend Mr. <hi>H.</hi> or go himſelf, (for I do not queſtion but he will allow both to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly well qualified) and give a call to the unconverted. Let 'em try the Emperor of <hi>China</hi> or the Cham of <hi>Tartary,</hi> or (as <hi>T. W.</hi> advis'd them) the grand Signior if he pleaſes, if the <hi>ſanctity of the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Spirituality and ſimplicity of Doctrine and Worſhip</hi> after the Congregational way; If zeal againſt Ceremonies without <hi>adoring any ſort of Religion</hi> will do the buſineſs. We ſhall ſoon ſee whether the Independent, or the Jeſuit, are more ſucceſsful (for there lies the controverſie) the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are no way concern'd, having not been much accuſtomed to travel upon that errand.</p>
            <p>It ſeems he never <hi>heard that the Apoſtles did actually preach the Goſpel to all nations,</hi> neither do I believe they did to all Countries, and to every perſon in every Nation. But if he will give us leave to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it of ſome perſons out of all Nations, (which I ſuppoſe was all that <hi>T. W.</hi> meant, and the thing is true, for) St. <hi>Peter</hi> we read preach'd <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and his Congregation conſiſted of people in all probability <hi>out of every nation under heaven,</hi> Acts 2.5.</p>
            <p>That the primitive Biſhops had the power of ordination and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (whereby their authority did exceed that of meer Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters) and that the Churches of ſeveral Presbyters were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under the government and care of one Biſhop, has been ſufficiently evinc'd by divers learned Pens: particularly that of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> (one of the famous Seven in <hi>Aſia</hi>) has been again and again prov'd to be ſo govern'd. And this is all that we need to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96210:25"/>
for; but if nothing leſs will ſatisfie him than having every Dioceſe acred, that he may know exactly <hi>the extent,</hi> (which he ſo briskly calls for, p. 13.) let him be at the charge of it himſelf, we for our parts are well contented with leſs ado, unleſs it were to more purpoſe. The primitive Dioceſes being never ſuppos'd to be all equal, but ſome greater and ſome leſs, as well as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern.</p>
            <p>Neither is it neceſſary to ſhew that their modes of worſhip were exactly the ſame with ours: the Vindicator himſelf aſſures us that they did not agree among themſelves about the circumſtances of worſhip; and then how can he expect that they ſhould all agree with us. That they us'd and impos'd things of the ſame nature with what he calls our modes, and that our Governors are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted in doing the like by their example and Authority, is all we need to ſhew; and that has been done often enough already by divers hands.</p>
            <p>We confeſs that <hi>Biſhop and Angel are not convertible terms,</hi> and yet ſuppoſe St. <hi>John</hi> had ſaid Angels of each Church in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (inſtead of Angel in the Singular); I would know how any man could prove Epiſcopacy from thoſe texts. And ſurely where an Argument may be made from the number in which a word is us'd, he is not far amiſs that ſhould ſay ſuch a thing is plain from that word.</p>
            <p>He triumphs in the next paragraph <hi>p.</hi> 14.15. as if he had found the Independent notion in one of <hi>T. W</hi>'s. aſſertions, Nay he cannot ſee <hi>how there ſhould be a multiplication or plurality of Churches till the increaſe of believers, according to the Epiſcopal model.</hi> If the Gentleman will be pleaſed to put on his ſpectacles, I will endeavour to ſhew him how. Suppoſe then that one parcel of converts were made at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Corinth,</hi> another at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> another at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and another at <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Biſhop and Presbyters conſtituted over each particular Church. I deſire him to conſider, whether this will not be the thing which <hi>T. W.</hi> ſpoke of, <hi>viz. A multiplication or plurality of Churches by the increaſe of believers,</hi> without any neceſſity of ſuppoſing that Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt multiply like Bees, only by ſending out a Colony when the Hive is too full.</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſe a Colony were ſent out under the conduct of a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, and he ſtill under the government of the ſame, or another Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, I ſuppoſe this would do the buſineſs, without any great ſervice to the Congregational way.</p>
            <p>But why did not the Vindicator give us ſome Scriptue-inſtances of this famous notion? For, <hi>if a Colony muſt needs be ſent out under indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Officers, when ever believers grow too numerous for one Aſſembly,</hi> it may ſurely be proved that ſome time or other it was ſo. And therefore
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96210:26"/>
I muſt call upon Mr. Vindicator for matter of fact, which unleſs he can produce (and I am pretty ſure he cannot) he muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that much credit ſhould be given to him: It being a little too much for him to impoſe his notions upon us, as if they were all according to Scripture; and yet not one Text to be found for them.</p>
            <p>I would fain know how many Congregations there were in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the believers increaſed to ſo vaſt a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in ſo ſhort a time: Three thouſand you meet with converted, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. More daily added, <hi>v.</hi> 47. Five thouſand you find menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.4. Multitudes both of men and women added, <hi>c.</hi> 5.14. And yet ſtill the word of God increaſed, and the number of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples multiplied in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> greatly, and a great company of the Prieſts were obedient to the faith, <hi>c.</hi> 6.7. Now I deſire him to give me his Anſwer to theſe following Queries: Whether all this number of Believers did make one Congregation or more? Whether or no they were under the Government of only one Biſhop? Whether each of them was known to his Biſhop, and to one another? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they could not be Members of the ſame Church, till they were all perſonally acquainted? Did they all ordinarily meet in one place to worſhip God? And if ſo, where was it? Were the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious? Or did the Jews lend the Temple for an ordinary Meeting-place to the Chriſtians? How the Preacher could be heard by all this Multitude at once? Whether the vigor and ſtrength of his Lungs, or the thinneſs of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> air, did enable and qualifie him for that loud Performance? Or whether he had the Conqueror's Engine, or Sir <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Morland</hi>'s Speaking Trumpet? Or a peculiar ſort of voice (like Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Friend, who preach'd to a Congregation of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, ſo that they could all hear him, and yet his voice was none of the loudeſt) I deſire his information in theſe particulars, that we may ſee whether it be likely that the Church of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> did increaſe and multiply in the Congregational way: but we hope he will not ſtir a ſyllable from the ſacred Text, that being no way proper for a man that receives nothing but expreſs Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph he falls foul upon one of his own blunders. And becauſe <hi>T. W.</hi> affirms that all other Churches were one with that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> all united in one body, under one head Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, thinks he confounds him mightily by proving a variety in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of worſhip (as if to ſay) that thoſe Churches were united in one body, and that all Members agreed in every circumſtance of worſhip, were the ſame thing, and he that confutes the latter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes the former alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96210:26"/>He might have conſider'd, that even in that variety, many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Apoſtolical Churches</hi> were the ſame. The <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> and moſt others, were made out of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who had the ſame different apprehenſions about <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies,</hi> as well as that at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> And therefore the difference was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> but betwixt the Members of the <hi>ſame Churches,</hi> who were left at liberty by the <hi>Apoſtolical Synod,</hi> except in three things; And for that Reaſon the <hi>Gentile Diſſenters</hi> cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be the <hi>Patrons</hi> of ours, unleſs the Vindicator can ſhew, that the <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies</hi> were impos'd, as ours are, by ſome <hi>Christian Church.</hi> If he can prove, that Rules were given, and Matters of Decence impos'd, and that any <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in that Age refus'd to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to 'em, let him name 'em, as the Precedents of his Cauſe and Party; I dare ſay, That every <hi>Churchman</hi> will allow 'em to be ſo.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph he is fond of the Notion which he quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell'd with in the laſt (ſo inconſtant are thoſe people that know not what they would have). It fits the <hi>Independents</hi> as exactly as if it had been made for 'em; for <hi>they hold a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity for Subſtance</hi> (tho not for <hi>Circumſtances); they are united to all true Churches,</hi> tho for <hi>condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhops</hi> (who are doubtleſs the principal and moſt neceſſary Members); <hi>they partake of the ſame Table,</hi> tho they ſet up <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar; they are the ſame with us in the External Worſhip and Service of God,</hi> tho in <hi>Covenant</hi> againſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they refuſe to communicate with us either in <hi>Sacraments</hi> or <hi>Prayers.</hi> They are <hi>all united to the Head,</hi> tho not into one <hi>Body,</hi> either among themſelves or with others: For that part of Unity I obſerve the Gent. paſſes over, and with a great deal of Reaſon, it being hard to find ſeveral Members united into One Body, and yet ſtill remaining all independent. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from others is <hi>according to the Apoſtolical Mode;</hi> That wherein others differ from them, is nothing but <hi>Innovation;</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>they are the ſame with all true Churches,</hi> if you will believe this Gent. To all which I ſhall only apply, and argue in the plain words of St. <hi>John;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would, no doubt, have continued with us; but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt that they were not all of us,</hi> 1 John 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Continuance</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> he agrees with us, <hi>p.</hi> 17. Only about the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Apostles</hi> he is pleas'd to fall out, <hi>not apprehending how any Man can ſucceed the Apoſtles in their Apoſtolical Power.</hi> If he means the <hi>Authority</hi> they had in the <hi>Church (i. e.)</hi> over the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and other Members, we affirm <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be their <hi>Succ ſſors;</hi> it being not reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that any <hi>Branch of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th rity</hi> given by our Saviour to his Apoſtles died with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for if their <hi>Authority</hi> over the <hi>Presbyters</hi> expir'd with their <hi>Perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> why ſhould that over the <hi>People</hi> continue after 'em, unleſs the Gentleman
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96210:27"/>
will ſuppoſe (which I ſuppoſe he will not) that the <hi>Laity</hi> are the <hi>only perſons</hi> that need the <hi>Regulation of Superiours. All Multitudes</hi> muſt have Governours, and the common <hi>Presbyters</hi> are certainly oo Numerou: a Populace to be <hi>all</hi> independent. Let 'em ſubmit therefore to <hi>Biſhops</hi> their Succeſſors, as they did to the <hi>Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> eſpecially till ſuch times as you can find a Text to prove, That the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Commiſſion was <hi>only a Patent for Life;</hi> it being a Matter of ſuch Conſequence in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> that few will believe you upon your own bare Word.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, and extended to the whole World, and was the ſame in all Churches,</hi> p. 18. ſo <hi>Biſhops</hi> do ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them in the ſame <hi>Authority.</hi> And if it were not for thoſe Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Agreements (which the <hi>Vindicator</hi> cannot diſallow), the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment Eccleſiaſtical muſt be ſo exerciſed; And I could wiſh the Gentleman would be pleas'd to conſider, whether a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is not as truly a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> as much a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in any other Man's Dioceſs or Pariſh, as he is in his own? Is he ſuſpended or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived when he's out of his own bounds? If not, I hope he may be a Miniſter, like the Apoſtles, all the World over. And yet the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Miniſtry confin'd within certain limits. Nor do's this Notion <hi>give the Pope any greater power in England,</hi> than it do's the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> (which is none at all.) On the contrary, if Ordinary Paſtors are Paſtors only within their own Precincts, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and his <hi>Vindicator</hi> (tho Ordain'd) can be none, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they exerciſe their pretended Miniſtry in other Mens Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>He will not diſpute the Epiſcopal Juriſdiction of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> but he tells us, <hi>it ſignifies nothing till the nature and extent of that Office be firſt determin'd out of Scripture,</hi> p. 18. As if the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were no Scripture. We find <hi>Timothy</hi> appointed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to examine the Qualifications of ſuch as were to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd; to lay hands ſuddenly on no Man; to receive Accuſations, and proceed judicially; and to rebuke before all even Elders them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if there were occaſion. <hi>Titus</hi> was to ordain Elders in every City, to ſet things in order, to rebuke with all authority, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and reject heretics. And this power of Ordination and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction wherewith <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were inveſted, is what the Biſhops have all along exerciſed, and do ſtill challenge at this day; and therefore we juſtify the preſent Epiſcopal Authority by theſe two Scripture-Inſtances. And as the <hi>Congregational Invention</hi> allows of no ſuch Officers, the moſt Ordinary Paſtors (call 'em <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or what you will) being all independent, without ever a <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> to ſuperviſe and govern 'em; by the ſame Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it ſtands condemn'd, and is plainly contrary to the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Pattern.</p>
            <p>And if the Office of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus was itinerant, by reaſon of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96210:27"/>
their frequent Removes from place to place</hi> (as the Gent. ſuppoſes, <hi>p.</hi> 19.) our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are extreamly like 'em in that particular, their Office being always very itinerant in their <hi>Epiſcopal Viſitations.</hi> But this is an idle Fancy, which he probably learn'd from Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (an idle one I call it); for if the Office of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> was really iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant, they were certainly out of their Office while they ſtaid at home, the one in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and the other in <hi>Crete</hi> (tho doing that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buſineſs for which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> plac'd 'em there) which how well it agrees with Scripture and common Sence, let every diſcerning Reader judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If none beſides St.</hi> Paul <hi>were concern'd in the Ordination of</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Sed quod ab uno Apoſtolo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum est id ab omnibus ſimul Apoſtolis geſtum eſſe dicitur ob Collegium &amp; Conſortium A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolatus Valeſ. Annot. in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>org. H. E. <hi>l. 3. c. 15.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sub impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore Claudio loco duorum unicus Praefectus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio Conſtitutus eſt Burrhus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franius. Sub Nerone Burrho mortuo duo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti praetorio conſtituti ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t ut unius ſucceſſores. Pearſ. de ſucceſſ. Diſſ. <hi>1.</hi> C.IX. ubi plura in hujus argumenti fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, allata le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Joſ. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. ult.</p>
                  <p>Auguſtus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbana villa Nicomedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> triceſſimo &amp; primo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Imperii ſui anno diem functus eſt liberis de<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſucceſſione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Orbis teſtamento Haeredibus ſcriptis. Ruffin. <hi>H. E.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> it ſurely juſtifies the preſent <hi>Ordinations</hi> by a ſingle Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; <hi>but if others joyn'd with him in Impoſition of Hands,</hi> as the Gent. ſuppoſes in the following p. <hi>T. W.</hi> was not much out; ſeveral of the Primitive Biſhops being Styl'd <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by the Ancients, as well as the Twelve: And therefore before he had condemn'd <hi>T.W.</hi> he ought to have told us who thoſe were that laid on hands with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and to demonſtrate 'em Unworthy of that Title. But it is ſufficient to juſtifie <hi>T. W.</hi> that what is done only by one, has been commonly ſaid to be done by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> by reaſon of their being Colleagues, and Partners in the ſame Apoſtleſhip.</p>
            <p>I dare anſwer for <hi>T. W.</hi> That this Man's Notion of a proper <hi>Succeſſion</hi> never enter'd into his head; No Man beſides <hi>Blondel,</hi> and his quarrelſome Brethren, ever reckoning it improper to call Two perſons the Succeſſors of One, when really they are ſo. When Two Perſons are <hi>Heirs</hi> to One, in the ſame Eſtate, or ſucceed him in his Authority, they are call'd by <hi>Civilians</hi> (and I believe not improperly) <hi>Haeredes,</hi> or <hi>Succeſſores partiarii.</hi> When the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire became divided, I would fain know, whether <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> and <hi>Jovian,</hi> &amp;c. had no <hi>Succeſſors?</hi> And I hope the Gent. will allow Their Majeſties, K. <hi>W.</hi> and Q. <hi>M.</hi> to be call'd the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of K. <hi>J.</hi> without any great Abſurdity. And as there are Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces enough to be given of Two Perſons ſucceeding One in his Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Eſtate and Authority, ſo I know no Reaſon, why Two Biſhops may not as well ſucceed One <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the Eccleſiaſtical. The lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the <hi>Apoſtles Province</hi> was, the more <hi>Diviſions</hi> it was capable of, and conſequently the more <hi>Succeſſors</hi> he might have; <hi>Timothy</hi> might ſucceed him at <hi>Epheſus, Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> &amp;c. Nor does this ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Apostle</hi> in theſe Two Provinces, <hi>give 'em an equal Power in one another's Dioceſſes</hi> (as the <hi>Vindicator</hi> ſuppoſes, p. 19.) any more than the King of <hi>Spain</hi> has Power at <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Roman Emperors</hi> are number'd amongſt his <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Taraph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and other <hi>Spaniſh Hiſtorians.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:96210:28"/>
            <p>Nor is there any neceſſity to ſuppoſe (as the Gent. would inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate), that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> muſt either be <hi>ſuspended, or degraded, or tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to an higher Seat,</hi> to make room for the Succeſſion of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> in the Sees of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Crete:</hi> For it is evident, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f gave them a Plenitude of Power within their reſpective Charges (chuſe how much or how little he reſerv'd to himſelf.) So that they had the full Ordering and Government of <hi>thoſe Two Churches,</hi> and did therefore ſucceed the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in it, even while he was alive.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Vindicator</hi> will needs call 'em the <hi>Apoſtle's Coadjutors,</hi> while he was alive, and give 'em the Title of <hi>Succeſſors</hi> only, after his Deceaſe, I know <hi>T. W.</hi> will not quarrel with him; it being no way contrary to any thing he hath ſaid. In the mean time I muſt deſire him to forbear making wry Faces. If any one ſhall ſtill aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> Ordain'd his <hi>Succeſſors</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Crete;</hi> for as it is impoſſible, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhould have any <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> unleſs ordain'd by themſelves; nor very probable that they ordain'd 'em when they were dead: So according to the Opinion of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and common Senſe, they are ſaid by <hi>T. W.</hi> to ordain 'em while they were alive. Thus <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. adv. Haereſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ab Apoſtolis inſtituti ſunt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi—quos &amp; Succeſſores relinquebant ſuum ipſorum locum Magiſterii tradentes.</hi> And a little after, ſpeaking concerning the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome, Fundantes igitur &amp; inſtruentes beati Apoſtoli Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Lino Epiſcopatum adminiſtrandae Eccleſiae tradiderunt.</hi> From which Two Paſſages it is plain, That the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ordain'd <hi>Biſhops</hi> their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> while they were alive, and that <hi>Linus,</hi> a ſingle Perſon, ſucceeded the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the plural; which is the <hi>double blunder,</hi> in expreſs terms, wherewith our nimble-ſighted Author charges <hi>T.W.</hi> p. 20. Nor will <hi>Tertullion</hi> eaſily free himſelf from our Author's Cenſure, if he ever hears of that Paſſage <hi>de Praeſcript. c.</hi> 32. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volvant Ordinem Epiſcoporum ſuorum ita per Succeſſiones ad initia decur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem, ut primus ille Epiſcopus aliquem ex Apostolis, vel Apostolicis viris, qui tamen cum Apoſtolis perſeveraverit habuerit Autotem &amp; Anteceſſorem. Hoc enim modo Eccleſiae Apoſtolicae cenſus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>os deferunt, ſicut Smyrnaeorum Eccleſia Polycarpum à Joanne Collocatum, ſicut Romanorum Clementem à Petro ordinatum itidem perinde uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; caeterae exhibent quos ab Apoſtolis in Epiſcopatum Conſtitutos Apoſtolici Seminis traduces habeant.</hi> So that according to <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Con. Antioch.</hi> c. 23.</note> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ordain'd the firſt <hi>Biſhops</hi> in each <hi>Church,</hi> and were their <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> and they the <hi>Apoſtles Succeſſors.</hi> Nor was it ever thought ſo great a Myſtery, by Men of Sence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ancient or Latter Ages, for a Biſhop, or other Perſon, to ordain or conſtitute his Succeſſor, as this Man makes it. The Council of <hi>Antioch</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rees it Unlawful for a Biſhop to conſtitute his Succeſſor: But if (according to the Opinion of our Author) they had thought it a thing impoſſible, they would certainly have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96210:28"/>
ſpar'd their Pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, it being not very uſual for Wiſe Men to make Laws againſt Impoſſibilities. <hi>Valerius</hi> ordained St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his Succeſſor, and he <hi>Heraclius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Auguſtine</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> ordained <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius</hi> to ſucceed him in that See, according to <hi>Bede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bedae Ec. Hist. l. 2. c. 40. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Epiph. Haer.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>who</hi> (ſays he) <hi>did it after the Example of</hi> St. Peter, who is ſaid to have conſecrated <hi>Clemens, evangelizandi adjutorem &amp; ſimul Succeſſorem;</hi> And <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> gives the Reaſon, why other Perſons were made Biſhops in the Life-time of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> even becauſe <hi>the Apoſtles did frequently travel into other Countries to preach the Goſpel, and the City of</hi> Rome <hi>could not be without a Biſhop:</hi> To which I might add, That <hi>Severus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Milevis,</hi> and <hi>Boniface,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> did, after the Example of the Apoſtles, ordain Perſons to ſucceed 'em in thoſe Sees. And now ſurely nothing but <hi>that Faculty of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> (if there be ſuch a Faculty) wherewith he reproaches <hi>T. W.</hi> p. 21. cou'd have embolden'd this <hi>Vindicator</hi> to charge a Man with Nonſence and Blunder, for aſſerting plain Matter of Fact, when there are ſo many Inſtances to be found of the ſame Nature, according to the Sence and Practice of ſeveral Ages.</p>
            <p>I fancy few, beſides this confident Author, will deny <hi>Linus</hi> to be the Succeſſor of the Apoſtles; and yet that he died before 'em, is maintain'd by Biſhop<note n="*" place="margin">Pearſ. de ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ. Diſſ. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Vid. etiam Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delin. de Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Temp.</note> 
               <hi>Pearſon,</hi> who, tho he was a Learn'd as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>roti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> yet he is as poſitive as <hi>T. W.</hi> that <hi>Linus</hi> immediately ſucceeded the Apoſtles in the <hi>Roman Chair.</hi> And therefore I cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that our Author ſhould pretend, <hi>That all the Learned Men in the World deliver 'emſelves timorouſly and uncertainly about this matter.</hi> It is a Caution that <hi>Reeb,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> gives all young Students, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how they aſſert a thing to be the Opinion of All Authors: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if any one happen to be of a contrary mind, you are quite ſham'd.</hi> Now here's ſome Modeſty in a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> but ſuch is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of this <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> that he pretends to tell you the Sence of all the Learned Men in the World (tho he never heard of their Names), as readily as if he himſelf had been one of 'em, or at leaſt, they had been his Familiars, and moſt intimate Acquaintance.</p>
            <p>With the ſame Gaiety, he affirms in the ſame page, <hi>That to ſay the Line of Apoſtolick Succeſſion of Biſhops hath continued in all Ages to this preſent time, is an Aſſertion without the leaſt ſhadow of Proof; yea, contrary to the Acknowledgment of all Church-Hiſtorians,</hi> p. 21. Pray, Sir, what Church-Hiſtorians ever acknowledg'd the contrary? A Man would imagine, that he meant only thoſe of his Party, who have been a Scandal to their Undertaking;<note place="margin">Nihil clarius in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ota veterum Doctrina ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pontificum, <hi>Phil. le Pr.</hi> in not. ad Tert. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re. c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> or elſe, if otherwiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t could be done, he needed not to have been aſham'd to have given us their Names; but I am afraid, he is no better acquainted with Church-Hiſtorians, than with other Learned Men.</p>
            <p>Only as to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> (ſo lately his Cronies), we may, I ſuppoſe, take his word, <hi>that they own inſuperable Difficulties about the Succeſſion of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96210:29"/>
Popes in the</hi> Roman <hi>See,</hi> p. 22. But what is this to the purpoſe? they neither deny, nor doubt, that there was a Succeſſion (altho, for want of Writings, they cannot determine the Order wherein thoſe Biſhops ſucceeded). There are Difficulties concerning the Succeſſion of Monarchs in ſeveral Kingdoms, not eaſily ſolv'd for want of Authors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And yet to ſay, All Catalogues are falſe, becauſe we cannot tell certainly which is true, or becauſe (through diſtance of time, and want of Authors) we cannot tell who firſt ſucceeded: To conclude that there was no Succeſſion at all, is a way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peculiar to its Author.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Irenaeus could Name all the Succeſſors in the Apoſtolick Churches,</hi> as the Gent. grants in the fore-cited page, I preſume he could not be miſtaken in the Succeſſion of <hi>Linus.</hi> And if this <hi>Vindicator</hi> had been but ſo learn'd, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to be acquainted with that Father, he would not have been ſo Angry with <hi>T. W.</hi> p. 21. for Aſſerting the ſame thing that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> does.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> I ſhall not trouble my ſelf with his Miſtake about the Year of that Father's Death; for tho he diſputed about the buſineſs of <hi>Eaſter</hi> Seven Years after that, in which (as ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy told this Gent.) he died; yet it is no great matter, ſince hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays will ſerve a <hi>Nonconformist</hi> inſtead of Chronology.</p>
            <p>With the ſame Skill he proceeds to enquire, <hi>how it came to paſs that the Apoſtolical Succeſſion was propagated in ſo few Churches as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchal were?</hi> As if it were the Opinion of any body, that no Biſhop, beſides the Patriarchs, did any where ſucceed the Apoſtles. If he ever met with ſuch an Aſſertion, let him tell us whoſe it is: In the mean time, if (for want of Argument, and Underſtanding in theſe Controverſies) he quarrels with his own <hi>Chimoera's,</hi> I hope it is not to be call'd a <hi>Confutation</hi> of <hi>T. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Biſhops;</hi> ſo that we can name 'em as they ſucceeded, ſo far as we have <hi>Hiſtory</hi> to inform us, which is for many Centuries. And as we find the Succeſſion Regular, where we have a clear Account; ſo we have no Reaſon to doubt of the like Care in former Ages; which is ſatisfaction enough to us, that our preſent Miniſtry is regularly deriv'd from the Apoſtles. And he that ſhall Aſſert the contrary, ſo as to make us doubt of it, muſt bring proof from good Authors, That the Succeſſion was interrupted, or elſe he will be but a feeble Expoſer of our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. It is not ſufficient to ſay, <hi>we are uncertain whether we have any true Miniſtry or Ordinance,</hi> p. 23. we rely upon the Providence of God, and the Care and Integrity of our Anceſtors, for a Right Succeſſion of Miniſters, as well as pure and genuine Scriptures. And altho we have not the Original Manuſcripts to compare the one, not intire <hi>Faſti</hi> in the other caſe; yet no Man ſhall bereave us of our Confidence, unleſs he can produce Matter of Fact, and ſhew, that we are deceiv'd upon either Account. I fancy the <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96210:29"/>
does verily believe, that he came regularly from <hi>Adam;</hi> and yet ſuppoſe any one ſhould object, that he cannot tell his own Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and give a Series of his Anceſtors down from <hi>Adam</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and conclude, that the Succeſſion might therefore be <hi>broken;</hi> ſome one of his <hi>Progenitors</hi> might have ne're a Father; and ſince he has not <hi>History</hi> to inform him perfectly in the Caſe, he ought not poſitively to affirm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That he is of the Seed of <hi>Adam:</hi> Would the Gent. take this way of Arguing to be ſtrong and concluſive? if not, I would fain know what occaſion we have given him to impoſe it upon us.</p>
            <p>But that he may not ſeem to talk wildly, and without any manner of Ground, he puts Two Caſes, which I preſume were all he could think of, wherein the Line of Succeſſion might be broken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>p</hi> 24. The firſt is, <hi>If there ſhould happen a Vacancy in any of the Apostolical Churches, and Sees, for ſome Years, and the ſucceeding Incumbent be a Perſon ordain'd by an Abbot, who is no Biſhop (as the</hi> Northumbrian <hi>Biſhops were by the Abbot of</hi> Hy, ſays the Margine), <hi>as is allowed in the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, through which this Authority must be convey'd to us; Does not this make an Interciſion in the Line of Epiſcopal Ordination ſo indispenſible?</hi> It muſt do ſo, if you will believe this Author, <hi>p.</hi> 25. But I ſay, there is no Nece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y of the Line being broken, tho we grant the whole Caſe; For ſuppoſe, that all that Succeſſion of pretended Biſhops deriv'd from the Abbot, ſhould be at laſt extinct, and the true Biſhops of that, or a Neighbouring Province, called in to conſecrate, the Line of Epiſcopal Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be right enough, notwithſtanding the Abbot, and all his Uſurpers. Or ſuppoſe, that after the Biſhop was ordain'd by the Abbot, One or Two Rightful Biſhops ſhould joyn with him in the Conſecration of the next, in this Caſe the Line would be right enough; and all that can be ſaid is, That there was One <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> in the Line of Juriſdiction, who never was within the Line of Order, and conſequently could make no interciſion in it.</p>
            <p>And perhaps to prevent any Irregularity in the Succeſſion of that Order, the Apoſtles gave the Example, and the Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd, That a Biſhop ſhould be ordain'd by Three at leaſt;<note place="margin">Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st. c. <hi>1.</hi> Con. Nican. c. <hi>4.</hi> Con. Are<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. c. <hi>21.</hi> Con. Laodic. c. <hi>12.</hi> Con. Pariſ. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and likewiſe, that he ſhould be Conſtituted with the Approbation of his Metropolitan, and Com-Provincials; which practices were certainly a very great ſecurity to the Right Succeſſion, it being not very likely, That all the Biſhops of a Province ſhould be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly careleſs, to ſuffer an irregular Ordination, and the Perſons concern'd to Conſecrate all void of that Character, which they pretended to beſtow.</p>
            <p>After all, That ever any Abbot that was no Biſhop, did ordain Biſhops, I do utterly deny. <hi>Adamnanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in his Life of <hi>Columba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Adamn. Vit. Col. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſh. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> makes mention of a Biſhop in the Abby of <hi>Hy;</hi> and that there was always one reſiding there, is confirmed by Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96210:30"/>
of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Annals:</hi> And perhaps the Biſhop of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nkeld</hi> (as the Learned Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> conjectures) joyn'd in the Conſecration of Biſhop <hi>Aldan, Finan;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bp. of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h. Gov. <hi>p.</hi> 102.</note> and <hi>Colman</hi> had the like <hi>Ordination:</hi> But <hi>Tuda,</hi> the next in <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> was ordain'd a Biſhop among the <hi>South Scots</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> So that ſhould we allow his Inſtance true, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dan, Finan,</hi> and <hi>Colman,</hi> were ordained by the Abbot, yet that Succeſſion at <hi>Lindisfarn,</hi> in all likelihood, fail'd in <hi>Colman,</hi> and the Line of Order was right in <hi>Tuda<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and conſequently, his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Inſtance is nothing to the purpoſe; an Inſtance that has been frequently urg'd by the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> againſt Epiſcopacy, and as often confuted from the moſt Authentick Hiſtory of thoſe Times by divers Learned Men:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vind.</hi> C. E. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Vind. Ignat. par.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Orig. Brit.</hi> Ch. Gov. <hi>c.</hi> 5. Barboſ. Paſt. p. 2. All. 3. Num. 3.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Maur. de Alz. de Prac. Epiſc. Dig. p. 2. c. 5. Num. 6, 7, 8, 9. Aquin. Sup. q. 38. ar. 1. Reſ. ad ter. Vid. Victor. in Sum. Num. 216. Sect. de Sac. Ord. Non facile cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>em Victor. in ſum. Num. 237. quem ſeq. Vivald in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del. aureo. p. 1. tit. de Sacram. Ordin. Num. 17. In fine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerenti ſe vidiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe quandam Bullam Papae concedentem facultatem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendi Diac. &amp; Sub. Diac. Barboſ. Paſt. p. 2. Al. 3. <hi>N.</hi> 4. Ap. c. 67. Nicaen. c. 19. Con. C. P. c. 4</note> Biſhop <hi>Bramh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Pearſon,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dodwell,</hi> have ſo fully Anſwer'd this buſineſs of <hi>Hy,</hi> that a Man would wonder at the Confidence of this Gent. that he ſhould ſtill hope to impoſe the ſame Miſtake upon the World.</p>
            <p>Nor does the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> allow that an Abbot who is no Biſhop ſhould Conſecrate a Biſhop. They are ſo far from allowing it, that their Canoniſts generally declare, that the Pope himſelf cannot impower any Presbyter to Ordain ſo much as a Deacon. An Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot who has <hi>Jus Mitrae &amp; Bacu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a Cardinal or an Ordinary Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter by Commiſſion from the Pope may confer the leſſer Orders, but not the greater, or thoſe which are called Sacred, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe of Biſhop, Prieſt, and Deacon; nay even as to the leſſer, <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Joh. Major,</hi> and <hi>Paludanus</hi> Affirm, that it is ſafer to receive the Order of Sub-Deacon from another, than from ſuch a priviledged Presbyter: And altho <hi>Anguianus</hi> and ſome few more are of opinion that the Pope might Impower a Presbyter to confer the Higer Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet it never was the allowed practice of that Church. And I challenge him to produce ſo much as one inſtance of any Abb t that was no Biſhop, who ever Conſecrated a Biſhop. As for Sub-Deacons and ſuch people, who are ſometimes Ordain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d by Abbots, the Gentileman knows well enough we have no occaſion for 'em, in <hi>England,</hi> and therefore the Succeſſion of our Biſhops may be juſt and regular notwithſtanding this firſt Caſe.</p>
            <p>As to the Second, <hi>viz. Whether this line of Ordina ion may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in a Schiſmatical Church?</hi> We Anſwer, 1ſt. That ſuch was the care of the Primitive Church, ſo great a regard they had to a right Succ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, that they who thought the Ordination of certain Hereticks void ſuch as the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lianiſts</hi> and <hi>Montaniſts <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
&amp;c.</hi> decreed 'em to be Ordained by a Catholick Biſhop. And it is likewiſe determin'd by the firſt Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> concerning the Ordinations made by <hi>Maximus Cymicus,</hi> that they are all null<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they neither allowing him to be a Biſhop not thoſe Ordained by him to enjoy any Function among the Clergy. And in the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96210:30"/>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Church,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>9. p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pont. <hi>p. 22.4.</hi> Contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanum, III. al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s IV. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bill. in Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. Com. <hi>p. cxix.</hi>
               </note> particularly thoſe ordain'd by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (the Lay-Invader of the Papal Chair), were by a Council under <hi>Stephen</hi> the Third or Fourth, to return to their former Orders, (unleſs they were in great Eſteem with the People, and in that Caſe they were to be re-ordain'd by the <hi>Church;</hi> and for fear of laying the Foundations of a future Schiſm, it was further decreed, That none of 'em ſhould be promoted to any higher degrees. By theſe and many other Inſtances, it is plain what Care the Church has taken to re-ordain, or utterly ſilence thoſe whoſe Orders they thought void.</p>
            <p>And leſt any ſuch perſons ſhould creep into ſtrange places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there invade that Office to which they had no Right: No Man, either of the Clergy or Laity,<note place="margin">Ap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12. con. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 30 con. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c. 33. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> C. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c. 7. con. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 12. con. Elizbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 51.</note> was to hold Communion with 'em, under pain of incurring the Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No Clergy Man was to go abroad without Commendatory Letters; no bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to be ordain'd without the Knowledge and Conſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of his Metropolitan, and the Neighbouring Biſhops; No Heretick to be admitted into Orders; and if ordain'd to be depos'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No Man to ordain in another's Province: By which, and ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l other <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> it became extreamly difficult for any ſuch Hereticks or Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, whoſe Orders they thought void to make any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interciſion in the Line of <hi>Succeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I can ſee no Reaſon, why the Line of <hi>Ordination</hi> may not paſs through a <hi>Schiſmatical Church;</hi> For although by Schiſm People are out of the Church, and while they continue ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cannot enjoy the benefit either of <hi>Ordination</hi> or <hi>Sacraments;</hi> yet to ſay. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h are abſolutely deſtroy'd, and nullify'd; ſo that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>matick l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Characters, and can neither be a <hi>Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (i. e.)</hi> not the Subject of Apoſtolical Power, 'till he be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> baptiz'd and ordain'd, is an Aſſertion beyond all that I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>d ever yet meet with. The <hi>Meleti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> were Schiſmaticks, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>Meletius</hi> were receiv'd into places where oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> though the <hi>Paulianiſts</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were to be re-baptiz'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ordain'd by the 19th <hi>Canon</hi> of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by the <hi>Nova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ibid c. 8.</note> when reconcil'd to the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were to continue in the ſame Station which they enjoy'd before (except Catholick were in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeſſion) by the 8th <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the very ſame Council. From which Inſtances it is plain, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Sence of thoſe Fathers; though Schiſmatical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieties were out of the Church, yet it did not wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>Y d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Character, ſo as to make 'em <hi>no longer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="8+ letters">
                     <desc>〈8… letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal Power,</hi> as this <hi>Vindicator</hi> would inſinuate.</p>
            <p>Nay, the ſevereſt Enemies <hi>to Heretical Ordination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> never went ſo far as <hi>our A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>or,</hi> as appears from what they declare in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lel Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Baptiſm. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> himſelf owns the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96210:31"/>
in his days to admit reconciled Hereticks,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Vid. Cypr. ad Quinte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Steph. ap. Cyp. ad Pomp. cp. 74. Creſcent. ap. Conc. Carthag.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ap Euſ. H. E. l. 7. c. 7.</p>
                  <p>Ec. Hiſ. l. 1. c. 9. Apoſ. c. 67. Con. Nic. Can. 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ap. Cypr. Ed. Ox. Ep. LXXV. Novatus à Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>umagade ap. Con. Carth.</p>
               </note> as Penitents only with Impoſition of Hands, if at firſt they were Baptiz'd by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Clergy. And ſo <hi>Heraclas</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> took care that ſuch perſons ſhould renounce their Hereſies, not at all requiring 'em to be Rebaptiz'd. And in like manner <hi>Miletius</hi> retain'd his Character tho debarr'd the exerciſe of his Function by the Decree of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, as appears by their Synodical Epiſtle in <hi>Socrates.</hi> So that here the caſe of Baptiſm and Ordination run parallel: neither being made void by meer Hereſie or Schiſm, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we find them put together in ſeveral Ancient Canons, and in <hi>Firmilianus</hi>'s Epiſtle to St. <hi>Cyprian, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true the caſe was otherwiſe with thoſe Baptized or Ordained by Hereticks or Schiſmaticks; they were to be Reordain'd and Rebaptiz'd, according to the Sentiments of thoſe <hi>African</hi> Fathers. How conſiſtently with their own practice let others judge; for if Hereticks or Schiſmaticks, did retain their Character while they were out of the Church, as thoſe Fathers ſeem to allow, I can ſee no reaſon why it ſhould be totally out of their Power to confer the like upon other Perſons; for if it be ſaid that they loſt their Character, by departing from the Church, how they could obtain it again, without a new Ordination is paſt my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: And therefore why <hi>Miletius</hi> himſelf ſhould retain his Character,<note place="margin">Socr. ubi. ſup.</note> and yet thoſe Ordain'd by him be confirmed or ſetled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (if by thoſe words is really meant a Second Ordination) I muſt learn from others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Iren. adv. Haer. l. 1. c. 18.</note>As for the groſſer Hereticks, that lived before the time of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and whoſe ſeveral manners of Baptizing were ſo Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and Wicked, I cannot wonder if the Ancients thought fit to Baptize them over again: Their former Baptiſm wanting the neceſſary words, and being Conſequently void in the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, and therefore when <hi>Tertullian</hi> and other Fathers reject their Baptiſm, I am of opinion it makes little for St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Cauſe. So that notwithſtanding the Teſtimonies produced by a Learned Author,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aun. Ep. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Agrippinus</hi> might be the firſt introducer of that Practice, as <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> teſtifies:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Vincen. Lirin. Com. c. 9. p. 21. Edit. Cantab. 1687.</p>
                  <p>Ap. Cyp. ut Supra. Vid. &amp; Cyp. ipſum in Ep. ad Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>aian</p>
               </note> And this I am the rather induc'd to believe be, cauſe Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> then condemn'd it, as a Novel Cuſtom, and <hi>Firmilianus</hi> and other <hi>Africans,</hi> ſeem to own, at leaſt could not deny that it was ſo, as appears by the Anſwer they made to that Objection.</p>
            <p>So that by the moſt conſtant uſage of the Church in thoſe firſt Ages, the Baptiſm of Hereticks was not to be admitted in groſs, neither was it Univerſally to be rejected upon St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Principles: there being a difference to be made betwixt thoſe Hereticks who did not really Baptize at all, and thoſe that did. And ſo you find both the firſt and ſecond Councils of <hi>Arles,</hi> admit ſuch as were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96210:31"/>
in the <hi>Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Con. Arcl. c. 8. 2. Con. Arcl. c. 16. 17. Optat. 1. 4.</note> and Rebaptiſing only thoſe that did not believe in the Trinity, nor Conſequently uſe the Eſſential Form, and ſo <hi>Optatus</hi> declares, <hi>Quodcunque in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate factum eſt bene factum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like diſtinction I reckon is to be made concerning Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe who derived their Orders only from Hereticks, and Conſequently never had any Succeſſion from the Church, were juſtly to be reputed as Unordain'd, but thoſe Ordain'd by Hereticks, who had their Ordination originally from the Church, and did not omit any thing neceſſary to the conferring of Orders, had no occaſion for Reordination. And to let paſs the diſtinction betwixt the <hi>Novatians,</hi> and <hi>Cataphrygae,</hi> made by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, <hi>Optatus</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> have both of 'em ſettled the point in their Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy with the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Vinc. Lirin. c. 11. p. 26. Ed. Cant. 1687</note> who pretended the Authority of the <hi>African</hi> Council, for Rebaptizing the Catholicks. Thus<note n="(b)" place="margin">In hoc Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmatis Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brando tres eſſe Species Conſtat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Optat. l. 5. p. 143. Edit. Com. 1599.</note> 
               <hi>Optatus in Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the Sacrament of Baptiſm, there are three kinds of things which you can neither increaſe, nor diminiſh, nor pretermit: The</hi> 1ſt. <hi>is the Trinity. The</hi> 2d. <hi>in him that Believes. The</hi> 3d. <hi>in him that does the Office, but they are not all to be eſteem'd of equal moment: For I look upon two of 'em to be neceſſary, and one as if it were neceſſary. The Trinity obtains the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal place, the Faith of him that Believes comes next after this, and the Perſon of him that Miniſters is nigh, but cannot be of the ſame Authority. The two former remain always unalterable, and fixt, for the Trinity is always the ſame, and the Faith in ſeveral Perſons is but one, both always retain their proper Efficacy, but the Perſon of him that Miniſters is known that it cannot be equal to the two former ſorts, for this reaſon, becauſe it alone appears to be alterable.</hi> &amp;c. And<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. p. 141, 142.</note> a little before he acquaints us with the practice of the Church at that time: <hi>As oft as any one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by you</hi> (i. e. the Donatiſts) <hi>deſires to come over to us, we receive him according to the Example of our Maſter with all ſimplicity, for, far be it from us that we ſhould call him back again to the Font who is already waſhed, far be it from us that we ſhould repeat that which is to be done but once, or double that which is but one; for ſo it is written by the Apoſtle, ſaying, there is one God, one Chriſt, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> confirms the ſame thing: 1ſt. of all diſtinguiſhing, <hi>aliud eſt non habere, aliud pernitioſe habere, aliud ſalubriter habere;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l. 2. Cont. Ep. Parmen.</note> and then telling us concerning thoſe that are ſeparated from the Unity of the Church; that there is now no queſtion but that they both have and may confer (both Orders and Baptiſm). <hi>Sed pernitioſe habent, pernicioſe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dant, quia extra Vinculum pacis ſunt.</hi> and the ſame Father aſſerts the ſame Doctrine a little before in two caſes; Firſt, If any of the Schiſmatical Clergy be reconciled to the Church, tho it ſeems expedient to allow them the exerciſe of their former Function, yet are they not to be Reordained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Secondly, If on the contrary the Church judges it not convenient to allow
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96210:32"/>
them any Miniſtration,<note place="margin">Vid. Tim. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. C. P. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ap. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teler. Ec. Gr. Mon. T. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>420.</hi> &amp; E. Niceph. C.P. Epiſt. Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. Ibid. p. <hi>459, &amp;c.</hi> Maſon Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mhal. Burnets Vind. p. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> yet their Ordination is not hereby made void, but continues with them ſtill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I might add the practice of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church in former Ages, and the opinion of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> at this day, who altho they are as little friends to thoſe they call Schiſmaticks as any People in the World, yet the moſt Learned of them declare that no Man indeed ought to receive Orders from either Hereticks or Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and that both he that gives and he that receives them ſin greivouſly, yet where Hereticks or Schiſmaticks that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain were truely Ordained themſelves, and the <hi>Ordinations</hi> made by them according to the Forms of the Church, ſuch <hi>Ordinations</hi> are valid, and Hereticks or Schiſmaticks ſo Ordained, need no new <hi>Ordination,</hi> but only to be reconciled. And this we find alledged by Proteſtants againſt thoſe Popiſh Enemies, who ſometime have urged the very ſame Argument againſt our firſt Biſhops, which this Vindicator makes uſe of now. I wiſh this were the only inſtance wherein, the Papiſts and Diſſenters are agreed againſt us.</p>
            <p>And now let the Gentleman take his Anſwer to this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult queſtion: Whether Schiſmaticks can Ordain? It being generally given in the Affirmitive; if we may be allowed to believe, as moſt People do, the deriving of our Orders through a Schiſmatical Church can be no prejudice to the line of Succeſſion: And yet all thoſe Perſons who have thus determined concerning the validity of Schiſmatical Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations think Schiſmaticks out of the Church as much as <hi>T. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps our Author expected to Triumph in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and that made him call ſo earneſtly for an Anſwer to this Queſtion: Suppoſing that if <hi>Ordinations</hi> made by Schiſmaticks are granted to be valid, our preſent Non-conformiſts may find a place among the Clergy, when ever Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and — can obtain a Comprehenſion without a new Ordination, but this we deny: For although Schiſm do's not invalidate any mans Orders when they are really given, yet this will be no plea for thoſe who never were Ordained; which muſt needs be the caſe of many of you who deny the Order of Biſhops. For we believe with <hi>St. Jerome,</hi> that the Power of Ordaining belongs only to the Biſhop, and your <hi>Ordinations</hi> made by Presbyters are all Void and Null; and till you can prove the contrary we take you for no more but a parcel of Lay-intruders into thoſe Holy Functions to which you have no right, (thoſe of you only excepted who have been Epiſcopally Ordain'd.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:96210:32"/>And thoſe who have enquir'd more nicely into your <hi>Miſſion,</hi> are apt to ſuſpect that many of your <hi>firſt Apoſtles,</hi> from whom ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of you, in all probability, do derive your Orders, never were Ordain'd; and how to diſtinguiſh thoſe from others, at this day, we cannot tell. And this is an <hi>Obſervation</hi> which I ſuppoſe the <hi>Vindicator</hi> had never met with; or elſe he would ſcarce have been ſo confid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nt, as to tell us, p. 26. <hi>that they are in the Line ſtill.</hi> And yet it is hard to ſay, whether he was not aware of ſome ſuch thing; or elſe what ſhould make him ſo earneſt, as to loſe ſo many Pages <hi>aga nst this Line of Succeſſion?</hi> which, if it would do him <hi>no good,</hi> would certainly do him <hi>no harm.</hi> Methinks it is, at leaſt, a Matter of <hi>Reputation</hi> to ſucceed the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and therefore I can ſee <hi>no Reaſon</hi> why this <hi>Vindicator</hi> ſhould take ſuch pains <hi>to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it,</hi> unleſs (being conſcious to himſelf, that his Party has no pretence to it) he would, if it lay in his power, make it void or needleſs, to prevent others inſiſting upon it, who he knows can make out a better Claim.</p>
            <p>It has been the common practice of many others, beſides this Gent. to lay aſide thoſe <hi>Notions</hi> which their Circumſtances would not bear, and to find out New Devices with which they would more eaſily quadrate. And therefore we cannot wonder; that he looks upon <hi>Ordination</hi> to be no more but a <hi>Publick Approbation of Miniſterial Abilities by competent Judges,</hi> p. 26. Moſt of this Man's Party have <hi>no other Ordination</hi> (and perhaps many of 'em not that). Otherwiſe, we know, the <hi>Saints</hi> are as tenacious of Priviledges as other Men. And therefore if they could make any tolerable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to the <hi>Line of Succeſſion,</hi> they would magnifie it to the full as much as we do.</p>
            <p>But why <hi>only a Publick Approbation of Miniſeterial Abilities?</hi> Does the Publick Approbation of a Man's Abilities inveſt him in his Office? Will a Teſtimonial from the <hi>Inns of Court</hi> make a Man a <hi>Judge?</hi> or from the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> without any <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Ordination</hi> from the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or any body elſe? But this is ſuch a way of making Clergy-men, as never was heard of before. And indeed our Author himſelf puts in Two other Circumſtances in the next page, <hi>viz. That he be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the reſt, and ſet apart by the moſt competent Judges,</hi> which amounts to a great deal more than only a Publick Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And theſe <hi>Judges</hi> he ſuppoſes may be <hi>Lay-men</hi> in certain Caſes of Neceſſity: As in caſe <hi>that a Company of Lay-men be caſt upon an Iſland, or remain in ſame Countrey, when their Paſtors are all kill'd, or turn'd Hereticks.</hi> But in the firſt place, I muſt put him in mind, That as no Man is to meddle with the Sacred Offices (except he <hi>he called of God</hi>), no Man to preach, except <hi>he be ſent;</hi> ſo no
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96210:33"/>
Man is to call or ſend as from God, but he that is Authorized by him for that purpoſe. Our bleſſed Saviour himſelf, when he gave Commiſſion to his Apoſtles, recites his own; <hi>All power is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto me in Heaven and in Earth; Go therefore,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19. <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> John 20.21. And We hope our Diſſenting Brethren, when they go about to Ordain, will not diſdain to follow his Example. In all Ages of the Church the calling or ſending of perſons to the Work of the Miniſtry, has ſtill been the buſineſs of a ſelect Order of Men: Neither is it to be alter'd now, except our Author can ſhew us a Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby Laymen are impower'd to Ordain the Clergy, or ſome Scripture Inſtance to juſtifie that Practice. And if this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done, I ſhould be loth to be one of thoſe Laymen, though never ſo diſcreet and knowing, that ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d preſume to appoint Embaſſadors for Almighty God, without his Order. Neither can I ſee any Reaſon, why a Man may not as well be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, without any Miſſion at all, as by the Miſſion of thoſe perſons who never were ſent themſelves.</p>
            <p>As to the Three Caſes, wherein ou Author ſuppoſes that ſuch Lay-Ordinations became Neceſſary, we have no Inſtances before us in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of that kind, nor any particular dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Scripture to do as he thinks we may. And therefore we cannot tell what Method God Almighty would take in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; whether he would revive the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and call perſons to the Miniſtry after an extraordinary manner, that hereby the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority might again appear to be derived from himſelf, rather than accept of ſuch unauthorized Miniſters, as are only propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the People.</p>
            <p>Nor is it ſo eaſie to guide our ſelves by Arguments drawn from ſeeming Neceſſity, in caſes where there is no ſuch Neceſſity at all. For inſtance; <hi>Suppoſe that a Company of Chriſtian Women were cast upon an Iſland, whether would one of them, of the beſt Qualifications, choſen by the rest, and approv'd, and ſet apart by the moſt competent Judges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong 'em, to adminiſter in Holy Ordinances to them, be a true Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, and a Lay Perſon no longer?</hi> Here is the ſame Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity which our Author ſuppoſes; And if the Caſe holds as to the Men, I can ſee no Reaſon why the Women (whoſe <hi>Salvation</hi> is as Neceſſary) ſhould be rejected. But if a well-qualified Siſter ſhould happen to win the Hearts of the moſt competent Judges in Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Congregation,</hi> ſhe muſt, according to our Author's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be a tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Clergywoman at their next Election. Suppoſe that the Sacred Scriptures ſhould be totally deſtroy'd, or ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by Hereticks, that it were impoſſible to learn out of 'em the great Chriſtian Trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, would not <hi>Papiſts,</hi> upon this Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, cry up the Uſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten Tradition,</hi> and the great Neceſſity
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96210:33"/>
of an <hi>Infallible Judge?</hi> Would not the <hi>Socinian</hi> argue ſtiffly for <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion?</hi> which might be practis'd well enough after all that loſs? And why ſhould not the <hi>Quaker</hi> put in for a ſhare, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the <hi>Conduct of Inward Light;</hi> which may eaſily ſurvive the <hi>Written Word?</hi> And yet what Orthodox Believer would abate his Reverence for Scripture, upon the Inferences of ſuch People? No more will it become us to admit <hi>Lay-Ordinations</hi> up n that of our Author, from this <hi>Suppoſal of Neceſſity.</hi> As wiſe Men as he would have concluded another way: Not that <hi>Laymen</hi> are to <hi>Ordain Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> but that where <hi>Miniſters</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e wanting, People may either miniſter to themſelves, or communicate without Symbols; or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear till ſuch times as <hi>Miniſters</hi> can be had. Why may not Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God as well diſpenſe with ſome One of theſe things, as with a <hi>Lay-Ordination?</hi> And therefore when ſo many other Courſes may be taken, I would know by what <hi>Logick</hi> this <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi> can prove, That <hi>Lay Ordinations</hi> become Neceſſary! And if not Neceſſary, all his Argument is at an end, whereby he would make 'em lawful.</p>
            <p>I believe there never was any Caſe of Abſolute Neceſſity for <hi>Lay-Ordinations;</hi> but if poſſibly ſuch ſhould happen as the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man mentions, I am apt to believe that <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Miniſters, duly ordain'd,</hi> might be had from other Countries; And if not, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it would be reaſonable and fit, that we ſhould firſt ſee what God would do in ſuch Caſes, before we preſume to do any thing of our ſelves, for which we have no Scripture Warrant. In the nigheſt Caſes to his, thoſe of the <hi>Abyſſines,</hi> &amp;c. 'tis plain the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concern'd</hi> were of a quite <hi>contrary Opinion</hi> to that of <hi>our Author:</hi> The <hi>Abyſſines</hi> did not think their want of Ordinances did impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 'em to Ordain Clergymen; but were <hi>contented</hi> to be <hi>without thoſe</hi> which are to be diſpens'd by <hi>Prieſts,</hi> till ſuch times as <hi>Frumentius</hi> return'd from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who was there made a <hi>Biſhop</hi> by <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> and his <hi>Colleagues</hi> in <hi>Council;</hi> And yet they ſerv'd God in the <hi>best manner</hi> that <hi>Laymen could do.</hi> They had their <hi>Conventicula, Meeting-houſes,</hi> as <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Oratories or places for Prayer, as <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Buffin. H.B. l. 1. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soc. H. E. l. 1. c. 19.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sunt enim Conventicula loca privata in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibus collectae fiunt &amp; ab illis: distinguuntur. Eccleſiae quae ſunt publici ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, <hi>&amp;c. Valeſ. Annot. in Sec. l. 1. c. 19.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> but not to be call'd Churches, as <hi>Valeſius</hi> diſtinguiſhes: They Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiz'd, but did not Preach: They pray'd, but had no Sacraments that we read of. And when <hi>Frumentius</hi> came back, like an Apoſtle of the Country, he was Endowed with the Power of Working Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as the moſt Authentick Evidence both of his <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Miſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>w if thoſe Chriſtians had been of this Author's Opinion, it might have ſav'd <hi>Frumentius</hi> the <hi>Fatigue</hi> of ſo long a Journy, for the Chriſtian Merchants at <hi>Auxumae</hi> might have <hi>Choſen, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and ſet him apart,</hi> and without ever troubling <hi>Athanaſius, he had been a true Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, ſufficiently Authoriz'd to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96210:34"/>
Work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vindic. p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and a Lay Perſon no longer.</hi> And if <hi>Oſwald,</hi> King of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria,</hi> had but underſtood the Nature of <hi>Ordination,</hi> like this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentleman, he needed not have ſent to the <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Hy</hi> for <hi>Biſhops;</hi> he and his Privy Council, or others of his Chriſtian Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects might have ordain'd enough. For probably there were not only Chriſtians but Presbyters in <hi>Northumbria</hi> at that time: Twelve Thouſand being baptiz'd according to <hi>Nennius</hi> and <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus;</hi> their Archbiſhop,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Nen. <hi>H.</hi> Prit. c. <hi>65.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vid. chronic. ſanct. cru. Edin. ad an. <hi>627. Angl</hi> Sac. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Hiſt. de Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ. Ep. Dunelm. ib. p. <hi>691.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> with the Aſſiſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ce of <hi>Edwin</hi> their King, having ſpent ſix years in planting and ſetling Chriſtianity there, and but two years betwixt his going off, and Biſhop <hi>Aidan</hi>'s co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither. And unleſs the Gent. can ſhew the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That none of the former Converts were then remaining; or if they were, that none of 'em were <hi>better qualified,</hi> none more <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges than the reſt;</hi> but all alike. It is plain, by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that they were not of his Opinion.</p>
            <p>When ever a new People were <hi>Converted</hi> to the <hi>Faith,</hi> great care was always taken to have a Lawful <hi>Miniſtry</hi> among 'em, both <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> duly <hi>Ordain'd:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruffin.</hi> H. E. l. 1. c. 10.</note> For this Reaſon the <hi>Iberians</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd an <hi>Embaſſy</hi> to <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> deſiring that Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſts might be ſent 'em.<note place="margin">Soz. H. E. l. 6. c. 38.</note> And when the <hi>Saracens</hi> were Converted, <hi>Mavia,</hi> their Queen, deſires that <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>Saracen,</hi> might be the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of that <hi>Nation;</hi> and when he refus'd to be <hi>Ordain'd</hi> by <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the Bloody <hi>Arian,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Magiſtrates (we find) carried him to the baniſhed <hi>Biſhops</hi> for <hi>Orders,</hi> which they needed not have done, if they had been of the Mind of our <hi>Author:</hi> For <hi>if Ordination be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more but a publick Approbation of Miniſterial Abilities by the moſt competent Judges, Moſes</hi> was really Ordain'd before ever he came at thoſe Biſhops; his <hi>Miniſterial Abilities being publickly Approv'd</hi> by the <hi>Roman</hi> Magiſtrates and the Queen, before he left his own Country.<note place="margin">Ang. ſac. p. 423. Tho. Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterf. de Epiſc. Cov. &amp; Lich. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 425.</note> So when <hi>Peada,</hi> King of the <hi>Mid-Angles,</hi> was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and Baptiz'd in <hi>Northumbria,</hi> he brought Home with him four Presbyters, <hi>viz. Cedda,</hi> and <hi>Adda,</hi> and <hi>Betti,</hi> and <hi>Duma,</hi> that he might Propagate the Chriſtian Religion among his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and <hi>Diuma</hi> was afterward Conſecrated the firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Mercians</hi> and <hi>Mid Angles,</hi> by <hi>Finan</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Northumbria;</hi> and yet I doubt not but his fellow Presbyters were competent Judges, and might have made him a Biſhop as well as <hi>Finan,</hi> if our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's way of <hi>Ordaining</hi> had been then found out: But as the Church never dream'd of any ſuch rare Inventions; ſo it is plain they thought <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination</hi> neceſſary, that the only way of deriving that Authority from our <hi>Saviour,</hi> was by <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and that no Man might Adminiſter in Sacred things, unleſs he were thus Admitted. And for this Reaſon the Councel of <hi>Celichyth</hi> under <hi>Wulfred,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> were ſo wary, that they would not admit an Stranger of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation to perform any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96210:34"/>
Sacred Office; <hi>quia incertum eſt nobis unde &amp; an ab aliquo Ordinentur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spelm. Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Ang. Tom. <hi>1. 329.</hi>
               </note> becauſe it was uncertain to them by whom, and whether they were ordain'd by any body at all.</p>
            <p>Now as it is plain, from all theſe Inſtances, that the <hi>Christians</hi> of ſeveral Countries and Ages, were of a quite contrary Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that of our Author, ſo I might add ſeveral more, were I not to deal with Perſons, who, rather than lay aſide that Scheme of Government which they have lately eſpous'd, will deſpiſe all Antiquity; inſomuch that the practice of the very <hi>Apoſtles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot eſcape their Cenſure;<note place="margin">Vind. p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> witneſs that unſeemly Jeſt wherewith the <hi>Vindicator</hi> endeavours to Ridicule that Sacred Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony; <hi>viz.</hi> Impoſition of Hands; which being uſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Ordination of <hi>Timothy,</hi> what is here ſaid againſt it in General Terms, is no leſs a Libel upon him, than it is upon us.</p>
            <p>I wonder who taught him the Notion of <hi>an uninterrupted Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Monarchs, from the Eldeſt Son of</hi> Noah.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> If he can produce it from <hi>any Author,</hi> I ſhall then believe that he can ſpeak truth for once. In the mean time, I cannot but admire, that a Man who diſputes with ſo much Pertneſs, as if every thing that he ſays were all Oracle, ſhould want either the Sence to underſtand, or Integrity to report ſo plain a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If our <hi>Loyalty</hi> to <hi>Engliſh Monarchs</hi> is ſo great a Trouble to theſe Gentlemen, that they cannot hear it aſſerted, without <hi>torturing their Ears,</hi> we cannot help it. I confeſs it is no more than what I always thought; and ſince the Gent. ſo freely owns it, I hope it will be taken notice of: For the Government (which G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d be thanked is not yet quite a <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) muſt needs be concern'd in that Grievance; And he that can libel the Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſo much Impudence,<note place="margin">Vind. p. <hi>57,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and triumph in the Subverſion of thoſe Principles, which lately ſupported the Monarchy, cannot be thought to wiſh very auſpiciouſly to the preſent Reign.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding their Natural Averſation, and Spight againſt Monarchy, ſo eaſie and flexible are thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen to any thing of their own Intereſt, that when King <hi>James</hi> the Second afforded 'em a <hi>Tolerat on,</hi> No Complements were too high for him. <hi>Subverſion of Religion,</hi> and <hi>cutting of Throats,</hi> the dangerous Conſequences of a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor, were abſolutely forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:</hi> The <hi>Monarch</hi> was no <hi>Bugbear,</hi> nor the <hi>Papiſts</hi> neither; <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> and <hi>Dispenſing Power</hi> were <hi>harmleſs, innocent things:</hi> His <hi>Leige-People, the Diſſenters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leads</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, June 25. 87.</note> 
               <hi>were vying who ſhould moſt feelingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a Thankful Heart;</hi> They magnified him <hi>as the Generous Leading Pattern to the Princes of other People, and a Father to his own;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96210:35"/>
The Aſſertor and Reſtorer of God's immediate Dominion over Conſcience; the covering Cherub, under whoſe refreſhing Shadow they promis'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Reſt—The Firſt and Happy Inſtrument,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Independ. and Bipt. in the County of <hi>Glou.</hi> May, 87. Diſſent. of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Great Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> &amp;c. July 9. 87.</p>
                  <p>Diſſenters in <hi>Leathward</hi> in <hi>Cumberl.</hi> Aug. 87.</p>
                  <p>Presbyter. of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. 87.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>under God, of the preſent and future Peace and Prosperity of his Dominions — One de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for great Services, the bloſſoming whereof was then made viſible in his Celebrated Wiſdom, in happening upon the moſt melodous Harp to charm all evil Spirits, that many other Princes had no Skill to uſe;</hi> (though according to others <hi>Concarring herein with many Noble Princes before him.</hi>) But as others thought fit to expreſs themſelves—<hi>Of all that ever ſate upon the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Throne, It ſhall only be ſaid of Your Maieſties Reign, That from the</hi> Weſtern <hi>Ocean, even to the Frozen</hi> Thule then had the Churches Reſt, and were multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no one forbidding them — <hi>Your Royal Indulgence, like the Sound of the Jubilee Trumpet, has ſo exhilarated the Hearts of your Diſſenting Subjects, that they want Words to expreſs their Gratitude, and Tongues to Celebrate your Clemency,</hi> &amp;c. So dear was that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Prince to theſe People, upon the Account of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence (though at the ſame time they knew well enough, that he inte ded hereby the Ruine of the Eſtabliſh'd Church), that they follow'd him with Acclamations and Shouts, beyond all others, wherever he came. The Flattery of their Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes had no other Bounds but want of Wit;<note place="margin">You have hereby eccho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical ſong, which brought him into the World, who at his ingreſs into it brought peace, and at his egreſs out of it, bought peace, and thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molated that Reſignation of a narrow inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, for the Divinity of a more general Preſervation; and ſo tuned the ſtrings of your auſpicious Government, as to make melody over your whole Empire. <hi>Presbyt. of</hi> Hull, Octob. 87. And a little after, they call him plainly their <hi>Redeemer.</hi>
               </note> and that Defect was oftentimes ſupply'd with Fuſtian and Blaſphemy. He that reads 'em, wou'd think many parts of 'em to have been taken out of their Prayers; inſomuch that God Almighty and King <hi>James</hi> the Second had in many inſtances the very ſame Complements. Nay, if the Prophets did any where magnifie the Divine Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency by a moſt extraordinary flight of Expreſſion, it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently got into the Addreſſes, and apply'd moſt ingenuouſly to King <hi>James,</hi> to enhaunce the Diſſenters Gratitude for that <hi>Illegal Act.</hi> So that methinks there is little Room for this Gentleman to talk of <hi>Lewd and Extravagan Careſſes between Ambitious Princes and Aſpiring Churchmen,</hi> Vind. p. 28. while thoſe of his own Party are extant, and may be ſeen.</p>
            <p>Though it ſhould be granted, <hi>That Ceremonies have no Moral Goodneſs in them</hi> (as he ſays is <hi>acknowledged,</hi> p 28.) yet Decency has; which we think will not eaſily be preſerv'd without them; and that it is fit they ſhould be choſen and impos'd by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Wiſdom of <hi>Superiours.</hi> For if otherwiſe Religious Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were to be perform'd, according to the Opinion and Will of every Rude and Phantaſtical Perſon, we ſee by the Practice of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96210:35"/>
Conventicles, where that Liberty is taken, how awkardly they would be manag'd, to the great Scandal and Offence of the more Ingenious and Sober People. Nor is it eaſilie to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That God Almighty ſhould be better pleas'd with the Rudeneſs of their Worſhip, than with the Decency of ours. Eſpecially conſidering, That beſides the Practice of the Church in all Ages, we have the Injunction of the Apoſtle, That all things be done decently, and are to Worſhip God with our Bodies, as well as with our Souls, which are God's.</p>
            <p>As to the Ceremonies of our Church in particular, they are ſo few, and eaſie, that he muſt certainly be a Man of more than ordinary Peeviſhneſs, or leſs than ordinary Sence, that can take 'em for <hi>Incumbrances upon the Worſhip of God.</hi> The Vindicator himſelf, upon Second Thoughts, will not, <hi>under pretence of Spirituality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vind. p. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>reject the Natural Decorum of an Action in the Worſhip of God</hi> which I am very glad to hear, And if he will but do One Thing more, <hi>viz.</hi> allow the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, in Convocation, to be fitter Judges of that Decorum than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mean and half-witted Paſtor, there would be very little more requir'd from him.</p>
            <p>I am confident, when this is done, that people will be better reconcil'd to our Ceremonies, than to ſuffer themſelves to be <hi>Excommunicated, and Damn'd, for not complying with them,</hi> as the Vindicator talks, <hi>page</hi> 28. In the mean time, if any Man be ſo ſtiff and peeviſh, or malicious againſt the Church, as to deprave her Ceremonies, and ſo far deſpiſes her Juriſdiction and Government, that he will not vouchſsafe an Appearance to the moſt Legal Summons, nor yield to the moſt Reaſonable and Juſt Monitions in that Caſe, ſhe does purſue our Saviour's Rule— He that neglects to hear the Church, we think ought to be reckon'd as an <hi>Heathen Man,</hi> and a <hi>Publican,</hi> or in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the UNITED MINISTERS — <hi>When all due Means for the reducing him prove ineffectual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heads of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>he having here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cut himſelf off from the Church's Communion, the Church may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem and declare it ſelf diſcharg'd of any further Inſpection over him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this practice the mildeſt Proteſtant Churches agree with us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. Diſ. of the Reform. Churches of <hi>France,</hi> tranſl. into <hi>Eng.</hi> 1642.</note> The Reformed Churches of <hi>France</hi> having us'd a Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive Power over their inferiour Members. <hi>Thoſe that ſhould ſtir up Strife or Contention, to dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oyn or break the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of their Church, concerning ſome Point of their Doctrine or Diſcipline, or about the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, Matter, or Stile of the Catechiſm</hi> (though of Humane Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition), <hi>or the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments; Publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:96210:36"/>
&amp;c. <hi>ſhall be cenſur'd as Rebellious Perſons — And in caſe they will not renounce their Errors — then they are to be cut off from the Church. If the Paſtor or Elder do it, he ſhall preſently be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from his Charge and Imployment, and be proceeded againſt at the next Eccleſiaſtical Synod. If he teaches Falſe Doctrine, and perſiſts after Admonition; If he is not obedient to the Admonition of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory, or Convicted of Hereſie, Schiſm, or Rebellion, againſt Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Order, he is to be depos'd. If he thruſts himſelf into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, where there is pure preaching already, and will not de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>it when warn'd of it, he is to be quite cut off, and proceeded againſt as the Synod ſhall think fit. And the ſame Courſe is to be taken with all his Followers.</hi> And at the End of that Book, we are told, That this Order and Diſcipline had been reſolv'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded on by no leſs than Twenty Seven National Synods, from 1559 to 1637, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe Reformed Churches of <hi>France</hi> were not to be Cenſur'd as Uncharitable, for the Eſtabliſhment and Exerciſe of this Diſcipline, I know no Reaſon why ours ſhould lie under that imputation.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph he finds fault with <hi>T. W</hi>'s. Notion of of the Communion of Saints but gives none of his own, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fear leſt he ſhould miſtake, or leſt his own Party ſhould be condemn'd by it, I ſhall not now enquire. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a nice Point for Separatiſts to manage, It being hard for thoſe that neither Pray with, nor receive the Sacraments, nor live under the Government of any Church, to Demonſtrate plainly how <hi>they hold Communion with all,</hi> as this <hi>Vindicator</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently pretends. However though he could eſtabliſh nothing himſelf; yet that he may do ſomething towards finding fault with <hi>T. W.</hi> he proceeds to examine his <hi>aggregate deſcription of the Communion of Saints,</hi> which he tells you conſiſts of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A firm belief of all the Articles of Faith contain'd in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical, Nicene, and Athanaſian Creeds.</hi> Now this mightily offends him: 1ſt. Becauſe it was not ſaid in Scripture; as if he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves thoſe Creeds did not believe Scripture. Thoſe Creeds, tho <hi>of human compoſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Symbolum Apoſt. exigi coepit ubi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae Haereſes in Eccleſiam irru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perant Voſſ. de tribus Symb. Diſ. 1. c. 14.</note> yet are according to Scripture, and contain the Faith into which Chriſtians are Baptized. They are the <hi>Symbola</hi> wherein the Orthodox of all Countreys agree, and whereby they have diſtinguiſhed themſelves in ſeveral Ages, from thoſe Hereticks which did not aſſent to them. The two former have been generally received, and admitted, into the Liturgies
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96210:36"/>
of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, and therefore it is ſtrange how the <hi>Vindicator</hi> can ſuppoſe that <hi>the Greek and other</hi> Eaſtern <hi>Churches are ſhut out by this condition of Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true in the Article of the Proceſſion they objected againſt the <hi>Latins,</hi> the addition of <hi>Filio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> in the <hi>Nicene</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Creed, (and perhaps not untruly, conſidering that in the old <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Hittorpius,</hi> wherein that Creed is ordered to be uſed in both Languages theſe words, tho in the <hi>Latine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, qui ex patre filio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, qui cum patre &amp; filio. ſimul adoratur Hittorp. Ord. Rom. de Div. Offic. p. 39. Ed. Col. 1568. Vide &amp; Voſſ. de tribus 9. symbol. Diſſ. 3 c. 20. &amp;c.</note> yet are omitted in the <hi>Greek</hi>). But nevertheleſs they uſ'd the Creed, and from them it came Originally into the <hi>Latine</hi> Church. And as to that which we receive under the Name of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> thoſe among the <hi>Greeks</hi> who thought it to be his, had always a very great veneration for it. But in ſome <hi>Greek</hi> Copies the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are left out. So that upon the whole matter the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches have no quarrel againſt either of thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Combefis. ad Man. Calec. not 59.</note> Creeds. All their contention with the <hi>Weſtern</hi> in this caſe is about the true Reading of them<note n="†" place="margin">Symbolum fidei, quod ipſi profitentur idem eſt atque illud quod Latini in Miſſa recitant: Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferunt in eo à Latinis quod ipſi de Spir. Sancto. dicunt, qui ex Patre procedit, Latini qui ex Patre filioque procedit; id cum Graeci non negent idem cum Latinis dicere exiſtimandi ſunt. Leo All. de Conſ. l. 3. c. 10. Sect. 1.</note>. And therefore unleſs he had been more particular about that, this firſt Branch of <hi>T. W</hi>'s. deſcription may ſtand, and yet neither the <hi>Greek</hi> or any <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church be excluded.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>To partake of the ſame Table,</hi> 'tis true <hi>T. W. did not mean the ſame individual Table,</hi> as the Gentleman rightly ſuppoſes, and yet he meant ſomthing more than barely the <hi>ſame Euchariſt in Specie;</hi> Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, may deliver the <hi>ſame Euchariſt in Specie;</hi> and yet he that Communicates with either is not thereby in the Communion of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>To joyn all in the ſame Holy Prayers, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, and giving of Thanks: T. W.</hi> does not hereby <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate all the reſt of the World.</hi> For although the Forms of Holy Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are different in ſeveral Countreys, yet people joyning with the Church where they live in its Holy Devotions, do anſwer this Branch of the Deſcription and thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who refuſe and ſeparate from them are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Schiſmaticks.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:96210:37"/>Fourthly, <hi>To be Subject and Obedient to our Spiritual Rulers, and Governors, who have derived their Authority from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles by a due Succeſſion in all things pertaining to godly Life, Decency and Order.</hi> He cannot except againſt this: <hi>They are deſirous to give due Honour and Obedience, to their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Governors who derive their Authority from Chriſt,</hi> but ſtill he endeavours to juſtifie their Separation upon two ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vind. p. 32.</note>Firſt, Becauſe <hi>he thinks the Biſhop ought not to Govern ſo many Congregations, nor by ſuch Rules, and Officers, as they do Neither,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, By the <hi>nomination of the Civil Magiſtrate without the conſent of the People, or the Miniſters within the Dioceſs, and while he does ſo, he is a Creature not to be found either in Scripture or in the Primitive Times,</hi> and <hi>therefore can be no Spiritual Governor of theirs by Divine Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Government of ſo many Congregations, we think it not Eſſential to the Office of a Biſhop: It being not the greatneſs of the City he lives in, or the extent of his Dioceſs, or the Number of Congregations, but the Ordination that makes him a Biſhop. We acknowledg with St.<note place="margin">Ep. ad Evagr.</note> 
               <hi>Jerome</hi> that the poor Biſhop of <hi>Eugubium</hi> had the ſame Order, and Authority, with him of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that he of <hi>Tanis</hi> was equal in that reſpect to him of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soz. l. 2. c. 14.</note> and that <hi>Milles</hi> the Martyr in <hi>Sozomen</hi> who had never a Chriſtian within his Dioceſs,<note place="margin">Ibid. l. 7. c. 19.</note> was as truly a Biſhop as he who had all <hi>Scythia</hi> under his care.</p>
            <p>On the other hand to perſuade us that the great Extent of a Biſhops Dioceſs does make void his Office, will be a task, I am afraid, too difficult for our Author to manage. We have no ſuch Doctrine in Sc ipture. And this conceit as it is beyond the malice, ſo it is below the Sence of all Hereticks and Schiſmaticks in former Times. And if it were true, the Apoſtles themſelves muſt have been the greateſt Uſurpers: They having a larger extent of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction even according to this Author, than any of their Succeſſors. But this Argument has been ſo Copiouſly, and ſo lately managed, by Doctor <hi>Maurice</hi> in his Learned Defence of Dioceſan Epiſcopacy; that I ſhall only need to refer the Reader thither.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:96210:37"/>Secondly, As for, the Officers uſed by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelacy, we think them ſuch as are extreamly uſeful, in order to the more regular and eaſy management of the Epiſcopal Charge, The <hi>Chancellor</hi> is a Perſon well learned in the Canon and Civil Laws, and conſequently able to judg or aſſiſt the Biſhop in his Judicial Proceedings. Nor is it any great exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, in my Opinion, that he is a <hi>Layman,</hi> while there is no Neceſſity for him Perſonally to perform any of thoſe things which belong only to the Clergy:<note place="margin">Lyndew. de Conſtit. q. incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. Dec. Rural. vid plura de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciis, c. <hi>1.</hi> Dec. Rural.</note> The <hi>Dean Rural</hi> is a Temporary Officer under the Archbiſhop or Biſhop, <hi>ad ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod miniſterium exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cendum Constitutus. —Cujus Officium eſt in Cauſis eccleſiaſticis citationes ei tranſmiſſas exequi—cujus ſigillum in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus erit auctenticum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rules they go by are the Canon and Civil Laws, where the Laws and Canons of our own Kingdom have not expreſly directed. The Authority they have is from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and the Law. So that he who diſobeys them in the juſt and legal Exerciſe of their Authority, diſobeys both. <hi>How Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Certain that Authority is,</hi> I wiſh theſe Gentlemen may conſider.</p>
            <p>And if it were purely a matter of Choice, yet methinks Church-Affairs are more likely to be well manag'd under our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelacy, by ſuch Officers and Rulers, than after the Independent Faſhion, by the Sudden and Arbitrary Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of every Mean and Ordinary Paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r, perhaps in a Conſiſtory of Clowns, who muſt Pole for that Truth and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which they do not underſtand: And if either the Paſtor, or any body elſe happens to be wiſer than the reſt, ſo as to judge right, have Power to over-rule his Sence and Arguments, either by Votes or Tumult.</p>
            <p>Neither, Thirdly, Do we think the <hi>Conſent of the People, or of the Miniſters of the Dioceſs,</hi> Eſſential to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Office of a Biſhop: Our Saviour Conſtituted his Apoſtles without it; We have no Command in Scripture for any ſuch Conſent: The Practice of the Primitive Times was various; and therefore we think it a Matter left wholly to the Diſcretion of the Church. <hi>Matthias</hi> and <hi>Juſtus</hi> ſeem to be appointed by the People, as well as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Apoſtleſhip was not determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that Election, but by the Lot which fell upon <hi>Matthias:</hi> For <hi>Justus,</hi> who was equally Sharer with him in that Act of the People, was thereby no more an Apoſtle than he was before. And perhaps the ſame way of Chuſing by Lots, might be us'd by St. <hi>John,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi> conjectures; but was never,<note place="margin">Diſſ. Cyp. p. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:96210:38"/>
probably, in Uſe after the Apoſtles Days; though if it had been Neceſſary, we cannot believe it would have been omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the following Ages. The Seven Deacons (we read) were Elected by the People, but receiv'd their Authorities and Office from the Apoſtles, by impoſition of Hands.</p>
            <p>And theſe are, I believe, all the Inſtances of Popular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections that can be found in Scripture; but from none of 'em is it evident, that the Election of the People did contribute any thing that was Eſſential to Holy Orders.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why it was admitted, was, that they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Power and Character upon the Beſt and moſt Unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable Perſons; ſuch as were of Honeſt Report; which could not ſo eaſily be known, without conſulting the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:<note place="margin">Cyp. Ep. LXVIII. Ed. Oxon.</note> And this is all the Uſe that St <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Inſtances, who tells us,
<q>That it was ſo order'd in the Caſe of <hi>Eleazar,</hi> the Son of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ought to be ſo, that the Crimes of ill Men may be Detected, and the Deſerts of Good Men Extoll'd — And that the Apoſtles proceeded ſo diligently and warily in the Choice of <hi>Matthias,</hi> and the Seven Deacons, leſt any Unworthy Perſon ſhould creep into the Service of the Altar, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Degree of Prieſthood.</q> 
               <hi>And he adds further,</hi> 
               <q>That in his Time it was the Cuſtom for the Neighbouring Biſhops of the ſame Province, to Meet and Chuſe a Biſhop in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the People, who fully underſtood each Man's Life. And after this manner they advanced <hi>Sabinus</hi> into the Place of <hi>Baſilide.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>All this ſeems to be plainly allow'd by the Council of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicea,</hi> which will have none to be made Biſhops, but ſuch as are of <hi>Known and Approved Converſation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con. Laod. Can. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and provides that they ſhould be conſtituted, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the Diſcretion of the Metropolitans, and Neighbouring Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops In which Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nts it agrees exactly with St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 13.</note> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yet the Canon immediat ly following, will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the People to chuſe thoſe that are to be advanced to the Prieſthood; and therefore ſurely their Conſent was not then thought Eſſentially Neceſſary to the making of a Biſhop. Nay, ſo far was the Church from the Opin on of this Author, that upon the Death of <hi>Auxentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. <hi>H.</hi> E. l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſh p of <hi>Milan,</hi> the Synod petition'd the Emperour, That he would chuſe one to ſuc eed him in that See; which certainly they would not have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96210:38"/>
done, if they had thought that his Nomination would have made him ſuch a Monſter, as our Author ſpeaks of, viz. <hi>A Creature not to be found in Scripture, or the Primitive Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might add ſeveral other Inſtances of Biſhops, Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans and Patriarchs, choſen to their reſpective Charges, by the Diſcretion of the Emperour and other Princes; but I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>As to the Nomination of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelacy; ſuppoſe it had been of right Originally in the Clergy and People, yet they by their Repreſentatives in Parliament,<note place="margin">25 H. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> have confirm'd it to the Prince; So that it is his by Law: And for my part, I know no Reaſon why it ſhould not ſo continue. Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is the ſame, chuſe who Names; it being not the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, but the Ordination that makes the Biſhop. And if that be the ſame now which it was in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times, our Epiſcopacy muſt needs be the ſame with theirs.</p>
            <p>Page 33, and 34. The Gentleman is <hi>willing to be try'd by the Pattern of thoſe Churches which are truly Primitive;</hi> but I find he dares not venture far among 'em, for fear of loſing his Cauſe. He complains,
<q>That a Century, or Two, made a conſiderable Change in the Features of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Worſhip:</q>
but in which Century that Change was wrought, he durſt not inform us. However, if he pleaſes to venture his Cauſe upon it, let him take any of the firſt Fifteen, to prove Congregational Epiſcopacy; and (provided he will allow the Writers of that, or the next Age, to be credited before thoſe that liv'd later) I ſhall freely joyn iſſue with him.</p>
            <p>We have a Specimen of his Abilities already, <hi>page</hi> 34 and 35. where he tells us,
<q>That <hi>Ignatius</hi> charges the Biſhop to take a perſonal cognizance of every Member of his Church, not excepting the very Servants.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And Secondly,
<q>That it was the Cuſtom then in every Congregation to receive the Sacrament every Lord's Day; and that they never receiv'd it, <hi>niſi ex antiſtitis manu,</hi> but from the Hand of the Biſhop. What could ſuch Biſhops be more than Paſtors of ſingle Congregations?</q> To which I Anſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:96210:39"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ignat. Ep. ad Polyc.</note>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>Ignatius</hi> does indeed require of the Biſhop, to <hi>diſcourſe people ſingly, as God ſhould enable him:</hi> But how does this prove, That he was to take a Perſonal Cognizance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Member of his Church? Had he no body to aſſiſt him in the Remoter parts of his Charge? Why could no Man elſe acquaint him with the Frailties and Miſdemeanors of particular perſons, but all muſt depend wholly upon his own Cognizance and Obſervation? Or becauſe he was not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf barely with Publick Preaching, but was to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe 'em particularly, as he found occaſion: Does it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that he muſt needs be acquainted with every Member o his Church? How if they were too numerous, or liv d too remote to be all Perſonally diſcours'd with? All that <hi>Ignatius</hi> requires is <hi>ſo far as God ſhall enable him;</hi> Which kind of Expreſſion, methinks, implies ſome difficulty — <hi>Let Aſſemblies be held often;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Enquire after all by their Names; do not deſpiſe,</hi> or behave thy ſelf inſolently towards <hi>the Men-Servants, or Maid-Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I ſuppoſe, is the Paſſage to which our Author prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally refers. Though if he had been able to have quoted it, we might have been abundantly more certain However, from this it is not to be concluded, that he muſt take a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Cognizance of every Member of his Church, or that he was the Paſtor only of One ſingle Congregation; For how does he prove, That thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were to be only at One Place? Why might not the ſeveral Aſſemblies in his Dioceſs be as well comprehended under that Title? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, how does our Author prove, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies no more but the Ordinary Congregations? Why not the more Extraordinary Aſſemblies, when the Biſhop Viſited? Perhaps the Biſhop had a Scroll, wherein the Names of Chriſtians were enroll'd; and in calling them over at his Viſitations might enquire into the Faith and Manners of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, and call for the Men themſelves, and as he found Occaſion, diſcourſe 'em, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by way of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct ine, Admonition, or Reproof: Or, peradventure he might call over the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>mes of the Congregation where he himſelf was preſent, that he might hereby diſcover who were heretically inclin'd: For even then ſuch Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to withdraw from the Communion of the Church, and to hold Conventicles, though very privately. And if we take it in the latter Sence, it will contribute little to his Cauſe, unleſs he could firſt prove, That the Biſhop's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:96210:39"/>
would not be a Pattern to the reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c. Id. ad Smyr. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ibid.</p>
                  <p>Vid. Dodw. in Irenae. Diſ. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>XVII.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and that there were no Subordinate Presbyters to do the ſame thing, by the Biſhops Order, in other Congregations within his Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>And that there were more Congregations than one under the Biſhop of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> is evident from that Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ge of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in his Epiſtle to them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ig. ad Smyrn.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man perform any of thoſe things which belong to Publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, without the Biſhop, That Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt is to be thought valid, which is either under him, or at leaſt, which he allowed.</hi> What had he to do to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Euchariſt in Congregations Independent upon him, and to talk of giving allowance to himſelf in his own is to great a Blunder for <hi>Ignatius</hi> to be charged with. So that all the diſtinction here made is betwixt a Congregation under the Biſhop, <hi>viz.</hi> that where he was Perſonally preſent, and another Congregation Aſſembled by his permiſſion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance; and muſt conſequently imply that in the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> there were ſeveral Congregations under one Biſhop, what relates to Servants is nothing to this purpoſe in <hi>Ignatius,</hi> whatever it was in our Authors Head.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Second Alligation more regular or juſt than the former. <hi>(Antiſtitis manu)</hi> in <hi>Tertullian</hi> (for thence it came Originally by way of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to our Author) referring not to the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">Aquam adituri ibidem, ſed &amp; <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanto prius</hi> in Eccleſia ſub Antiſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> manu conteſtamur nos Renunciare Diai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — Euchariſtiae Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum &amp; in Tempore victus, &amp; Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; mandatum a Domino, etiam antelucanis Caetizbus, nec de Aliorum manu, quam praeſidentium ſumimus. Tert. De Cor. Milit. c. 3.</note> but to the Form of Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Devil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory to Baptiſm, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be Baptized did it <hi>ſub Antiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titis manu,</hi> for (<hi>ex</hi>) as this Man quotes it would have made it Non-ſence. <hi>Tertullian</hi> does indeed ſpeak of the Lords Supper not to be Received <hi>niſi de Praeſidentium manu,</hi> But this will do our Author no Service: The word
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96210:40"/>
               <hi>Praeſidentium</hi> including the Bench of Presbyters, as well as the Biſhop in <hi>Cathedra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Pearſ. Vind. Ignat. p. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Aſſert. <hi>2.</hi> Dod. in Iren. Diſ. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>VII.</hi>
               </note>Nor will the Paſſage out of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> which he ſo haſtily miſapplies (if fully cited and underſtood,) afford any advantage to his cauſe. Presbyters in that Father, oftentimes denoting the Age, rather than the Office of thoſe Perſons meant by it, as divers Learned Men have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready obſerved. And in that Sence not only Presbyters, but likewiſe Biſhops, Deacons and Laymen might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under that Title: And accordingly <hi>Irenaeus</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhes by divers Characters telling them what ſort of Elders they were to hearken to,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Qua propter eis qui in Eccleſ. ſunt Preſ. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audire oportet hiis qui Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem habent ab Apoſtolis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut oſtendimus, qui cum Epiſc. Succeſſione cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſma veritatis Certum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum placitum Patris accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Iren. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>4, 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iren. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>43</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Eis qui in Eccleſia ſunt,</hi> thoſe who are within the Pale of the Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Hiis qui Succeſſionem habent ab Apostolis,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe who had the Succeſſion from the Apoſtles, and who together with the Succeſſion, in their Epiſcopal Charge, did receive the ſure Gift of Truth, according to the Will of the Father.</p>
            <p>Whence it is plain that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in this place, means Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops only when he talks of the Apoſtles Succeſſors. And therefore our Authors Inference in behalf of <hi>Presbyters having their Succeſſion from the Apostles as well as Biſhops,</hi> is out of Doors. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> reckons up the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> in order as they Succeeded to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> then Biſhop, who was the Twelfth from the Apoſtles, concluding <hi>Hac Ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ione &amp; Succeſſione, &amp;c. by this Ordination, and Succeſſion, that Tradition which is in the Church from the Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s and the Preaching of the Truth is handed down to us.</hi> From which it is plain that Succeſſion in their days, was more than <hi>bare Conformity to the Apoſtles Model in Government and Worſhip:</hi> For they Succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>In Power and Authority,</hi> So Irenaeus — <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus etiam ipſas Eccleſias Committebant — quos &amp; Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores relinquebant ſuum ipſorum, Locum Magiſterii traden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>In Place, So Linus</hi> was conſtituted the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> at <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> tells us further that they made him Biſhop. And therefore if his Succeſſors afterwards mentioned kept up to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Model, they muſt likewiſe derive their Office as he did, from Perſons inveſted w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th the ſame Character, and Conſequently as <hi>Linus</hi> was Ordained by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who had that Epiſcopal Authority in themſelves,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96210:40"/>
which they conferred upon him, So the reſt down to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> muſt be Ordained by Biſhops. And if ſo let our Author conſider with himſelf whether his Notion, or ours, is nearer in all Points to the <hi>ſenſe of thoſe Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I conſider how nice and ſtrict this Gentleman was in the Notion of Succeſſion, <hi>P.</hi> 19. 20 that he could not allow Two Biſhops to Succeed One Apoſtle, nor One to Succeed Two, I cannot but wonder that in the Writing of 16 <hi>Pages,</hi> his Head ſhould grow ſo looſe as to make it no more than <hi>Conformity to the Apoſtles Model in Government and Worſhip.</hi> Surely if this be the <hi>trueſt Sence</hi> as the Gentleman affirms, One Biſhop may Succeed Two Apoſtles, or One Apoſtle be Succeeded by Twenty Biſhops without any ſuch abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity or Blunder as our Author cries out againſt in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted Pages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We all grant that for Perſons wilfully to withdraw themſelves from ſuch particular Churches as are framed according to Scripture Rules, and impoſe no new or needleſs Terms, is to Act Schiſmatically, becauſe ſuch willfull Separation when n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe is giuen, cannot be without breach of Charity with our fellow Chriſtians,</hi> Page 37. Yes it may through the prejudices of Education, or for want of underſtanding: Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may take that to be <hi>New</hi> which is very <hi>Old,</hi> and that which is very <hi>Decent</hi> and <hi>Fit</hi> to be Impoſed, to be altogether <hi>Needleſs;</hi> and withdraw themſelves from <hi>particular Churches fram'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture Rules,</hi> when purely out of miſtake they think them otherwiſe. They may be led by Intereſt, or won over by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, to a new Communion, and yet have no hard thoughts of that Church, or its Members, which they left. I cannot believe that every Diſſenter at his firſt going off from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> does immediately hate us; I find ſeveral of 'em very Kind a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d Affable Perſons; And yet if our Author has granted Right, all their Charity (though a very good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thing) cannot excuſe 'em from the Guilt of acting ſchiſmatically.</p>
            <p>And becauſe <hi>our Author</hi> has granted this, I ſhall grant likewiſe, That Schiſm is frequently the Effect of Uncharitableneſs, which perhaps was all that <hi>honeſt</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> meant, when he call d it <hi>formalis ratio.</hi> People are ſometimes froward and peeviſh, and apt to take Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> at little things; and when they are <hi>once</hi> angry, and out of charity will forſake the beſt friends in the world (tho perhaps <hi>for worſe Company</hi>); And the new Acquaintance, if he be not very dull, will be ready enough, for his own advantage, to find out Suggeſtions, true or falſe to <hi>confirm</hi> and <hi>improve</hi> the Quarrel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:96210:41"/>Again, Uncharitableneſs is otherwiſe the Effect of Schiſm, when People have no way to juſtifie their Separation from an Orthodox Church, and to ſupport and propagate the Cauſe which they have engaged in, but by vilifying and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing its Members, and abuſing every thing that belongs to its Communion: And when by the long continuance of theſe Practices, they have ſo far wrought upon their own belief, as to think thoſe Objections right, which at firſt were only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up to ſerve a Paſſion, or Deſign; and that both Perſons and Things are really as bad as they have been us'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent 'em: When they look upon others as the Enemies of God, and Oppoſers of his pure Worſhip, as Reprobates, and Damn'd themſelves and Hinderers of the Salvation of others. It is no wonder if they make no Scruple of the moſt Violent and Uncharitable Practices: Eſpecially when Ambition, Covetouſneſs, and Vain-Glory go along with theſe Conceits.</p>
            <p>And yet in the very height of Violence and Cruelty, it will be no mean Task to perſwade 'em, That they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, nor conſequently Schiſmaticks in Mr. <hi>H s</hi> Notion; For Charity is ſeated in the heart, which no Man can look into; and therefore the breach of it not otherwiſe Viſible than by outward Practices. And as to thoſe, be they never ſo Villainous, yet it is in vain to object 'em<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted under the Patronage of a Rjghteous Cauſe, and alſo with a great Appearance of Devotion and Sobriety. If you are robb'd and plunder'd by One of theſe People, you are not to call him a Thief, or to ſay, he was Uncharitable, for thus undoing his poor Neighbour; for it was only the ſpoiling of an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> or, in another Phraſe, the weakening of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If they kill you, it cannot be Murder, ſo long as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Phineas</hi> ſtands upon Record.</p>
            <p>Or if he deſtroys his Prince, yet if he can but once paſs <hi>Tyburne,</hi> he's no Traytor; there is Scripture enough, as he thinks, to diſcharge him from that Guilt. And as for the more puny Inſtances of Uncharitableneſs; ſuch as Lying and Slandering, and raiſing Tumults, and the moſt Grave and Solemn Perjuries, to promote the Cauſe, either the Love of Good Men, or Zeal for Reformation, will eaſily excuſe 'em among Friends: And to prevent Scandal among other People, if they be done one Day, they may be denied the next.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:96210:41"/>If any Tradeſman appears more than ordinary in Defence of the Church, no Schiſmatick is to have any Dealing with him; and if you ſay, he is Uncharitable, he tells you, No, ſurely! He has the Management of his own Purfe, and may lay out his Money where he pleaſes. If any injur'd Catholick goes about to Right himſelf in a Court of Judicature, get a Jury of <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and he is ſo far from obtaining any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, or Benefit of Law, that he is ſure to be Condemn'd. And if you ſay, the Jury was Unjuſt, they will bring their Action. — Take Warning by your Neighbour; for they went according to their Conſciences, and you are not to queſtion their Reputation. If any Clergyman appears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 'em, in Defence of the Church, it ſhall be their whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uſineſs to make him Odious, to expoſe his Faults, in caſe he be any way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>noxious; which Charity would rather co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and by Detraction and Calumny, to leſſen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prave the Character of the moſt Excellent Perſons. If he be of a Grave and Reſerv d Converſation, they ſhall accuſe him of Pride; if more chearful and free, he ſhall be Reputed Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute; if Thrifty, Covetous; if Liberal and Charitable, it ſhall be ſaid, that he does it out of Vain-Glory, or the hopes of Merit: And if he be more than ordinarily ſtrict in the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Faſting and Prayer, he ſhall be reckon'd Superſtitious, and the beſt Title he can obtain, will be that of a very great Formaliſt In fine, be they Clergy, or Lay-people, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Schiſmatick, he that either manages the Faction, or hates the Church, will never ſpeak well of 'em, where he can find the leaſt Occaſion, or pretence to ſpeak ill.</p>
            <p>And, as in all theſe Inſtances, the Charge of Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is confidently evaded, ſo I would know of theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, how Schiſm, in their <hi>Notion,</hi> may be diſcover'd, ſo as that a Diſſenter may be Convicted, if he be really Guilty: For if it be one of the <hi>blackeſt Crimes, the Arch-Rebel of all in Chriſt's Kingdom,</hi> it is very fit that it ſhould be reprov'd and diſcountenanc'd. But I cannot ſee how this can be done, till we firſt know how to fix it upon particular Perſons, We deſire theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re a plain Anſwer:</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, by what Rules that is to be done?</p>
            <p>And Secondly, Whether thoſe who are concern d in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention d, and ſuch like Practices, are not real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y Schiſmaticks? For if they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we hope that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and the reſt of his Way, who boaſt what Power they have within themſelves to Admoniſh, Suſpend, and Reject Scandalous Perſons; will ſo order the matter that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be no ſuch People in any
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96210:42"/>
of their Congregations. For otherwiſe, if we ſee a Book written to prove Uncharitableneſs to be Schiſm, and the Crime of Schiſm therein aggravated to the higheſt degree, and yet the Author's own Congregation crowded with Uncharitable People, what can we think of the Diſcourſe, but that it was all meer bant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r; And that all the Power of Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they ſo eagerly challenge, is to be employ'd only for the Advantage of the Conventicle, but never againſt any of thoſe Practices, though never ſo violent or ſcandalous, that ſerve to promote its Intereſt.</p>
            <p>What he ſays to p. 40. has been already Anſwer'd, as far as it is material; And there ends his Vindication of Mr. <hi>H's No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> So that having examin d him hitherto <hi>with as much Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> as he did <hi>T. W.</hi> I ſhall purſue him no further, hoping that I need not trouble my ſelf about the Remarks on either ſide.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96210:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
